import { Question } from '../types';

export const CRIMINAL_LAW_QUESTIONS: Question[] = [
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 1,
        "Question": "Principles of public international law exempt certain individuals from the Generality characteristic of criminal law. Who among the following are NOT exempt from the Generality rule?  (A) Ministers Resident (B) Commercial Attache of a foreign country (C) Ambassador (D) Chiefs of Mission",
        "Answer": "Commercial Attache of a foreign country"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 2,
        "Question": "The maxim Nullum crimen nula poena sine lege means that  (A) the act is criminal at the time of its commission and recognized as such at the time of its commission but the penalty therefor is prescribed in a subsequently enacted law. (B) the act is criminal and punished under and pursuant to common law. (C) there is a crime for as long as the act is inherently evil. (D)crime is a product of the law.",
        "Answer": "crime is a product of the law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 3,
        "Question": "When a penal law is absolutely repealed such that the offense is decriminalized, a pending case charging the accused of the repealed crime is to be  (A) prosecuted still since the charge was valid when filed. (B) dismissed without any precondition. (C) dismissed provided the accused is not a habitual delinquent. (D) prosecuted still since the offended party has a vested interest in the repealed law.",
        "Answer": "(B) dismissed without any precondition."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 4,
        "Question": "It is a matter of judicial knowledge that certain individuals will kill others or commit serious offenses for no reason at all. For this reason,  (A) lack of motive can result in conviction where the crime and the accused's part in it are shown. (B) motive is material only where there is no evidence of criminal intent. (C) lack of motive precludes conviction. (D) the motive of an offender is absolutely immaterial.",
        "Answer": "lack of motive can result in conviction where the crime and the accused's part in it are shown."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 5,
        "Question": "Motive is generally IMMATERIAL in determining criminal liability EXCEPT when  (A) several offenders committed the crime but the court wants to ascertain which of them acted as leader. (B) the evidence of the crime consists of both direct and circumstantial evidence. (C)ascertaining the degree of penalty that may be imposed on the offender. (D) the evidence of guilt of the accused is circumstantial.",
        "Answer": "the evidence of guilt of the accused is circumstantial."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 6,
        "Question": "X inflicted serious injuries on Y. Because of delay in providing medical treatment to Y, he died. Is X criminally liable for the death of Y?  (A) Yes because the delay did not break the causal connection between X's felonious act and the injuries sustained by Y. (B) Yes because any intervening cause between the infliction of injury and death is immaterial. (C)No because the infliction of injury was not the immediate cause of the death. (D)No because the delay in the administration of the medical treatment was an intervening cause.",
        "Answer": "Yes because the delay did not break the causal connection between X's felonious act and the injuries sustained by Y."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 7,
        "Question": "X inflicted violent kicks on vital parts of E's body. E nevertheless was able to flee for fear of his life. Refusing to undergo treatment for his injuries, E died 3 days later. Is X liable for E’s death?  (A) No, since kicks on the body cannot cause death. (B) No, since it took too long for death to occur. (C) Yes, since E cannot be compelled to undergo medical treatment. (D) Yes, since it was a natural result of the injuries X inflicted on E.",
        "Answer": "Yes, since it was a natural result of the injuries X inflicted on E."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 8,
        "Question": "What court has jurisdiction when an Indonesian crew murders the Filipino captain on board a vessel of Russian registry while the vessel is anchored outside the breakwaters of the Manila bay?  (A) The Indonesian court. (B) The Russian court. (C) The Philippine court. (D) Any court that first asserts jurisdiction over the case.",
        "Answer": "The Philippine court."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 9,
        "Question": "Distinguish crimes mala in se from crimes mala prohibita.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "(a) Mala in se and mala prohibita are distinguished as follows: (1) Mala in Se are inherently wrong or immoral, while mala prohibitia are not inherently wrong; they are only wrong because they are prohibited by law; (2) In mala in se, good faith or lack of criminal intent is a defense, while in mala prohibita, good faith is not a defense; (3) Modifying circumstances can be appreciated in mala in se. These circumstances cannot be appreciated in mala prohibitia, unless the special law that punishes them adopts the technical nomenclature of the penalties of the Revised Penal Code; (4) Mala in se are punishable under the Revised Penal Code; or special laws where the acts punishable therein are wrong by nature. Mala prihibita are punishable under special laws."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 10,
        "Question": "Choose from the list below the correct principle in considering motive.  (A) If the evidence is merely circumstantial, proof of motive is essential. (B) Generally, proof of motive is not necessary to pin a crime on the accused if the commission of the crime has been proven and the evidence of identification is convincing. (C) Motive is important to ascertain the truth between two antagonistic theories. (D) Motive is relevant if the identity of the accused is uncertain. (E) All of the above are correct.",
        "Answer": "All of the above are correct."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 11,
        "Question": "When are light felonies punishable?  a) Light felonies are punishable in all stages of execution. b) Light felonies are punishable only when consummated. c) Light felonies are punishable only when consummated, with the exception of those committed against persons or property. d) Light felonies are punishable only when committed against persons or property.",
        "Answer": "Light felonies are punishable only when consummated, with the exception of those committed against persons or property."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 12,
        "Question": "What is the doctrine of pro reo? How does it relate to Article 48 of the Revised Penal Code?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The doctrine of pro reo advocates that penal laws and laws penal in nature are to be construed and applied in a way lenient or liberal to the offender, consonant to and consistent with the constitutional guarantee that an accused shall be presumed innocent until his guilt is established beyond reasonable doubt. Following the pro reo doctrine, under Art. 48 of the Revised Penal Code, crimes are complexed and punished with a single penalty (i.e that prescribed for the most serious crime and to be imposed in its maximum period). The rationale being, that the accused who commits two crimes with single criminal impulse demonstrates lesser perversity than when the crimes are committed by different acts and several criminal resolutions. (People v. Comadre, 431 SCRA 366, 384 [2004}. However, Art. 48 shall be applied only when it would bring about the imposition of a penalty lesser than the penalties imposable for all the component crimes if prosecuted separately instead of being complexed."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 13,
        "Question": "The acquittal of an accused shall bar the civil action arising from the crime where the judgment of acquittal holds that __________.  (A) the acquittal is based on reasonable doubt (B) the liability of the accused is not criminal but civil in nature (C) the civil liability does not arise from or is not based on the criminal act for which the accused has been acquitted (D) the accused did not commit the act imputed to him",
        "Answer": "the accused did not commit the act imputed to him"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 14,
        "Question": "Subsidiary liability may be imposed on the following, except __________.  (A) innkeepers, in relation to the crime committed in their establishment (B) employers engaged in industry, for the crime committed by their employees (C) parents of minors who act with discernment in committing crimes  (D) hospital administrators or owners, for crimes committed by their hospital nurses",
        "Answer": "hospital administrators or owners, for crimes committed by their hospital nurses"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 15,
        "Question": "Luis was sentenced to prision mayor and to pay a fine of P50,000.00, with subsidiary imprisonment in case of insolvency. Is the sentence correct?  (A) Yes, because Luis has no property to pay for the fine, so he must suffer the equivalent imprisonment provided by law in lieu of fine. (B) No, because subsidiary imprisonment is applicable only when the penalty imposed is prision correccional or below. (C)Yes, because the sentence says so. (D)No, because the subsidiary imprisonment is applicable only when the penalty imposed is limited to a fine. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "No, because subsidiary imprisonment is applicable only when the penalty imposed is prision correccional or below."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 16,
        "Question": "The death of the accused extinguishes his criminal liability but civil liability is not extinguished.  (A) when the death of the accused occurred before conviction (B) when the death of the accused occurred after conviction and after he has perfected his appeal from conviction (C) when the death of the accused occurred during the pendency of his appeal (D) when the death of the accused occurred after final judgment (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "when the death of the accused occurred after final judgment"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 17,
        "Question": "Dang was a beauty queen in a university. Job, a rich classmate, was so enamored with her that he persistently wooed and pursued her. Dang, being in love with another man, rejected him. This angered Job. Sometime in September 2003, while Dang and her sister Lyn were on their way home, Job and his minor friend Nonoy grabbed them and pushed them inside a white van. They brought them in an abandoned warehouse where they forced them to dance naked. Thereafter, they brought them to a hill in a nearby barangay where they took turns raping them. After satisfying their lust, Job ordered Nonoy to push Dang down a ravine, resulting in her death. Lyn ran away but Job and Nonoy chased her and pushed her inside the van. Then the duo drove away. Lyn was never seen again. (Is the body of the victim, Lyn, required to establish the corpus delicti for kidnapping/murder?)",
        "Answer": "No. The corpus delicti or fact of commission of the crime is clear. Even the death of Lyn may be established from the acts of the culprits, without the need of the body of Lyn being presented."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 18,
        "Question": "The police officer in civilian clothes asked X where he can buy shabu. X responded by asking the officer how much of the drug he needed. When he told him, X left, returned after a few minutes with the shabu, gave it to the officer, and took his money. X is  (A) liable for selling since the police operation was a valid entrapment. (B) not liable for selling since the police operation was an invalid entrapment. (C) liable for selling since the police operation was a valid form of instigation. (D) not liable since the police operation was an invalid instigation.",
        "Answer": "liable for selling since the police operation was a valid entrapment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 19,
        "Question": "X, without intent to kill, aimed his gun at Z and fired it, hitting the latter who died as a consequence. Under the circumstances  (A) X cannot plead praetor intentionem since the intent to kill is presumed from the killing of the victim. (B) X may plead praetor intentionem since he intended only to scare, not kill Z. (C)X may plead aberratio ictus as he had no intention to hit Z. (D)X may plead commission of only Discharge of Firearm as he had no intent to kill Z when he fired his gun.",
        "Answer": "X may plead praetor intentionem since he intended only to scare, not kill Z."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 20,
        "Question": "Ando, an Indonesian national who just visited the Philippines, purchased a ticket for a passenger vessel bound for Hong Kong. While on board the vessel, he saw his mortal enemy Iason, also an Indonesian national, seated at the back portion of the cabin and who was busy reading a newspaper. Ando stealthily approached Iason and when he was near him, Ando stabbed and killed Iason. The vessel is registered in Malaysia. The killing happened just a few moments after the vessel left the port of Manila. Operatives from the PNP Maritime Command arrested Ando. Presented for the killing of Iason, Ando contended that he did not incur criminal liability because both he and the victim were Indonesians. He likewise argued that he could not be prosecuted in Manila because the vessel is a Malaysian-registered ship. Discuss the merits of Ando's contentions. ",
        "Answer": "Both contentions of Ando lack merit. The argument of Ando that he did not incur criminal liability because both he and the victim were Indonesians is not tenable. Under the generality principle, penal laws shall be obligatory upon all who live or sojourn in the Philippine territory (Article 14 of the Civil Code). The foreign characteristic of an offender and offended party does not exclude him from operation of penal laws (People v. Galacgac, C.A., 54 O.G. 1027). Under the Revised Penal Code, except as provided in treaties and laws of preferential application, penal laws of the Philippines shall have force and effect within its territory. Here, since the killing took place within the Philippine territory, our penal laws applies and Ando may be held criminally responsible despite his being and Indonesian citizen. Likewise, the contention of Ando that he could not be prosecuted in Manila because the vessel is a Malaysian- registered ship is without merit. Under the English Rule, which our jurisdiction recognizes and follows, crimes committed aboard a vessel within the territorial waters of a country are triable in the courts of such country except when crimes merely affect things within the vessel or when they only refer to the internal management thereof. Here, since the crime was committed within the Philippine waters and neither exception applies, Ando may be prosecuted in Manila. (ADDITIONAL ANSWER: Under Section 27 of the Convention of the Law of The Sea, the criminal jurisdiction of the coastal State should not be exercised on board a foreign ship passing through the territorial sea to arrest any person or to conduct any investigation in connection with any crime committed on board the ship during its passage except if the crime is of a kind to disturb the peace of the country or the good order of the territorial sea. The vessel is still within the territorial waters of the Philippines when the crime was committed since the killing happened a few moments after the vessel left the port of Manila. Murder committed by Ando disturbs the peace of the Philippines; hence, he could be prosecuted in Manila.)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 21,
        "Question": "Which of the following crimes is an exception to the Territoriality Rule in Criminal law?  (A) Violation of the Trademark Law committed by an alien in the Philippines. (B) Forgery of US bank notes committed in the Philippines. (C) Crime committed by a Filipino in the disputed Spratly's Island. (D) Plunder committed at his place of assignment abroad by a Philippine public officer.",
        "Answer": "Plunder committed at his place of assignment abroad by a Philippine public officer."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 22,
        "Question": "When committed outside the Philippine territory, our courts DO NOT have jurisdiction over the crime of  (A) treason. (B) piracy. (C) espionage. (D) rebellion.",
        "Answer": "rebellion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 23,
        "Question": "Pierce is a French diplomat stationed in the Philippines. While on EDSA and driving with an expired license, he hit a pedestrian who was crossing illegally. The pedestrian died. Pierce was charged with reckless imprudence resulting in homicide. In his defense, he claimed diplomatic immunity. Is Pierce correct? ",
        "Answer": "Yes, Pierce is correct. Pierce, being a French diplomat stationed in the Philippines, would be exempt from the general application of our criminal laws, as provided for under laws or treaties of preferential application, more particularly under R.A. 75."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 24,
        "Question": "A foreigner residing in Hong Kong counterfeits a twenty-peso bill issued by the Philippine Government. May the foreigner be prosecuted before a civil court in the Philippines?  a) No. The provisions of the Revised Penal Code are enforceable only within the Philippine Archipelago. b) No. The Philippine Criminal Law is binding only on persons who reside or sojourn in the Philippines. c) No. Foreigners residing outside the jurisdiction of the Philippines are exempted from the operation of the Philippine Criminal Law. d) Yes. The provisions of the Revised Penal Code are enforceable also outside the jurisdiction of the Philippines against those who should forge or counterfeit currency notes of the Philippines or obligations and securities issued by the Government of the Philippines.",
        "Answer": "Yes. The provisions of the Revised Penal Code are enforceable also outside the jurisdiction of the Philippines against those who should forge or counterfeit currency notes of the Philippines or obligations and securities issued by the Government of the Philippines."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 25,
        "Question": "Distinguish between ex post facto law and bill of attainder. ",
        "Answer": "Ex post facto law is any law which makes an innocent act a crime after the act was committed. It is a Latin phrase which means “from something done afterwards.” It could also be a law which aggravates a crime, or makes it greater than when it was committed, or which changes the punishment and inflicts a greater penalty than the law governing the crime when committed. A bill of attainder is a law which inflicts punishment on a named individual or a group of individuals without judicial trial. Ex post facto law pertains to the act while a bill of attainder pertains to a named individual or to members of a group."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 26,
        "Question": "Congress passed a law reviving the Anti-Subversion Law, making it a criminal offense again for a person to join the Communist Party of the Philippines. Reporma, a former high-ranking member of the Communist Party, was charged under the new law for his membership in the Communist Party when he was a student in the 80’s. He now challenges the charge against him. What objections may he raise? ",
        "Answer": "Reporma may raise the limitations imposed by the 1987 Constitution on the power of Congress to enact retroactive penal laws which are prejudicial to the accused. Under the Bill of Rights of the Constitution such is classified as an ex post facto law. It should be noted that when Congress decriminalized the crime of subversion, under R.A. 7637, it obliterated the felony and its effects upon Reporma. Consequently charging him now under the new law for his previous membership in the Communist Party would be constitutionality impermissible."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 27,
        "Question": "What are the constitutional provisions limiting the power of Congress to enact penal laws? ",
        "Answer": "The constitutional provisions limiting the power of Congress to enact penal laws are the following: 1. The law must not be an ex post facto law or it should not be given a retroactive effect. 2. The law must not be a bill of attainder, meaning it cannot provide punishment without judicial process. 3. The law must not impose cruel, unusual or degrading punishment. 4. No person shall be held to answer for a criminal offense without due process of law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 28,
        "Question": "Assume that you are a member of the legal staff of Senator Salcedo who wants to file a bill about imprisonment at the National Penitentiary in Muntinlupa. He wants to make the State prison a revenue earner for the country through a law providing for premium accommodations for prisoners (other than those under maximum security status) whose wives are allowed conjugal weekend visits, and for those who want long-term premium accommodations. For conjugal weekenders, he plans to rent out rooms with hotel-like amenities at rates equivalent to those charged by 4-star hotels; for long-term occupants, he is prepared to offer room and board with special meals in air conditioned single-occupancy rooms, at rates equivalent to those charged by 3-star hotels. What advice will you give the Senator from the point of view of criminal law, taking into account the purpose of imprisonment (7%) and considerations of ethics and morality ? ",
        "Answer": "I would advise Senator Salcedo not to file the said bill. First, the bill is unconstitutional as it violates the equal protection clause of the Constitution. It will create economic inequality in our criminal justice system. Rich prisoners will enjoy better amenities and privileges than those who are poor. Second, the bill will defeat the purpose of penalties in criminal law, which is to secure justice, retribution, and reformation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 29,
        "Question": "How are felonies committed? Explain each. ",
        "Answer": "Felonies are committed not only by means of deceit (dolo) but also by means of fault (culpa). There is deceit when the act is performed with deliberate intent; and there is fault when the wrongful act results from imprudence, negligence, lack of foresight, or lack of skill (Article 3 of Revised Penal Code)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 30,
        "Question": "What is aberration ictus? ",
        "Answer": "Aberratio ictus means mistake of blow. Under the principle of aberratio ictus, a person is criminally responsible for committing an intentional felony although the consequent victim is different from that intended due to mistake of blow. This principle is based on the rule in Article 4 of the Revised Penal Code, which provides that criminal liability shall be incurred by any person committing a felony (delito) although the wrongful act done be different from that which he intended."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 31,
        "Question": "Felonies are classified according to manner or mode of execution into felonies committed by means of deceit (dolo) and by means of fault (culpa). Which of the following causes may not give rise to culpable felonies?  a) Imprudence; b) Malice; c) Negligence; d) Lack of foresight.",
        "Answer": "Malice;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 32,
        "Question": "The classification of felonies into grave, less grave, and light is important in ascertaining  (A) if certain crimes committed on the same occasion can be complexed. (B) the correct penalty for crimes committed through reckless imprudence. (C) whether the offender is liable as an accomplice. (D) what stage of the felony has been reached.",
        "Answer": "what stage of the felony has been reached."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 33,
        "Question": "Is the penalty for impossible crime applicable to one who attempts to commit a light felony of impossible materialization?  a) No. The evil intent of the offender cannot be accomplished. b) No. An attempt to commit light felony constitutes an employment of inadequate or ineffectual means. c) No. The penalty for consummated light felony is less than the penalty for impossible crime. d) No. In impossible crime, the act performed should not constitute a violation of another offense.",
        "Answer": "No. In impossible crime, the act performed should not constitute a violation of another offense."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 34,
        "Question": "DO, intending to kill EE, peppered the latter's bedroom with bullets, but since the intended victim was not home at that time, no harm came to him. What crime is committed?  a) DO committed the crime of attempted murder. b) DO committed the crime of attempted homicide. c) DO committed the crime of impossible crime. d) DD committed the crime of malicious mischief.",
        "Answer": "DO committed the crime of impossible crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 35,
        "Question": "Can there be a frustrated impossible crime?  a) Yes. When the crime is not produced by reason of the inherent impossibility of its accomplishment, it is a frustrated impossible crime. b) No. There can be no frustrated impossible crime because the means employed to accomplish the crime is inadequate or ineffectual. c) Yes. There can be a frustrated impossible crime when the act performed would be an offense against persons. d) No. There can be no frustrated impossible crime because the offender has already performed the acts for the execution of the crime.",
        "Answer": "No. There can be no frustrated impossible crime because the means employed to accomplish the crime is inadequate or ineffectual."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 36,
        "Question": "Puti detested Pula, his roommate, because Pula was courting Ganda, whom Puti fancied. One day, Puti decided to teach Pula a lesson and went to a veterinarian (Vet) to ask for poison on the pretext that he was going to kill a sick pet, when actually Puti was intending to poison Pula. The Vet instantly gave Puti a non-toxic solution which, when mixed with Pula’s food, did not kill Pula. What crime, if any, did Puti commit? ",
        "Answer": "Puti committed the impossible crime of murder. All the elements of an impossible crime are present. Puti’s act of mixing a solution with Pula’s food would have been murder, a crime against persons. The act was done evil intent which is to kill Pula. However, the crime was not accomplished because of the employment of ineffectual means, i.e., the solution turned out to be non-toxic which would not kill Pula. And said act would not fall under any other provision of the RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 37,
        "Question": "Puti detested Pula, his roommate... [He tried to poison Pula using a non-toxic solution]. Would your answer be the same if, as a result of the mixture, Pula got an upset stomach and had to be hospitalized for 10 days? ",
        "Answer": "No, my answer would not be the same. If as a result of the mixture, Pula got an upset stomach and had to be hospitalized for 10 days, the crime committed by Puti is Less Serious Physical Injuries. It is not an impossible crime because the last element of an impossible requires that the act performed should not constitute a violation of another provision of the RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 38,
        "Question": "Carla, four (4) years old, was kidnapped by Enrique... Enrique wrote a ransom note demanding... P500,000.00 ransom... before the ransom note could be received... Enrique’s hideout was discovered by the police. Carla was rescued while Enrique was arrested. The prosecutor considered that the ransom note was never received... and filed a case of “Impossible crime to commit kidnapping” against Enrique. Is the prosecutor correct? If he is not correct, can he instead file a case of grave coercion? ",
        "Answer": "The Prosecutor is not correct. There is no “Impossible crime to commit kidnapping”. First, an impossible crime applies only to Crimes against Persons and Crimes against Property under Titles 8 and 10 of the RPC, respectively. Kidnapping is a Crime against Personal Liberty and Security under Title 9, RPC. Second, even if the ransom note was not received by Carla’s parents, the crime of kidnapping and serious illegal detention for ransom is already consummated. Under Article 267, RPC, Kidnapping for Ransom is committed “when the kidnapping or detention is for the purpose of extorting ransom from the victim or any other person.” To consummate the crime, it suffices that the purpose is to extort ransom; it is not necessary that the ransom note be received or that ransom be paid. No, the Prosecutor cannot file a case of grave coercion because the crime committed, as explained above, is kidnapping for ransom."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 39,
        "Question": "Charlie hated his classmate, Brad... Charlie went to a veterinarian and asked for some poison... Actually, Charlie intended to use the poison on Brad. The veterinarian mistakenly gave Charlie a non-toxic powder which, when mixed with Brad's food, did not kill Brad. Did Charlie commit any crime? If so; what and why? If not, why not?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Charlie committed an impossible crime of murder. His act of mixing the non-toxic powder with Brad's food, done with intent to kill, would have constituted murder which is a crime against persons, had it not been for the employment of a means which, unknown to him, is ineffectual (Art.4, par. 2, RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 40,
        "Question": "Would your answer be the same if, instead of killing Brad, Brad proved to be allergic to the powder, and after ingesting it with his food, fell ill and was hospitalized for ten (10) days? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, the answer would not be the same. Charlie would be, criminally liable for less serious physical injuries because his act of mixing the powder with Brad's food was done with felonious intent and was the proximate cause of Brad's illness for 10 days. It cannot constitute attempted murder, although done with intent to kill, because the means employed is inherently ineffectual to cause death and the crime committed must be directly linked to the means employed, not to the intent. Liability for an impossible crime can only arise from a consummated act."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 41,
        "Question": "In an attempted felony, the offender’s preparatory act  (A) itself constitutes an offense. (B) must seem connected to the intended crime. (C) must not be connected to the intended crime. (D) requires another act to result in a felony.",
        "Answer": "requires another act to result in a felony."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 42,
        "Question": "Delmo learned that his enemy, Oscar, was confined at the Intensive Care Unit (ICU)... Intending to kill Oscar, Delmo disguised himself as a nurse, entered the ICU, and saw a man lying on the hospital bed... Delmo disconnected the tubes and left... The patient survived. It turned out that the patient was Larry... Delmo was charged with frustrated murder, qualified by evident premeditation and treachery as aggravating circumstances. Discuss the propriety of the charge. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Delmo was correctly charged with the crime of frustrated murder qualified by treachery—not evident premeditation because the victim was different from the one premeditated against. Delmo has performed all the acts of execution that would produce the death of the victim but for reasons independent of the will of the perpetrator, the death of the victim was not accomplished. Treachery qualifies the crime, because the means, manner and method of committing the intended killing were consciously adopted to insure its execution without risk that may arise from the defense the victim may make. Evident premeditation is absorbed in the treachery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 43,
        "Question": "Define wheel conspiracy and chain conspiracy. Is either or both kinds existent herein? Explain your answer. (The scenario involves Mr. Gangnam giving gifts to public officers Datu, Diva, and Dolor for a government contract/overpriced project.) (4%) (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "In the case at bar, both type of conspiracy exists. The distribution of commissions or gifts by Mr. Gangnam and the acceptance of Governor Datu, Bokal Diva, Mayor Dolor is a type of wheel conspiracy where a single person, Mr. Gangnam, dealt individually with the public officials to commit the overt acts. The chain conspiracy, on the other hand, is evident in the overpricing of the sports complex through the facilitation of Bokal Diva, the conclusion of the agreements by Mayor Dolor, and the distribution of the gifts by Mr. Gangnam."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 44,
        "Question": "Proposal to commit felony is punishable only in cases in which the law specifically provides a penalty therefor. Under which of the following instances are proponents NOT liable?  a) Proposal to commit coup d'etat. b) Proposal to commit sedition. c) Proposal to commit rebellion. d) Proposal to commit treason.",
        "Answer": "Proposal to commit sedition."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 45,
        "Question": "A proposal to commit a felony is punishable only when the law specifically provides a penalty for it as in the case of proposal to commit  (A) rebellion. (B) sedition. (C) espionage. (D) highway robbery.",
        "Answer": "rebellion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 46,
        "Question": "Conspiracy to commit felony is punishable only in cases in which the law specifically provides a penalty therefor. Under which of the following instances are the conspirators not liable?  a) Conspiracy to commit arson. b) Conspiracy to commit terrorism. c) Conspiracy to commit child pornography. d) Conspiracy to commit trafficking in persons.",
        "Answer": "Conspiracy to commit arson."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 47,
        "Question": "Define conspiracy. ",
        "Answer": "Conspiracy exists when two or more persons come to an agreement concerning the commission of a felony and decide to commit it."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 48,
        "Question": "Distinguish by way of illustration conspiracy as a felony from conspiracy as a manner of incurring liability in relation to the crimes of rebellion and murder. ",
        "Answer": "Conspiracy to commit rebellion – if “A” and “B” conspired to overthrow the government, conspiracy is punishable. Conspiracy to commit rebellion is a felony. Rebellion – if they committed rebellion, they are equally liable for the crime of rebellion. However, they will not be additionally charged with conspiracy to commit rebellion. Since they committed what they conspired, conspiracy will not be considered as an independent felony but as a manner of incurring criminal responsibility. Conspiracy to commit homicide, not punishable – if “A” and “B” conspire to kill “X”, conspiracy is not punishable. The law provides no penalty for conspiracy to be commit homicide. Homicide – if pursuant to conspiracy to commit homicide, “A” embraced “X” and then “B” stabbed and killed “X”, the conspirators are equally liable for homicide. Conspirators are equally liable for homicide. Conspiracy in this case will be considered as a manner of incurring liability."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 49,
        "Question": "Conspiracy to commit a felony is punishable only in cases where the law specifically provides a penalty. Which of the following combinations contain specific felonies under the Revised Penal Code?  (A) Conspiracy to commit treason, conspiracy to commit rebellion, conspiracy to commit coup d'etat, conspiracy to commit misprision of treason. (B) Conspiracy to commit rebellion, conspiracy to commit coup d'etat, conspiracy to commit treason, conspiracy to commit sedition. (C) Conspiracy to commit rebellion or insurrection, conspiracy to commit sedition, conspiracy to commit illegal assemblies, conspiracy to commit treason. (D) Conspiracy to commit treason, conspiracy to commit sedition, conspiracy to commit terrorism. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "Conspiracy to commit rebellion, conspiracy to commit coup d'etat, conspiracy to commit treason, conspiracy to commit sedition."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 50,
        "Question": "Define maifeasance, misfeasance and nonfeasance.  ",
        "Answer": "“Malfeasance” is the doing of an act which a person ought not to do at all. “Misfeasance” is the improper doing of an act which a person mayor might lawfully do. “Nonfeasance” is the omission of an act which a person ought to do. — (Black’s Dictionary, 6th Edition, West Publishing 1990)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 51,
        "Question": "Differentiate wheel conspiracy and chain conspiracy.  ",
        "Answer": "There are two structures of multiple conspiracies, namely: wheel or circle conspiracy and chain conspiracy. A “wheel conspiracy” occurs when there is a single person or group (the hub) dealing individually with two or more other persons or groups (the spokes). The spoke typically interacts with the hub rather than with another spoke. In the event that the spoke shares a common purpose to succeed; there is a single conspiracy. However, in the instances when each spoke is unconcerned with the success of the other spokes, there are multiple conspiracies. A “chain conspiracy”, on the other hand, exists when there is successive communication and cooperation in much the same way as with legitimate business operations between manufacturer and wholesaler, then wholesaler and retailer, and then retailer and consumer (Estrada v. Sandiganbayan, G.R. No. 148965, February 26, 2002)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 52,
        "Question": "Who is a habitual delinquent? Distinguish habitual delinquency from recidivism as to the crimes committed, the period of time the crimes are committed, the number of crimes committed and their effects in relation to the penalty to be imposed on a convict. ",
        "Answer": "A person shall be deemed to be habitual delinquent, if within a period of ten years from the date of his release or last conviction of the crimes of serious or less serious physical injuries, robo, hurto estafa or falsification, he is found guilty of any of said crimes a third time or oftener (Art. 62, RPC). The following are the differences between recidivism and habitual delinquency: RECIDIVISM: Nature of crime: First crime and the aggravated second crime are embraced in the same Title of the RPC. Time element: Accused was convicted of the first crime by final judgment at the time of the trial of the second crime. Number of crimes: At least two crimes committed. Nature of the aggravating circumstance: Ordinary aggravating circumstance the presence of any of which will trigger the application of the penalty for the second crime committed in its maximum period unless it is off-set by a mitigating circumstance. HABITUAL DELINQUENCY: Nature of crime: First, second and third crimes must be a habitual delinquency crime, that is, serious or less serious physical injuries, theft, robbery, estafa or falsification of document. Time element: The accused was convicted of first habitual delinquency crime; within ten years after conviction or release, he was found guilty or habitual-delinquency crime for the second time; within 10 years after conviction or release, he was found guilty of habitual-delinquency crime for the third time or oftener. Number of crimes: At least three crimes committed. Nature of the aggravating circumstance: Extraordinary or special aggravating circumstance, the presence of which will trigger the imposition of additional penalty for the third or subsequent crime. This is not subject of the off-set rule."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 53,
        "Question": "During trial for theft in 2014, the prosecution managed to show that accused AA has also been convicted by final judgment for robbery in 2003... A subsequent verification showed that AA had several convictions, to wit: 1. In 1998, she was convicted of estafa; 2. In 2002, she was convicted of theft; 3. In 2004, she was convicted of frustrated homicide; The judge trying the theft case in 2014 is about to convict AA. What circumstances affecting the liability or penalty may the judge appreciate against AA? ",
        "Answer": "The judge may appreciate the aggravating circumstance of recidivism. A recidivist is one who, at the time of his trial for one crime, shall have been previously convicted by final judgment of another crime embraced in the same title of the RPC. Robbery, theft, estafa are crimes against property embraced in Title Ten of the RPC. The judge may also appreciate the aggravating circumstance of habituality or reiteracion, because there have been two or more crimes committed for which she has been published, regardless of the degree of penalty."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 54,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Amado, convicted of rape but granted an absolute pardon by the President, and one year thereafter, convicted of homicide, is a recidivist.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "True. Rape is now a crime against persons and, like the crime of homicide, is embraced in the same Title of the Revised Penal Code under which Amado had been previously convicted by final judgment. The absolute pardon granted him for rape, only excused him from serving the sentence for rape but did not erase the effects of the conviction therefore unless expressly remitted by the pardon."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 55,
        "Question": "B was convicted by final judgment of theft. While serving sentence for such offense, B was found in possession of an unlicensed firearm. Is B a quasi-recidivist?  a) B is a quasi-recidivist because he was serving sentence when found in possession of an unlicensed firearm. b) B is not a quasi-recidivist because the offense for which he was serving sentence is different from the second offense. c) B is not a quasi-recidivist because the second offense is not a felony. d) B is not a quasi-recidivist because the second offense was committed while still serving for the first offense.",
        "Answer": "B is a quasi-recidivist because he was serving sentence when found in possession of an unlicensed firearm."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 56,
        "Question": "What is delito continuado?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Delito continuado refers to a crime constituted by several overt acts committed by the offender in one place, at about the same time, and all such overt acts violate one and the same provision of penal law, thus demonstrating that all such acts are the product of a single indivisible criminal resolution. Hence, all said acts are considered as one crime only."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 57,
        "Question": "Angelo devised a Ponzi Scheme in which 500 persons were deceived... Angelo was charged with 500 counts of estafa and 2,000 counts of violation of Batas Pambansa (BP) 22. In his motion to quash, Angelo contends that he committed a continued crime, or delito continuado, hence, he committed only one count of estafa and one count of violation of BP 22. Is Angelo's contention tenable? Explain. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. His contention is not tenable. He committed as many counts of estafa against the 500 victims and 2000 counts of violation of BP 22, since each swindling is achieved through distinct fraudulent machinations contrived at different times or dates, and in different amounts. Moreover, his drawing separate checks payable to each payee is a separate criminal resolution, as they must be of different amounts and of different dates. He acted with separate fraudulent intent against each swindling victim and had distinct criminal intent in drawing and issuing each check. It cannot be maintained that his acts are the product of one criminal resolution only."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 58,
        "Question": "Pedro, Pablito, Juan and Julio, all armed with bolos, robbed the house where Antonio, his wife, and three (3) daughters were residing. While the four were ransacking Antonio’s house, Julio noticed that one of Antonio’s daughters was trying to escape. He chased and caught up with her at a thicket somewhat distant from the house, but before bringing her back, raped her. What crime or crimes, if any, did Pedro, Pablito, Juan and Julio commit? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Julio is liable for special complex crime of robbery with rape since he raped the daughter of Antonio on occasion or by reason of robbery. Even if the place of robbery is different from that of rape, the crime is still robbery with rape since what is important is the direct connection between the two crimes (People v. Conastre, G.R. No. L-2055, December 24, 1948). Rape was not separate by distance and time from the robbery. Pedro, Pablito and Juan are liable for robbery by band. There is band in this case since more than three armed malefactors take part in the commission of a robbery. Under Article 296 of the Revised Penal Code, any member of a band, who is present at the commission of a robbery by the band, shall be punished as principal of any of the assaults committed by the band, unless it be shown that he attempted to prevent the same. The assault mentioned in Article 296 includes rape (People v. Hamiana, G.R. Nos. L-3491-94, May 30, 1971). They are not liable, however, for rape under Article 296 since they were not present when the victim was raped and thus, they had no opportunity to prevent the same. They are only liable for robbery by band (People v. Anticamaray, G.R. No. 178771, June 8, 2011)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 59,
        "Question": "Suppose, after the robbery, the four took turns in raping the three daughters inside the house, and, to prevent identification, killed the whole family just before they left. What crime or crimes, if any, did the four malefactors commit?  ",
        "Answer": "They are liable for a special complex crime of robbery with homicide. In this special complex crime, it is immaterial that several persons are killed. It is also immaterial that aside from the homicides, rapes are committed by reason or on the occasion of the crime. Since homicides are committed by or on the occasion of the robbery, the multiple rapes shall be integrated into one and indivisible felony of robbery with homicide (People v. Diu, G.R. No. 201449, April 3, 2013)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 60,
        "Question": "OFW A hired X, Y and Z to kidnap C and D (C's wife). They kidnapped C and D, took them to a hut, raped D multiple times in front of C, tortured C, and set the hut on fire before leaving, killing both C and D. A surrendered the next day. As the RTC judge, decide what crime or crimes were committed by A, X, Y and Z, and what mitigating and aggravating circumstances will be applied in imposing the penalty. Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "A, X, Y and Z are liable for two counts of kidnapping with murder qualified by means of fire, since C and D were killed in the course of the detention. In a special complex crime of kidnapping with murder, it is immaterial that other crimes were committed such as multiple rapes and arson. Since multiple rapes and arson are committed by reason or on occasion of kidnapping, they shall be integrated into one and indivisible felony of kidnapping with murder (People v. Larranaga, G.R. Nos. 138874-75, January 31, 2004). The mitigating circumstances of passion and voluntary surrender can be appreciated in favor of A. The aggravating circumstances of unlawful entry, by means of fire, and treachery can be appreciated against A, X, Y and Z."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 61,
        "Question": "A police officer surreptitiously placed a marijuana stick in a student’s pocket and then arrested him for possession of marijuana cigarette. What crime can the police officer be charged with?  (A) None, as it is a case of entrapment (B) Unlawful arrest (C) Incriminating an innocent person (D) Complex crime of incriminating an innocent person with unlawful arrest",
        "Answer": "Complex crime of incriminating an innocent person with unlawful arrest"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 62,
        "Question": "A special complex crime is a composite crime  (A) made up of 2 or more crimes defined in the Penal Code. (B) with its own definition and special penalty provided by the Penal Code. (C) with its own definition and special penalty provided by a special penal law. (D) made up of 2 or more crimes defined in the Penal Code and special penal laws.",
        "Answer": "with its own definition and special penalty provided by the Penal Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 63,
        "Question": "X, intending to kill Y, a store owner, fired at Y from the street, but the shot killed not only Y but also Z who was in the store. As a case of aberratio ictus, it is punishable as a  (A) complex crime proper. (B) special complex crime. (C) continuing crime. (D) compound crime.",
        "Answer": "complex crime proper."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 64,
        "Question": "Wenceslao and Loretta were staying in the same boarding house... Wenceslao entered Loretta's room with the use of a picklock... ravished Loretta... stabbed Loretta to death and, before leaving the room, took her jewelry. What crime or crimes, if any, did Wenceslao commit? Explain. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Wenceslao committed the following crimes: (1) the special complex crime of rape with homicide (2) theft and (3) unlawful possession of picklocks and similar tools under Art. 304, RPC. His act of having carnal knowledge of Loretta against her will and with the use of force and violence constituted rape, plus the killing of Loretta by reason or on the occasion of the rape, gave rise to the special complex crime of rape with homicide. Since the taking of the jewelry was an afterthought as it was done only when he was about to leave the room and when Loretta was already dead, the same constitutes theft. His possession and use of the picklock without lawful cause is by itself punishable under Art. 304, RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 65,
        "Question": "Would your answer to the previous question (Q64) be the same if, despite the serious stab wounds she sustained, Loretta survived? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, the answer will be different. In that case, the crimes committed would be four separate crimes of (1) rape (2) frustrated homicide or 'murder (3) theft and (4) unlawful possession and use of picklocks under Art. 304, RPC. The special complex crime of rape with homicide is constituted only when both the rape and the killing are consummated; when one or both of them are not consummated, they are to be charged and punished separately. In any event, the possession of the picklock without lawful cause, more so its use in an unlawful entry is punished as a crime by itself."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 66,
        "Question": "Roger and Jessie, Municipal Mayor and Treasurer... falsified the disbursement vouchers and supporting documents in order to make it appear that qualified recipients who, in fact, are non-existent individuals, received the money. Roger and Jessie are charged with malversation through falsification. Discuss the propriety of the charge filed against Roger and Jessie. Explain. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The charge of malversation through falsification is not correct because the falsifications of several documents were not necessary means to obtain the money that were malversed. The falsifications were committed to cover up or hide the malversation and therefore, should be separately treated from malversation. The given facts state that Roger and Jessie falsified disbursement vouchers and supporting documents in order to make it appear that qualified recipients received the money. Art. 48, RPC on complex crimes is not applicable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 67,
        "Question": "While Alfredo, Braulio, Ciriaco, and Domingo were robbing a bank, policemen arrived. A firefight ensued... and one of the policemen was killed. What crime or crimes, if any, had been committed? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The crimes committed are Robbery with homicide (Art. 294(1], RPC), a single indivisible offense, and Direct Assault with Multiple Attempted Homicide, a complex crime (Art. 48, Art. 148 and Art. 249, RPC; People v. Gayrama, 60 Phil. 796 (1934]). Robbery with Homicide was committed because one of the responding policemen was killed by reason or on occasion of the robbery being committed. The complex crime of Direct Assault with Multiple Attempted Homicide was committed in respect of the offender's firing guns at the responding policemen who are agents of person in authority performing their duty when fired at to frustrate such performance. (People vs. Ladjaalam, G.R. Nos. 136149-51, Sept 19, 2000)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 68,
        "Question": "Suppose it was Alfredo (one of the robbers) who was killed by the responding policemen, what charges can be filed against Braulio, Ciriaco and Domingo? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The crime of which Braulio, Ciriaco and Domingo can be charged is Robbery with Homicide (Art.294, RPC) because the killing resulted by reason or on the occasion, of the robbery. It is of no moment that the person killed is one of the robbers. A killing by reason or on the occasion of the robbery, whether deliberate or accidental, will be a component of the crime of Robbery with Homicide, a single indivisible offense, as long as it is intimately connected to the robbery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 69,
        "Question": "Suppose in the course of the robbery, before the policemen arrived, Braulio shot and killed Alfredo (another robber) following a heated disagreement on who should carry the money bags, what would be the criminal liability of Braulio, Ciriaco and Domingo? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Braulio shall be liable for Robbery with homicide (Art. 294, RPC) for killing Alfredo, since the killing was by reason of the robbery. Ciriaco and Domingo having conspired only in the commission of the robbery, should incur liability only for the crime conspired upon—the robbery, unless they were with Braulio during the killing and could have prevented the same but they did not, in which case they shall also be liable for Robbery with homicide. It is of no moment that the person killed is one of the robbers and he was killed during the robbery (People v, Barot, 89 SCRA 16 [19791)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 70,
        "Question": "Christopher, John, Richard, and Luke... boarded a taxicab, held the driver at gunpoint and took the latter's earnings. What crime, if any, did the four commit if they killed the driver? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The crime becomes robbery with homicide and all the fraternity brothers are liable. The existence of a band shall be appreciated only as generic aggravating circumstance. Also, if the firearms used were unlicensed, the same would only be taken as generic aggravating circumstance as provided by the Rep. Act No. 8294 (People v. Bolinget, G.R. Nos. 137949-52, December 11, 2003)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 71,
        "Question": "The alternative circumstance of relationship shall NOT be considered between  (A) mother-in-law and daughter-in-law. (B) adopted son and legitimate natural daughter. (C) aunt and nephew. (D) stepfather and stepson.",
        "Answer": "adopted son and legitimate natural daughter."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 72,
        "Question": "As a modifying circumstance, insanity  (A) is in the nature of confession and avoidance. (B) may be presumed from the offender’s previous behavior. (C)may be mitigating if its presence becomes apparent subsequent to the commission of the crime. (D)exempts the offender from criminal liability whatever the circumstances.",
        "Answer": "exempts the offender from criminal liability whatever the circumstances."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 73,
        "Question": "A qualifying aggravating circumstance  (A) changes the description and the nature of the offense. (B) increases the penalty to its next degree but absorbs all the other aggravating circumstances. (C)raises the penalty by two periods higher. (D) is one which applies only in conjunction with another aggravating circumstance.",
        "Answer": "changes the description and the nature of the offense."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 74,
        "Question": "What is the nature of the circumstance which is involved in the imposition of the maximum term of the indeterminate sentence?  a) qualifying circumstance; b) aggravating circumstance; c) modifying circumstance; d) analogous circumstance.",
        "Answer": "modifying circumstance;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 75,
        "Question": "Porthos bumped a parked car. Aramis confronted Porthos and shouted: Putang Ina mo! Porthos shouted back: Wag kang magtapangtapangan dyan, papatayin kita! Aramis drew his gun and shot Porthos in the leg (not life threatening). What are the kinds of unlawful aggression, and which kind was displayed in this case? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Unlawful aggression is of two kinds: (a) actual or material unlawful aggression; and (b) imminent unlawful aggression. Actual or material unlawful aggression means an attack with physical force or with a weapon, an offensive act that positively determines the intent of the aggressor to cause the injury. Imminent unlawful aggression means an attack that is impending or at the point of happening; it must not consist in a mere threatening attitude, nor must it be merely imaginary, but must be offensive and positively strong... In this case, there is neither actual nor imminent unlawful aggression. The statement “papatayin kita” neither constitutes an attack with physical force or with a weapon... nor an impending attack, which is offensive and positively strong."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 76,
        "Question": "Standing trial for frustrated murder, Aramis pleaded self-defense. The Prosecution’s contention was that the plea of self-defense applied only to consummated killings. Rule, with explanations, on the tenability of Aramis’ claim of self-defense, and on the Prosecution’s contention.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The prosecution's contention is not tenable. Shooting the leg of the victim without killing him may be a reasonable means to prevent or repel an actual or imminent unlawful aggression; hence, self-defense is not confined to consummated killing."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 77,
        "Question": "Porthos insisted that the element of treachery was present. To rule out treachery, Aramis asserted that both he and Porthos were then facing and confronting each other when he fired the shot. Rule, with reasons, on the respective contentions.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "There is no treachery as the attack was preceded by heated words. The act was spontaneous, arising from the said circumstance. The sudden attack was not preconceived and deliberately adopted but was just triggered by the sudden infuriation on the part of the accused, because of the provocative act of the victim, where their meeting was purely accidental."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 78,
        "Question": "Three men gave Arnold fist blows and kicks causing him to fall. As they surrounded and continued hitting him, he grabbed a knife he had in his pocket and stabbed one of the men straight to the heart. What crime did Arnold commit?  (A) Homicide with incomplete self-defense, since he could have run from his aggressors. (B) Homicide, since he knew that stabbing a person in the heart is fatal. (C)Homicide mitigated by incomplete self-defense, since stabbing a person to the heart is excessive. (D)No crime, since he needed to repel the aggression, employing reasonable means for doing so.",
        "Answer": "No crime, since he needed to repel the aggression, employing reasonable means for doing so."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 79,
        "Question": "To save himself from crashing into an unlighted truck abandoned on the road, Jose swerved his car to the right towards the graveled shoulder, killing two bystanders. Is he entitled to the justifying circumstance of state of necessity?  (A) No, because the bystanders had nothing to do with the abandoned truck on the road. (B) No, because the injury done is greater than the evil to be avoided. (C) Yes, since the instinct of self-preservation takes priority in an emergency. (D) Yes, since the bystanders should have kept off the shoulder of the road.",
        "Answer": "No, because the injury done is greater than the evil to be avoided."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 80,
        "Question": "Under which of the following circumstances is an accused not liable for the result not intended?  a) Accused is not criminally liable for the result not intended when there is mistake in the identity of the victim. b) Accused is not criminally liable for the result not intended when there is mistake in the blow. c) Accused is not criminally liable for the result not intended when the wrongful act is not the proximate cause of the resulting injury. d) Accused is not criminally liable for the result not intended when there is mistake of fact constituting an involuntary act.",
        "Answer": "Accused is not criminally liable for the result not intended when the wrongful act is not the proximate cause of the resulting injury."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 81,
        "Question": "Pedro is married to Tessie. Juan is the first cousin of Tessie. In the market, Pedro saw a man stabbing Juan. Pedro picked up a spade and hit the attacker on his head which caused the latter’s death. Can Pedro be absolved of the killing on the ground that it is in defense of a relative? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "No. The relatives of the accused for purpose of defense of relative under Article 11 (2) of the Revised Penal Code are his spouse, ascendants, descendants, or legitimate, natural or adopted brothers or sisters, or of his relatives by affinity in the same degrees, and those by consanguinity within the fourth civil degree. Relative by affinity within the same degree includes the ascendant, descendant, brother or sister of the spouse of the accused. In this case, Juan is not the ascendant, descendant, brother or sister of Tessie, the spouse of Pedro. Relative by consanguinity within the fourth civil degree includes first cousin. But in this case Juan is the cousin of Pedro by affinity but not by consanguinity, Juan, therefore, is not a relative of Pedro for purpose of applying the provision on defense of relative. Pedro, however, can invoke defense of a stranger. Under the revised Penal Code, a person who defends a person who is not his relative may invoke the defense of a stranger provided that all its elements exist, to wit: (a) unlawful aggression, (b) reasonable necessity of the means employed to prevent or repel the attack; and (c) the person defending be not induced by revenge, resentment, or other evil motive."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 82,
        "Question": "Romeo and Julia were married and the quarrels became increasingly violent... One night, Romeo came home drunk and went straight to bed. Fearing the onset of another violent fight, Julia stabbed Romeo while he was asleep... She asserted “battered woman’s syndrome” as her defense. Explain the “cycle of violence.”  ",
        "Answer": "The battered woman syndrome is characterized by the so-called “cycle of violence,” which has three phases: (1) the tension-building phase; (2) the acute battering incident; and (3) the tranquil, loving (or, at least, nonviolent) phase. During the tension-building phase, minor battering occurs-it could be verbal or slight physical abuse or another form of hostile behavior. The woman tries to pacify the batterer through a kind, nurturing behavior; or by simply staying out of his way. The acute battering incident is characterized by brutality, destructiveness and, sometimes, death. The battered woman deems this incident as unpredictable, yet also inevitable. During this phase, she has no control; only the batterer may put an end to the violence. The final phase of the cycle of violence begins when the acute battering incident ends. During this tranquil period, the couple experience profound relief."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 83,
        "Question": "Romeo and Julia were married... Julia stabbed Romeo while he was asleep... She asserted “battered woman’s syndrome” as her defense. Is Julia’s “battered woman’s syndrome” defense meritorious? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Yes. Under Section 3 (c) of RA NO. 9262, “Battered Woman Syndrome” refers to a scientifically defined pattern of psychological and behavioral symptoms found in women living in battering relationships as a result of “cumulative abuse”. In this case, because of the battering episodes, Julia, feared the onset of another violent fight and honestly believed the need to defend herself even if Romeo had not commenced an unlawful aggression. Even in the absence of unlawful aggression, however, Battered Woman Syndrome is a defense. Under Section 27 of RA No. 9262, Battered Woman Syndrome is a defense notwithstanding the absence of any of the elements for justifying circumstances of self-defense under the Revised Penal Code such as unlawful aggression (Section 26 of RA No. 9262)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 84,
        "Question": "Ms. A was habitually beaten and verbally abused by her husband Mr. B. One night, Mr. B arrived dead drunk, he suddenly stabbed Ms. A several times... Ms. A grappled for the possession of a knife... and stabbed Mr. B several times which caused his instantaneous death. Can Ms. A validly put up a defense? Explain. (2014, 2010)",
        "Answer": "Yes, Ms. A can put up the defense of battered woman syndrome. It appears that she is suffering from physical and psychological or emotional distress resulting from cumulative abuse by her husband. Under Sec. 3 of R.A. 9262, “victim survivors who are found by courts to be suffering from battered woman syndrome do not incur any criminal and civil liability notwithstanding the absence of any of the elements for justifying circumstances of self defense under the RPC.”"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 85,
        "Question": "The husband has for a long time physically and mentally tortured his wife. After one episode of beating, the wife took the husband’s gun and shot him dead. Under the circumstances, her act constitutes  (A) mitigating vindication of grave offense. (B) battered woman syndrome, a complete self-defense. (C) incomplete self-defense. (D) mitigating passion and obfuscation.",
        "Answer": "battered woman syndrome, a complete self-defense."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 86,
        "Question": "A battered woman claiming self-defense under the Anti-Violence against Women and Children must prove that the final acute battering episode was preceded by  (A) 3 battering episodes. (B) 4 battering episodes. (C) 5 battering episodes. (D) 2 battering episodes.",
        "Answer": "2 battering episodes."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 87,
        "Question": "Dion and Talia were spouses. Dion always came home drunk... One night, in addition to the usual verbal abuse, Dion beat up Talia... Just after one week, he started drinking again. Talia... stabbed Dion with a kitchen knife while he was passed out... May Talia invoke the defense of Battered Woman Syndrome to free herself from criminal liability? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "No, a single act of battery or physical harm committed by Dion against Talia resulting to the physical and psychological or emotional distress on her part is not sufficient to avail of the benefit of the justifying circumstance of “Battered Woman Syndrome”. The defense of Battered Woman Syndrome can be invoked if the woman with marital relationship with the victim is subjected to cumulative abuse or battery involving the infliction of physical harm resulting to the physical and psychological or emotional distress. Cumulative means resulting from successive addition. In sum, there must be “at least two battering episodes” between the accused and her intimate partner and such final episode produced in the battered person’s mind an actual fear of an imminent harm from her batterer and an honest belief that she needed to use force in order to save her life (People v. Genosa, G.R. No. 135981, January 15, 2004)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 88,
        "Question": "Will your answer be the same (regarding the Battered Woman Syndrome defense), assuming that Talia killed Dion after being beaten up after a second time? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Yes, Talia can invoke the defense of Battered Woman Syndrome to free herself from criminal liability for killing her husband since she suffered physical and emotional distress arising from cumulative abuse or battery. Under Section 26 of RA 9262, victim survivors of Battered Woman Syndrome do not incur any criminal or civil liability despite the absence of the requisites of self-defense."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 89,
        "Question": "Define Battered Woman Syndrome?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Battered Woman Syndrome refers to a scientifically defined pattern of psychological and behavioral symptoms found in women living in battering relationships as a result of cumulative abuse (Section 31dj, Rep. Act No. 9262)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 90,
        "Question": "What are the three phases of the Battered Woman Syndrome?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The three (3) phases of the Battered Woman Syndrome are: (1) the tension-building phase; (2) the acute battering incident; and (3) the tranquil, loving, or non-violent phase (People v. Genosa, G.R. No. 135981, January 15, 2004)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 91,
        "Question": "Would the Battered Woman Syndrome defense prosper despite the absence of any of the elements for justifying circumstances of self-defense under the Revised Penal Code? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. Section 26 of Rep. Act No. 9262 provides that victim-survivors who are found by the courts to be suffering from battered woman syndrome do not incur any criminal and civil liability notwithstanding the absence of any of the elements for justifying circumstances of self-defense under the Revised Penal Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 92,
        "Question": "What is now the age of doli incapax in the Philippines?  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "If the accused is 15 years of age or below, minority is an exempting circumstance (Section 6 of RA No. 9344). With or without discernment, the accused of such age is exempt from criminal liability. Lack of discernment is conclusively presumed. Hence, the age of doli incapax in the Philippines is now 15 years of age or under."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 93,
        "Question": "Sixteen year old Aliswan... fatally stabbed Allesso... Before the trial court, Aliswan moved that the cases should be dismissed because he was entitled to the exempting circumstance of minority. Is his motion correct? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Since Aliswan's age is above 15 but below 18, being the brother of 16 year old Aliswan, the exempting circumstance of minority shall be appreciated in his favor unless it is shown that be acted with discernment. The cases are not dismissible since the prosecution must be first given opportunity to present evidence to establish that Aliswan acted with discernment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 94,
        "Question": "Answering the criminal complaint filed by Alisto (Aliswan's twin), Amante (Amethyst's father) contended that he had incurred no criminal liability for lack of criminal intent on his part, his intended victim being Aliswan, not Alisto. What is this defense of Amante, and explain if the same will prosper?  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The defense raised by Amante is error in personae. This defense is not proper because of Article 4 of the Revised Penal Code, which provides that a person committing a felony is liable criminally although the wrongful act done be different from the unlawful intent. Thus, under this provision, Amante is liable for the wrongful act done, and that is child abuse against Alisto, although it differs from the wrongful act intended, and that is abusing Aliswan."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 95,
        "Question": "Charges d’affairės Volvik of Latvia suffers from a psychotic disorder... He asked for the gun of his escort and shot ten (10) people and wounded five (5) others... What crime or crimes, if any, did he commit? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Volvik committed five frustrated murders for the unwounded victims and five frustrated murders for the wounded victims. Treachery is present since the sudden attack rendered the victims defenseless. The nature of the weapon used in attacking the victims and extent of the wounds sustained by the five victims showed intent to kill. His psychotic condition is not an exempting circumstance of insanity in the absence of showing that there is a complete deprivation of intelligence in accordance with the cognition test. However, he is immune from criminal prosecution. Since the position of Volvik as charges de affaires is diplomatic, he is vested with blanket diplomatic immunity from criminal suit (Minucher v. Hon. CA, G.R. No. 142396, February 11, 2003)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 96,
        "Question": "What is the criminal liability, if any, of a private person who enters the dwelling of another against the latter's will and by means of violence or intimidation for the purpose of preventing some harm to himself?  a) The private person is criminally liable for qualified trespass to dwelling. b) The private person is criminally liable for simple trespass to dwelling. c) The private person incurs no criminal liability. d) The private person is criminally liable for light threats.",
        "Answer": "The private person incurs no criminal liability."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 97,
        "Question": "What is a privileged mitigating circumstance? Distinguish a privileged mitigating circumstance from an ordinary mitigating circumstance as to reduction of penalty and offsetting against aggravating circumstance/s. ",
        "Answer": "Privileged mitigating circumstances are those that mitigate the criminal liability of the accused by graduating the imposable penalty for the crime being modified to one or two degrees lower. These circumstances cannot be offset by aggravating circumstance. The circumstance of incomplete justification or exemption (when majority of the conditions are present), and the circumstance of minority (if the child above 15 years of age acted with discernment) are privileged mitigating circumstance. The distinctions between ordinary and privileged mitigating circumstances are as follows: i. Under the rules for application of divisible penalties (RPC, Art. 64), the presence of a mitigating circumstance, if not off-set by aggravating circumstance, has the effect of applying the divisible penalty in its minimum period. Under the rules on graduation of penalty (RPC, Art. 68, 69), the presence of privileged mitigating circumstance has the effect of reducing the penalty one to two degrees lower; ii. Ordinary mitigating circumstances can be off-set by aggravating circumstances. Privileged mitigating circumstances are not subject to the off-set rule."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 98,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a privilege mitigating circumstance?  (A) 17-year-old offender (B) 14-year-old offender (C) incomplete self-defense (D) incomplete defense of a relative",
        "Answer": "14-year-old offender"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 99,
        "Question": "Who among the following accused is entitled to a privileged mitigating circumstance that would lower the imposable penalty by one degree?  (A) A minor above 15 years old and below 18 years old who acted with discernment. (B) One who, in fulfilment of his duty to carry out the warrant of arrest of a fugitive, shot the fugitive to death without ascertaining his identity. (C) One who defended himself against an unlawful aggression but used unreasonable means and gave provocation. (D) All of the above.",
        "Answer": "All of the above."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 100,
        "Question": "A child over fifteen (15) years of age acted with discernment in the commission of murder. What is the duty of the court if he is already over eighteen (18) years of age at the time of the determination of his guilt for the offense charged?  a) The court shall pronounce the judgment of conviction. b) The court shall place the child under suspended sentence for a specified period or until he reaches twenty-one (21) years of age. c) The court shall discharge the child for disposition measures. d) The court shall place the child on probation.",
        "Answer": "The court shall place the child under suspended sentence for a specified period or until he reaches twenty-one (21) years of age."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 101,
        "Question": "A, B and C, all seventeen (17) years of age, waited for nighttime to avoid detection and to facilitate the implementation of their plan to rob G. They entered the room of G through a window. Upon instruction of A, G opened her vault while B was poking a knife at her. Acting as lookout, C had already opened the main door of the house when the helper was awakened by the pleading of G to A and B to just take the money from the vault without harming her. When the helper shouted for help upon seeing G with A and B inside the room, B stabbed G and ran towards the door, leaving the house with C. A also left the house after taking the money of G from the vault. G was brought to the hospital where she died as a result of the wound inflicted by B. Under the given facts, are A, B and C exempt from criminal liability? If not, what is the proper charge against them or any of them? ",
        "Answer": "Considering the given facts which manifest discernment, A, B and C are not exempt from criminal liability and should be charged with the complex crime of robbery with homicide, subject to automatic suspension of sentence upon finding of guilt."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 102,
        "Question": "Michael was 17 years old when he was charged for violation of Sec. 5 of R.A. 9165 (illegal sale of prohibited drug). By the time he was convicted and sentenced, he was already 21 years old. The court sentenced him to suffer an indeterminate penalty of imprisonment of six (6) years and one (1) day of prision mayor, as minimum, to seventeen (17) years and four (4) months of reclusion temporal, as maximum, and a fine of P500,000. Michael applied for probation but his application was denied because the probation law does not apply to drug offenders under R.A. 9165. Michael then sought the suspension of his sentence under R.A. 9344 or the Juvenile Justice and Youth Welfare Code. Can Michael avail of the suspension of his sentence provided under this law? ",
        "Answer": "The benefits of a suspended sentence can no longer apply to Michael. The suspension of sentence lasts only until the law reaches the maximum age and thus, could no longer be considered a child for purposes of applying R.A. 9344. However, he shall be entitled to the right of restoration, rehabilitation and reintegration in accordance with the law to give him the chance to live a normal life and become a productive member of the community. Accordingly, Michael may be confined in an agricultural camp and other training facility in accordance with Sec. 51 of R.A. 9344 (People v. Jacinto, G.R. No. 182239, March 16, 2011)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 103,
        "Question": "Charged with murder, Romeo pleaded insanity as a defense. Will Romeo’s defense prosper? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, Romeo’s defense of insanity will not prosper because, even assuming that Romeo was “insane” when diagnosed after he committed the crime, insanity as a defense to the commission of a crime must have existed and proven to be existing at the precise moment when the crime was being committed. The facts of the case indicate that Romeo committed the crime with discernment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 104,
        "Question": "What is the effect of the diagnosis of the NCMH on the case  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The effect of the diagnosis made by NCMH is possibly a suspension of the proceedings against Romeo and his commitment to appropriate institution for treatment until he could already understand the proceedings."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 105,
        "Question": "Passion or obfuscation may be appreciated ________.  (A) if it arises from jealousy in an amorous relationship between a married man and a single woman (B) if it arises from jealousy of a man who has been living-in with the woman for the past 20 years (C) if it arises from jealousy with immoral, lustful and vindictive sentiments of the offender against the victim (D) in none of the above situations",
        "Answer": "in none of the above situations"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 106,
        "Question": "W allowed a man to have sex with her thinking that he was her husband. After realizing that the man was not her husband, W stabbed him to death. Under the circumstances, the mitigating circumstance in attendance constitutes  (A) defense of honor. (B) immediate vindication of a grave offense. (C) passion or obfuscation. (D) self-defense.",
        "Answer": "immediate vindication of a grave offense."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 107,
        "Question": "After properly waiving his Miranda rights, the offender led the police to where he buried the gun he used in shooting the victim. How does this affect his liability?  (A) This serves as an analogous mitigating circumstance of voluntary surrender. (B) It has no effect at all since the law provides none. (C) He is considered to have confessed to murder. (D) This serves as aggravating circumstance of concealment of weapon.",
        "Answer": "This serves as an analogous mitigating circumstance of voluntary surrender."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 108,
        "Question": "Without meaning anything, Z happened to stare into the eye of one of four men hanging out by a store which he passed. Taking offense, the four mauled and robbed him of his wages. Z went home, took a knife, and stabbed one of his attackers to death. Charged with murder, Z may raise the mitigating circumstance of  (A) praeter intentionem. (B) incomplete self-defense preceded by undue provocation. (C) passion or obfuscation. (D) complete self-defense.",
        "Answer": "incomplete self-defense preceded by undue provocation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 109,
        "Question": "The presence of a mitigating circumstance in a crime  (A) increases the penalty to its maximum period. (B) changes the gravity of the offense. (C) affects the imposable penalty, depending on other modifying circumstances. (D) automatically reduces the penalty.",
        "Answer": "affects the imposable penalty, depending on other modifying circumstances."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 110,
        "Question": "To mitigate his liability for inflicting physical injury to another, an accused with a physical defect must prove that such defect restricted his freedom of action and understanding. This proof is not required where the physical defect consists of  (A) a severed right hand. (B) complete blindness. (C) being deaf mute and dumb. (D) a severed leg.",
        "Answer": "being deaf mute and dumb."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 111,
        "Question": "An extenuating circumstance, which has the same effect as a mitigating circumstance, is exemplified by  (A) the mother killing her 2-day old child to conceal her dishonor. (B) the accused committing theft out of extreme poverty. (C) the accused raping his victim in extreme state of passion. (D) the accused surrendering the weapon he used in his crime to the authorities.",
        "Answer": "the accused committing theft out of extreme poverty."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 112,
        "Question": "Minority is a privileged mitigating circumstance which operates to reduce the penalty by a degree where the child is  (A) 15 years and below acting without discernment. (B) above 15 years but below 18 acting without discernment. (C) below 18 years acting with discernment. (D) 18 years old at the time of the commission of the crime acting with discernment.",
        "Answer": "below 18 years acting with discernment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 113,
        "Question": "The crime of robbery in an inhabited house or public building is mitigated when the offenders  (A) entered the house using false keys. (B) although armed did not fire their weapons. (C) entered through a window without breaking it. (D) although armed took property valued at only P200.",
        "Answer": "entered through a window without breaking it."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 114,
        "Question": "The mitigating circumstance of immediate vindication of a grave offense cannot be appreciated in a case where  (A) Following the killing of his adopted brother, P went to the place where it happened and killed S whom he found there. (B) X kills Y who attempted to rape X’s wife. (C) P severely maltreats S, a septuagenarian, prompting the latter to kill him. (D) M killed R who slandered his wife.",
        "Answer": "Following the killing of his adopted brother, P went to the place where it happened and killed S whom he found there."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 115,
        "Question": "Deeply enraged by his wife’s infidelity, the husband shot and killed her lover. The husband subsequently surrendered to the police. How will the court appreciate the mitigating circumstances of (i) passion or obfuscation, (ii) vindication of a grave offense, and (iii) voluntary surrender that the husband invoked and proved?  (A) It will appreciate passion or obfuscation and voluntary surrender as one mitigating circumstance and vindication of a grave offense as another. (B) It will appreciate all three mitigating circumstances separately. (C) It will appreciate the three mitigating circumstances only as one. (D) It will appreciate passion or obfuscation and vindication of a grave offense as just one mitigating circumstance and voluntary surrender as another.",
        "Answer": "It will appreciate passion or obfuscation and vindication of a grave offense as just one mitigating circumstance and voluntary surrender as another."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 116,
        "Question": "A killed M. After the killing, A went to the Barangay Chairman of the place of incident to seek protection against the retaliation of M's relatives. May voluntary surrender be appreciated as a mitigating circumstance in favor of A?  a) Yes. A surrendered to the Barangay Chairman who is a person in authority. b) Yes. The surrender of A would save the authorities the trouble and expense for his arrest. c) No. A did not unconditionally submit himself to the authorities in order to acknowledge his participation in the killing or to save the authorities the trouble and expenses necessary for his search and capture. (People vs. Del Castillo, GR 169084, January 18, 2012) d) No. The surrender to the Barangay Chairman is not a surrender to the proper authorities.",
        "Answer": "No. A did not unconditionally submit himself to the authorities in order to acknowledge his participation in the killing or to save the authorities the trouble and expenses necessary for his search and capture."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 117,
        "Question": "Bernardo was enraged by his conviction for robbery by Judge Samsonite despite insufficient evidence. Pending his appeal, Bernardo escaped in order to get even with Judge Samsonite. Bernardo learned that the judge regularly slept in his mistress’ house every weekend. Thus, he waited for the judge to arrive on Saturday evening at the house of his mistress. It was about 8:00 p.m. when Bernardo entered the house of the mistress. He found the judge and his mistress having coffee in the kitchen and engaging in small talk. Without warning, Bernardo stabbed the judge at least 20 times. The judge instantly died. Prosecuted and tried, Bernardo was convicted of direct assault with murder. Rule with reasons whether or not the conviction for direct assault with murder was justified, and whether or not the trial court should appreciate the following aggravating circumstances against Bernardo, to wit: (1) disregard of rank and age of the victim, who was 68 years old; (2) dwelling; (3) nighttime; (4) cruelty; and (5) quasi-recidivism. (10%) (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The phrase on occasion of such performance used in Article 48 of RPC means by reason of the past performance of official duty because the purpose of the law is to allow them to discharge their duties without fear of being assaulted by reason thereof (People v. Renegado, G.R. No. L-27031, May 31, 1974). Attacking Judge Samsonite by reason of past performance of duty of convicting Bernardo based on his assessment of the evidences constitutes qualified direct assault (U.S. v. Garcia, G.R. No. 6820, October 16, 1911). Since the single act of attacking Judge Samsonite constitutes direct assault and murder qualified by the circumstance of treachery, the two shall be merged together to form a complex crime of direct assault with murder (People v. Estonilo, Jr., G.R. No. 201565, October 13, 2014; People v. Dural, G.R. No. No. 84921, June 8, 1993; People v. Riuorta, G.R. No. 57415, December 15, 1989). Disregard of rank, being inherent in direct assault, is absorbed. Disregard of age shall not be considered for lack of showing of intent to offend or insult the age of Judge Samsonite (People v. Onabia, G.R. No. 128288, April 20, 1999). Dwelling and nighttime shall not be appreciated because the presence of treachery in the instant case absorbs these aggravating circumstances. The crime is not aggravated by cruelty simply because Judge Samson sustained 10 stab wounds. For cruelty to be considered as an aggravating Circumstance, it must be proven that in inflicting several stab wounds on the victim, the perpetrator intended to exacerbate the pain and suffering of the victim. The number of wounds inflicted on the victim Is not proof of cruelty (Simangan v. People G.R. No. 157984 July 8, 2004). Unless there is a proof that when the 2nd or subsequent stabs were made, the Judge was still alive, there is no cruelty to speak of. A quasi-recidivist is a person who shall commit a felony after having been convicted by final judgment, before beginning to serve such sentence, or while serving the same (Article 160 of the Revised Penal Code). In this case, Bernardo committed the crime while the judgement of conviction is on appeal. Thus, quasi-recidivism cannot be considered since he did not commit the crime after having been convicted by final judgment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 118,
        "Question": "When is a crime deemed to have been committed by a band?  a) When armed men, at least four (4) in number, take direct part in the execution of the act constituting the crime. b) When three (3) armed men act together in the commission of the crime. c) When there are four ( 4) armed persons, one of whom is a principal by inducement. d) When there are four (4) malefactors, one of whom is armed.",
        "Answer": "When armed men, at least four (4) in number, take direct part in the execution of the act constituting the crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 119,
        "Question": "Which of the following circumstances may be taken into account for the purpose of increasing the penalty to be imposed upon the convict?  a) Aggravating circumstances which in themselves constitute a crime specially punishable by law. b) Aggravating circumstances which are inherent in the crime to such a degree that they must of necessity accompany the crime. c) Aggravating circumstances which arise from the moral attributes of the offender. d) Aggravating circumstances which are included by the law in defining a crime.",
        "Answer": "Aggravating circumstances which arise from the moral attributes of the offender."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 120,
        "Question": "Arthur, Ben, and Cesar quarreled with Glen while they were at the latter’s house. Enraged, Arthur repeatedly stabbed Glen while Ben and Cesar pinned his arms. What aggravating circumstance if any attended the killing of Glen?  (A) Evident premeditation. (B) None. (C) Abuse of superior strength. (D) Treachery.",
        "Answer": "Treachery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 121,
        "Question": "Ana visited her daughter Belen who worked as Caloy’s housemaid. Caloy was not at home but Debbie, a casual visitor in the house, verbally maligned Belen in Ana’s presence. Irked, Ana assaulted Debbie. Under the circumstances, dwelling is NOT regarded as aggravating because  (A) Dwelling did nothing to provoke Ana into assaulting Debbie. (B) Caloy, the owner of the house, was not present. (C) Debbie is not a dweller of the house. (D) Belen, whom Debbie maligned, also dwells in the house.",
        "Answer": "Debbie is not a dweller of the house."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 122,
        "Question": "The aggravating circumstance of uninhabited place is aggravating in murder committed  (A) on a banca far out at sea. (B) in a house located in cul de sac. (C) in a dark alley in Tondo. (D) in a partly occupied condominium building.",
        "Answer": "on a banca far out at sea."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 123,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a qualifying aggravating circumstance?  (A) treachery (B) evident premeditation (C) dwelling (D) cruelty",
        "Answer": "dwelling"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 124,
        "Question": "Wenceslao and Loretta were staying in the same boarding house, occupying different rooms. One late evening, when everyone in the house was asleep, Wenceslao entered Loretta's room with the use of a picklock. Then, with force and violence, Wenceslao ravished Loretta. After he had satisfied his lust, Wenceslao stabbed Loretta to death and, before leaving the room, took her jewelry. Discuss the applicability of the relevant aggravating circumstances of dwelling, nocturnity and the use of the picklock to enter the room of the victim.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Dwelling is aggravating because the crimes were committed in the privacy of Loretta's room which in law is considered as her dwelling. It is well settled that dwelling includes a room in a boarding house being occupied by the offended party where she enjoys privacy, peace of mind and sanctity of an abode. Nocturnity or nighttime is also aggravating because although it was not purposely or especially sought for by Wenceslao, nighttime was obviously taken advantaged of by him in committing the other crimes. Under the objective test, nocturnity is aggravating when taken advantaged of by the offender during the commission of the crime thus facilitating the same. The use of a picklock to enter the room of the victim is not an aggravating circumstance under Art. 14 of the Code but punished as a crime by itself where the offender has no lawful cause for possessing it. The use of picklocks is equivalent to force upon things in robbery with force upon things."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 125,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. The use of an unlicensed firearm in homicide is considered a generic aggravating circumstance which can be offset by an ordinary mitigating circumstance.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. Offsetting may not take place because the use of an unlicensed firearm in homicide or murder is a specific aggravating circumstance provided for by Rep. Act No. 8294. It is not one of the generic aggravating circumstances under Art.14 of the Revised Penal Code (People v. Avecilla, 351 SCRA 635 [20011)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 126,
        "Question": "George, the 20-year old son of a rich politician, was arrested at the NAIA arrival lounge and found positive for opium, a dangerous drug. When arrested, 15 grams of cocaine were found in his backpack. What offense would you charge George under R.A. No. 9160 (Comprehensive Dangerous Drugs Act)?  (A) Use of dangerous drug. (B) Use and possession of dangerous drugs. (C) Possession of dangerous drugs. (D) Importation of dangerous drugs. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "Possession of dangerous drugs."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 127,
        "Question": "Following his arrest after a valid buy-bust operation, Tommy was convicted of violation of Section 5, Republic Act 9165. On appeal, Tommy questioned the admissibility of the evidence because the police officers who conducted the buy-bust operation failed to observe the requisite chain of custody of the evidence confiscated and/or seized from him. What is the chain of custody requirement in drug offenses? What is its rationale? What is the effect of failure to observe the requirement?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Chain of custody requirement in drug offenses refers to the duly recorded, authorized movement and custody of seized dangerous drugs, controlled chemicals, plant sources of dangerous drugs, and laboratory equipment for dangerous drugs from the time of confiscation/seizure thereof from the offender, to its turn-over and receipt in the forensic laboratory for examination, to its safekeeping and eventual presentation/offer in court as evidence of the criminal violation, and for destruction. (Dangerous Drugs Board Regulation No.1 Series of 2002)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 128,
        "Question": "Emilo, a poseur buyer, exchanged marked money with Rado for sachets of shabu in a buy-bust operation. May Rado adopt as his own Emilo's defense? Explain.",
        "Answer": "No. First, an entrapment operation is a valid means of arresting violators of RA 9165. It is an effective way of apprehending law offenders in the act of committing a crime. In a buy-bust operation, the idea to commit a crime originates from the offender, without anybody inducing or prodding him to commit the offense. Second, the immunity does not extend to violators of Section 5 of RA 9165 or the sale of shabu (sec. 33, RA 9165). Lastly, he was the offender of the crime and apparently the most guilty of the offense."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 129,
        "Question": "AA knowingly and wilfully induced BB to swear falsely. BB testified as told in a formal hearing of an administrative case under circumstances rendering him guilty of perjury. Is AA criminally liable?  a) AA is not criminally liable because his act constitutes subornation of perjury which is not expressly penalized in the Revised Penal Code. b) AA is not criminally liable because he was not the one who gave false testimony in the administrative case. c) AA is not criminally liable because the witness suborned testified in an administrative case only. d) AA is criminally liable for perjury as principal by inducement with BB as the principal by direct participation.",
        "Answer": "AA is criminally liable for perjury as principal by inducement with BB as the principal by direct participation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 130,
        "Question": "A person gave Zeno and Primo a map that helped them escape after committing murder. He is liable as  (A) Accomplice to murder, since his cooperation was minimal. (B) Accessory to murder, since his map facilitated the escape of the two. (C) None, since he took no step to take part in executing the crime. (D) Principal to murder, since he acted in conspiracy with Zeno and Primo.",
        "Answer": "Accessory to murder, since his map facilitated the escape of the two."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 131,
        "Question": "A, B, and C agreed to rob a house of its cash. A and B entered the house while C remained outside as lookout. After getting the cash, A and B decided to set the house on fire to destroy any evidence of their presence. What crime or crimes did C commit?  (A) Robbery and arson since arson took place as an incident of the robbery. (B) Robbery and arson since C took no step to stop the arson. (C) Just for robbery since he only agreed to it and served as lookout. (D) Accomplice to robbery since his role in the crime was minimal.",
        "Answer": "Just for robbery since he only agreed to it and served as lookout."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 132,
        "Question": "A private person who assists the escape of a person who committed robbery shall be liable  (A) as a principal to the crime of robbery. (B) as an accessory to the crime of robbery. (C) as a principal to the crime of obstruction of justice. (D) as an accessory to the crime of obstruction of justice.",
        "Answer": "as an accessory to the crime of robbery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 133,
        "Question": "Mr. Red was drinking with his buddies, Mr. White and Mr. Blue when he saw Mr. Green with his former girlfriend, Ms. Yellow. Already drunk, Mr. Red declared in a loud voice that if he could not have Ms. Yellow, no one can. He then proceeded to the men’s room but told Mr. White and Mr. Blue to take care of Mr. Green. Mr. Blue and Mr. White asked Mr. Red what he meant but Mr. Red simply said, You already know what I want, and then left. Mr. Blue and Mr. White proceeded to kill Mr. Green and hurt Ms. Yellow. What, if any, are the respective liabilities of Mr. Red, Mr. White and Mr. Blue for the death of Mr. Green? ",
        "Answer": "Mr. Blue and Mr. White are liable for the death of Mr. Green as principals by direct participation. They were the ones who participated in the criminal resolution and who carried out their plan and personally took part in its execution by acts which directly tended to the same end. Mr. Red cannot be held criminally liable as principal by inducement because his statement that Mr. Blue and Mr. White are to take care of Mr. Green was not made directly with the intention of procuring the commission of the crime. There is no showing that the words uttered by him may be considered as so efficacious and powerful so as to amount to physical or moral coercion (People v. Assad, G.R. No. L-33673, February 24, 1931). Neither is there evidence to show that Mr. Red has an ascendancy or influence over Mr. White and Mr. Blue (People v. Abarri, F.R. No. 90815, March 1, 1995)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 134,
        "Question": "What, if any, are the respective liabilities of Mr. Red, Mr. White and Mr. Blue for the injuries of Ms. Yellow?",
        "Answer": "Mr. Blue and Mr. White are liable as principals by direct participation for the crime of physical injuries for hurting Ms. Yellow to the extent of the injuries inflicted. Having no participation in the attack upon Ms. Yellow, Mr. Red would have no criminal liability therefor."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 135,
        "Question": "A was bitten by a dog owned by a neighbor. The following day, angered by the incident, A took the dog without the knowledge of the owner, had it butchered and cooked the meat. He then invited his friends to partake of the dish with his friends who knew fully well that the dog was taken without the knowledge of the owner. What are the friends of A liable for?  (A) Theft (B) Malicious mischief (C) Accessories (D) Obstruction of Justice",
        "Answer": "Accessories"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 136,
        "Question": "Modesto and Abelardo are brothers. Sometime in August 1998 while Abelardo was in his office, Modesto, together with two other men in police uniform, came with two heavy bags. Modesto asked Abelardo to keep the two bags in his vault until he comes back to get them. When Abelardo later examined the two bags, he saw bundles of money that, in his rough count, could not be less than P5 Million. He kept the money inside the vault and soon he heard the news that a gang that included Modesto had been engaged in bank robberies. Abelardo, unsure of what to do under the circumstances, kept quiet about the two bags in his vault. Soon after, the police captured, and secured a confession from, Modesto who admitted that their loot had been deposited with Abelardo. What is Abelardo's liability? ",
        "Answer": "Abelardo is not criminally liable. To be criminally liable as an accessory under Art. 19, such person must have knowledge of the commission of the crime. The term “knowledge “under the law is not synonymous with suspicion. Mere suspicion that the crime has been committed is not sufficient. Even if he can be considered as an accessory under Art. 19(2) of RPC, Abelardo is not liable, being the brother of Modesto under Art. 20, RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 137,
        "Question": "Who is an accomplice? ",
        "Answer": "Accomplices are those persons who, not being the principal, cooperate in the execution of the offense by previous or simultaneous acts (Art. 18, RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 138,
        "Question": "Distinguish an accomplice from a conspirator as to their knowledge of the criminal design of the principal, their participation, the penalty to be imposed in relation to the penalty for the principal, and the requisites/elements to be established by the prosecution in order to hold them criminally responsible for their respective roles in the commission of the crime. ",
        "Answer": "Accomplice: Knowledge of the criminal design of the principal need not be shown to prove complicity, although the offender must be aware of the principal’s intention; Participation consists of previous or simultaneous acts that are not indispensable to the commission of the crime; Penalty is one degree lower than the penalty prescribed by law for the principal; Elements to be established are: (1) that the principal committed a felony; (2) that the accused cooperated in the execution of the crime by previous or simultaneous acts; and (3) that the cooperation was not indispensable. Conspirator: Knowledge of the criminal design of the principal is essential for conspiracy; Participation consists of coming to an agreement and deciding to commit the felony; Penalty is the same as the penalty prescribed by law for the principal; Elements to be established are: (1) that two or more persons come to an agreement; (2) that the agreement concerned the commission of a crime; and (3) that the execution of the felony was decided upon."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 139,
        "Question": "Nel learned that Elgar, the owner of the biggest house in the place, would be out of town for three days with no one left to watch the house. He called his friends Ben, Ardo and Gorio and they planned to take the valuables in the house while Elgar was away. Nel and Ben would go inside the house, Ardo would serve as the lookout, while Gorio would stay in the getaway car. When Elgar left, they carried out their plan to the letter. Nel and Ben went inside the house through the backdoor which was left unlocked. None of the rooms and drawers inside were locked. They took the money, jewelry and other valuables therefrom and immediately left using the getaway car. After driving for about one kilometer, Nel realized he left his bag and wallet with IDs in the house and so he instructed Gorio to drive back to the house. Nel just went in thinking that the house was still empty. But to his surprise, Nel found Fermin seated on a bench with Nel's bag and wallet beside him and appeared to be texting using his smart phone. Nel took a golf club near him and hit Fermin with it. Fermin shouted for help, but Nel kept hitting him until he stopped making noise. The noise alerted the neighbor who called the police. Nel, Ben, Ardo and Gorio were caught. Fermin died. What is the criminal liability of Nel, Ben, Ardo and Gorio? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Nel, Ben, Ardo and Gorio are criminally liable as principals for the crime of Theft. They conspired to take Elgar’s personal properties without his knowledge, with intent to gain, and without violence against or intimidation of persons or force upon things (Art. 308, RPC). Nel and Ben are liable as principals by direct participation while Ardo and Gorio are principals by indispensable cooperation because they have concurred in the criminal resolution and cooperated by performing another act as lookout and driver of a getaway car, respectively, which were indispensable for the commission of the crime (Art. 17, RPC). Nel, however, is also liable for the separate crime of Homicide for the death of Fermin. The killing of Fermin was a separate act and was not a necessary means for committing Theft (Art. 48, RPC) because the latter crime was already consummated. Nel killed Fermin for a different reason perhaps because of his anger that Fermin was in possession of his bag and wallet and appeared to be using his smart phone to contact the police."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 140,
        "Question": "To secure a release of his brother Willy, a detention prisoner, and his cousin Vincent, who is serving sentence for homicide, Chito asked the RTC Branch Clerk of Court to issue an Order which would allow the two prisoners to be brought out of jail. At first, the Clerk refused, but when Chita gave her P50,000.00, she consented. She then prepared an Order requiring the appearance in court of Willy and Vincent, ostensibly as witnesses in a pending case. She forged the judge's signature, and delivered the Order to the jail warden who, in turn, allowed Willy and Vincent to go out of jail in the company of an armed escort, Edwin. Chito also gave Edwin P50,000.00 to leave the two inmates unguarded for three minutes and provide them with an opportunity to escape. Thus, Willy and Vincent were able to escape. What crime or crimes, if any, had been committed by Chito, the Branch Clerk of court, and Edwin? Explain your answer.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The crimes committed in this case are as follows: Chito committed the crimes of -1. Delivery of Prisoners from Jail (Art. 156, RPC) for working out the escape of prisoners Willy and Vincent; 2. Two counts of Corruption of Public Officials (Art. 212, RPC); and 3. Falsification of Public Documents, as a principal by inducement (Art. 172, RPC). The Branch Clerk of Court committed the crimes of: 1. Direct Bribery (Art. 210, RPC) for accepting the P50,000.00 - in consideration of the order she issued to enable the prisoners to get out of jail; 2. Falsification of Public Document for forging the judge's signature on said Order (Art. 171, RPC); 3. Delivery of Prisoners from Jail (Art. 156, RPC), as a co-principal of Chito by indispensable cooperation for making the false Order and forging the judge's signature thereon, to enable the prisoners to get out of jail; 4. Evasion of Service of Sentence (Art. 157, RPC); as a co-principal of Vincent by indispensable cooperation for making the false Order that enabled Vincent to evade service of his sentence; Edwin, the jail guard who escorted the prisoners in getting out of jail, committed the crimes of – 1. Infidelity in the Custody of Prisoners, specifically conniving with or consenting to Evasion for leaving unguarded the prisoners escorted by him and provide them an opportunity to escape (Art. 223, RPC); 2. Direct Bribery for receiving the P50,000.00 as consideration for leaving the prisoners unguarded and allowing them the opportunity to escape (Art. 210, RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 141,
        "Question": "Ponciano, armed with his newly acquired gun, went to the house of Freddie and shot him to death. Ponciano's friend, Ruben, lent him the gun, knowing Ponciano's intention to kill Freddie. What, if any, is the liability of Ruben? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Ruben's liability is that of an accomplice only because he merely cooperated in Ponciano's determination to kill Freddie. Such cooperation is not indispensable to the killing, as in fact the killing was carried out without the use of Ruben's gun. Neither may Ruben be regarded as a co-conspirator since he was not a participant in the decision-making of Ponciano to kill Freddie; he merely cooperated in carrying out the criminal plan which was already in place (Art. 18, RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 142,
        "Question": "Would your answer be the same if, instead of Freddie, it was Manuel, a relative of Ruben, who was killed by Ponciano using Ruben's gun? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. The answer would be same because Ruben lent his gun to Ponciano with knowledge that it would be used in killing a person, thus with knowledge that the gun would be used to commit a crime. It is of no moment who was killed, so long as Ruben is aware when he lent the gun that it would be used to commit a crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 143,
        "Question": "Immediately after murdering Bob, Jake went to his mother to seek refuge. His mother told him to hide in the maid's quarters until she finds a better place for him to hide. After two days, Jake transferred to his aunt's house. A week later, Jake was apprehended by the police. Can Jake's mother and aunt be made criminally liable as accessories to the crime of murder? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Jake's mother was aware of her son's having committed a felony, such that her act of harboring and concealing him renders her liable as an accessory. But being an ascendant of Jake, she is exempt from criminal liability by express provision of Article 20 of the Revised Penal Code. On the other hand, the criminal liability of Jake's aunt depends on her knowledge of the felony committed by Jake. If she had knowledge of his commission of the felony, her act of harboring and concealing Jake would render her criminally liable as accessory to the crime of murder; otherwise without knowledge of Jake's commission of the felony, she would not be liable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 144,
        "Question": "The penalty of perpetual or temporary special disqualification for the exercise of the right of suffrage does NOT deprive the offender of the right  (A) to be elected to a public office. (B) to vote in any popular election for a public office. (C) to vote in a plebiscite. (D) to hold any public office.",
        "Answer": "to vote in a plebiscite."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 145,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Life imprisonment is a penalty more favorable to the convict than reclusion perpetua.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. Life imprisonment is unfavorable to a convict because the penalty is without a fixed duration, unlike the penalty of reclusion perpetua which has a fixed duration of 40 years and the convict may be eligible for pardon after 30 years of imprisonment (People v. Penillos, 205 SCRA 546 (1992)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 146,
        "Question": "Sammy Peke was convicted of a violation of R.A. No. 123456 for selling fake books. The law prescribes the penalty of prision correccional, a divisible penalty... At arraignment, Sammy Peke pleads guilty to the crime charged. Explain how the Indeterminate Sentence Law is applied in crimes punished by special laws.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Under the second part of the Indeterminate Sentence Law, in cases where the offense is punishable under special law, the maximum indeterminate penalty shall not exceed the maxi- mum limit of the prescribed penalty while the minimum penalty shall not be less than the minimum limit thereof. However, if the special law adopts the technical nomenclature of the penalties under the Revised Penal Code (People v. Macatanda, G.R. No. 51368, November 6, 1981), the provision of the Revised Penal Code will apply. Consequently, there will be an application of Art. 64 of the Revised Penal Code. The maximum penalty shall be fixed within the range of the proper imposable period after taking into consideration the modifying circumstance; while the minimum penalty shall be fixed within the range of the penalty next lower in degree than that prescribed by law (People v. Simon, G.R. No. 93028, July 29, 1994; Jacaba11 v. People, G.R. No. 184355, March 23, 2015; Mallo v. People, G.R. No. 164733, September 21, 2007; People v. Montalaba, G.R. No. 186227, July 20, 201J; People v. Musa, G.R. No. 199735, October 24, 2012; Peopl v. Salazar"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 147,
        "Question": "The mitigating circumstance of immediate vindication of a grave offense cannot be appreciated in a case where  (A) Following the killing of his adopted brother, P went to the place where it happened and killed S whom he found there. (B) X kills Y who attempted to rape X’s wife. (C)P severely maltreats S, a septuagenarian, prompting the latter to kill him. (D)M killed R who slandered his wife.",
        "Answer": "Following the killing of his adopted brother, P went to the place where it happened and killed S whom he found there."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 148,
        "Question": "May Rado adopt as his own Emilo's defense? Explain. (In the context of a buy-bust operation where Emilo is the poseur buyer and Rado is the seller of shabu.)",
        "Answer": "No. First, an entrapment operation is a valid means of arresting violators of RA 9165. It is an effective way of apprehending law offenders in the act of committing a crime. In a buy-bust operation, the idea to commit a crime originates from the offender, without anybody inducing or prodding him to commit the offense. Second, the immunity does not extend to violators of Section 5 of RA 9165 or the sale of shabu (sec. 33, RA 9165). Lastly, he was the offender of the crime and apparently the most guilty of the offense."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 149,
        "Question": "What, if any, are the respective liabilities of Mr. Red, Mr. White and Mr. Blue for the injuries of Ms. Yellow? ",
        "Answer": "Mr. Blue and Mr. White are liable as principals by direct participation for the crime of physical injuries for hurting Ms. Yellow to the extent of the injuries inflicted. Having no participation in the attack upon Ms. Yellow, Mr. Red would have no criminal liability therefor."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 150,
        "Question": "Nel learned that Elgar, the owner of the biggest house in the place, would be out of town for three days... Nel and Ben went inside the house... They took the money, jewelry and other valuables therefrom and immediately left... Nel realized he left his bag and wallet... Nel found Fermin seated on a bench with Nel's bag and wallet beside him... Nel took a golf club near him and hit Fermin with it. Fermin shouted for help, but Nel kept hitting him until he stopped making noise... Fermin died. What is the criminal liability of Nel, Ben, Ardo and Gorio? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Nel, Ben, Ardo and Gorio are criminally liable as principals for the crime of Theft. Nel and Ben are liable as principals by direct participation while Ardo and Gorio are principals by indispensable cooperation... Nel, however, is also liable for the separate crime of Homicide for the death of Fermin. The killing of Fermin was a separate act and was not a necessary means for committing Theft because the latter crime was already consummated."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 151,
        "Question": "To secure a release of his brother Willy, a detention prisoner, and his cousin Vincent, who is serving sentence for homicide, Chito asked the RTC Branch Clerk of Court to issue an Order which would allow the two prisoners to be brought out of jail... She then prepared an Order... She forged the judge's signature, and delivered the Order to the jail warden who, in turn, allowed Willy and Vincent to go out of jail in the company of an armed escort, Edwin... Chito also gave Edwin P50,000.00 to leave the two inmates unguarded... Thus, Willy and Vincent were able to escape. What crime or crimes, if any, had been committed by Chito, the Branch Clerk of court, and Edwin? Explain your answer.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Chito committed the crimes of - 1. Delivery of Prisoners from Jail (Art. 156, RPC); 2. Two counts of Corruption of Public Officials (Art. 212, RPC); and 3. Falsification of Public Documents, as a principal by inducement (Art. 172, RPC). The Branch Clerk of Court committed the crimes of: 1. Direct Bribery (Art. 210, RPC); 2. Falsification of Public Document for forging the judge's signature on said Order (Art. 171, RPC); 3. Delivery of Prisoners from Jail (Art. 156, RPC), as a co-principal of Chito by indispensable cooperation; 4. Evasion of Service of Sentence (Art. 157, RPC); as a co-principal of Vincent by indispensable cooperation. Edwin, the jail guard who escorted the prisoners in getting out of jail, committed the crimes of – 1. Infidelity in the Custody of Prisoners, specifically conniving with or consenting to Evasion; 2. Direct Bribery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 152,
        "Question": "Mr. Red was drinking with his buddies, Mr. White and Mr. Blue... Mr. Red declared in a loud voice that if he could not have Ms. Yellow, no one can. He then proceeded to the men’s room but told Mr. White and Mr. Blue to take care of Mr. Green... Mr. Blue and Mr. White proceeded to kill Mr. Green and hurt Ms. Yellow. What, if any, are the respective liabilities of Mr. Red, Mr. White and Mr. Blue for the death of Mr. Green? ",
        "Answer": "Mr. Blue and Mr. White are liable for the death of Mr. Green as principals by direct participation... Mr. Red cannot be held criminally liable as principal by inducement because his statement... was not made directly with the intention of procuring the commission of the crime... Neither is there evidence to show that Mr. Red has an ascendancy or influence over Mr. White and Mr. Blue."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 153,
        "Question": "A was bitten by a dog owned by a neighbor... A took the dog without the knowledge of the owner, had it butchered and cooked the meat. He then invited his friends to partake of the dish with his friends who knew fully well that the dog was taken without the knowledge of the owner. What are the friends of A liable for?  (A) Theft (B) Malicious mischief (C) Accessories (D) Obstruction of Justice",
        "Answer": "Accessories"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 154,
        "Question": "Modesto and Abelardo are brothers... Modesto, together with two other men in police uniform, came with two heavy bags. Modesto asked Abelardo to keep the two bags in his vault... Abelardo... saw bundles of money that... could not be less than P5 Million... Abelardo, unsure of what to do under the circumstances, kept quiet... Modesto... admitted that their loot had been deposited with Abelardo. What is Abelardo's liability? ",
        "Answer": "Abelardo is not criminally liable. To be criminally liable as an accessory under Art. 19, such person must have knowledge of the commission of the crime... Even if he can be considered as an accessory under Art. 19(2) of RPC, Abelardo is not liable, being the brother of Modesto under Art. 20, RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 155,
        "Question": "Nel learned that Elgar... Nel and Ben went inside the house... took the money, jewelry and other valuables... Nel realized he left his bag... Nel found Fermin seated on a bench... Nel took a golf club... and hit Fermin with it... Fermin died. What is the criminal liability of Nel, Ben, Ardo and Gorio? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Nel, Ben, Ardo and Gorio are criminally liable as principals for the crime of Theft... Nel and Ben are liable as principals by direct participation while Ardo and Gorio are principals by indispensable cooperation... Nel, however, is also liable for the separate crime of Homicide for the death of Fermin. The killing of Fermin was a separate act and was not a necessary means for committing Theft because the latter crime was already consummated."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 156,
        "Question": "To secure a release of his brother Willy, a detention prisoner, and his cousin Vincent, who is serving sentence for homicide, Chito asked the RTC Branch Clerk of Court to issue an Order which would allow the two prisoners to be brought out of jail... The Branch Clerk of Court... forged the judge's signature... Edwin, the jail warden's armed escort... allowed Willy and Vincent to go out of jail... Willy and Vincent were able to escape. What crime or crimes, if any, had been committed by Chito, the Branch Clerk of court, and Edwin? Explain your answer.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Chito committed the crimes of - 1. Delivery of Prisoners from Jail (Art. 156, RPC); 2. Two counts of Corruption of Public Officials (Art. 212, RPC); and 3. Falsification of Public Documents, as a principal by inducement (Art. 172, RPC). The Branch Clerk of Court committed the crimes of: 1. Direct Bribery (Art. 210, RPC); 2. Falsification of Public Document for forging the judge's signature... (Art. 171, RPC); 3. Delivery of Prisoners from Jail (Art. 156, RPC), as a co-principal of Chito by indispensable cooperation; 4. Evasion of Service of Sentence (Art. 157, RPC); as a co-principal of Vincent by indispensable cooperation. Edwin, the jail guard who escorted the prisoners in getting out of jail, committed the crimes of – 1. Infidelity in the Custody of Prisoners, specifically conniving with or consenting to Evasion; 2. Direct Bribery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 157,
        "Question": "Immediately after murdering Bob, Jake went to his mother to seek refuge. His mother told him to hide in the maid's quarters... After two days, Jake transferred to his aunt's house. A week later, Jake was apprehended by the police. Can Jake's mother and aunt be made criminally liable as accessories to the crime of murder? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Jake's mother was aware of her son's having committed a felony, such that her act of harboring and concealing him renders her liable as an accessory. But being an ascendant of Jake, she is exempt from criminal liability by express provision of Article 20 of the Revised Penal Code. On the other hand, the criminal liability of Jake's aunt depends on her knowledge of the felony committed by Jake. If she had knowledge... she would render her criminally liable as accessory to the crime of murder; otherwise without knowledge... she would not be liable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 158,
        "Question": "Sammy Peke was convicted of a violation of R.A. No. 123456 for selling fake books. The law prescribes the penalty of prision correccional... At arraignment, Sammy Peke pleads guilty to the crime charged. Explain how the Indeterminate Sentence Law is applied in crimes punished by special laws.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Under the second part of the Indeterminate Sentence Law, in cases where the offense is punishable under special law, the maximum indeterminate penalty shall not exceed the maximum limit of the prescribed penalty while the minimum penalty shall not be less than the minimum limit thereof. However, if the special law adopts the technical nomenclature of the penalties under the Revised Penal Code, the provision of the Revised Penal Code will apply... The maximum penalty shall be fixed within the range of the proper imposable period after taking into consideration the modifying circumstance; while the minimum penalty shall be fixed within the range of the penalty next lower in degree than that prescribed by law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 159,
        "Question": "Supposing the trial judge imposes a straight penalty of imprisonment for one year (for Sammy Peke's case of violating R.A. No. 123456 for selling fake books), is the penalty correct in the context of the Indeterminate Sentence Law? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Since Sammy Peke made a confession, the penalty of prision correctional prescribed for selling fake book shall be applied in its minimum period, which ranges from 6 months and 1 day to 2 years and 4 months. Thus, the court may opt to impose a penalty of 1 year of imprisonment within the range of the minimum period of prision correcional. In this case, Indeterminate Sentence Law is applicable, therefore, the straight penalty of one year of imprisonment is correct."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 160,
        "Question": "AA was convicted of proposal to commit treason. Under Article 115 of the Revised Penal Code, proposal to commit treason shall be punished by prision correccional and a fine not exceeding P5,000.00. Is the Indeterminate Sentence Law applicable to AA?  a) Yes. The Indeterminate Sentence Law is applicable to AA because the maximum of prision correccional exceeds one (1) year. b) Yes. The Indeterminate Sentence Law is applicable to AA because there is no showing that he is a habitual delinquent. c) No. The Indeterminate Sentence Law is not applicable to AA considering the penalty imposable for the offense of which he was convicted. d) No. The Indeterminate Sentence Law is not applicable considering the offense of which he was convicted.",
        "Answer": "Yes. The Indeterminate Sentence Law is applicable to AA because the maximum of prision correccional exceeds one (1) year."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 161,
        "Question": "Chris Brown was convicted of a complex crime of direct assault with homicide aggravated by the commission of the crime in a place where public authorities are engaged in the discharge of their duties. The penalty for homicide is reclusion temporal. On the other hand, the penalty for direct assault is prision correccional in its medium and maximum periods. What is the correct indeterminate penalty?  a) Twelve (12) years of prision mayor as minimum to twenty (20) years of reclusion temporal as maximum . b) Ten (10) years of prision mayor as minimum to seventeen (17) years and four (4) months of reclusion temporal as maximum. c) Eight (8) years of prision mayor as minimum to eighteen (18) years and four (4) months of reclusion temporal as maximum. d) Twelve (12) years of prision mayor as minimum to seventeen (17) years and four (4) months of reclusion temporal as maximum.",
        "Answer": "Twelve (12) years of prision mayor as minimum to twenty (20) years of reclusion temporal as maximum ."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 162,
        "Question": "What is the fundamental principle in applying and interpreting criminal laws, including the Indeterminate Sentence Law? How is the Indeterminate Sentence Law applied in imposing a sentence? ",
        "Answer": "The fundamental principle in interpreting and applying penal laws is the principle of pro reo... If crime is punishable under the RPC, the court shall sentence the accused to an indeterminate sentence the maximum term of which shall be that which, in view of the attending circumstance, could be properly imposed under the rules of the said Code, and the minimum of which shall be within the range of the penalty next lower to that prescribed by the Code for the offense. If the offense is punishable under a special law, the court shall sentence the accused to an indeterminate sentence, the maximum term of which shall not exceed the maximum fixed by said law, and the minimum shall not be less than the minimum term prescribed in the same."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 163,
        "Question": "Assuming a judgment of conviction (for homicide) and after considering the attendant circumstances, what penalty should the judge impose? (The background describes Bruno being entitled to two privileged mitigating circumstances of incomplete self-defense and the presence of at least two ordinary mitigating circumstances (voluntary surrender and plea of guilt) without any aggravating circumstance.) ",
        "Answer": "Bruno should be sentenced to an indeterminate sentence penalty of arresto mayor in any of its period to prision correccional in its medium period as maximum. Bruno was entitled to two privileged mitigating circumstances of incomplete self-defense and the presence of at least two ordinary mitigating circumstances (voluntary surrender and plea of guilt) without any aggravating circumstance under Art. 69 and 64(5) of the RPC respectively, which lowers the prescribed penalty for homicide which is reclusion temporal to prision correccional."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 164,
        "Question": "Who among the following convicts are not entitled to the benefits of the lndeterminate Sentence Law?  a) Those who are recidivists. b) Those whose maximum term of imprisonment exceeds one (1) year. c) Those convicted of inciting to sedition. d) Those convicted of misprision of treason.",
        "Answer": "Those who are recidivists."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 165,
        "Question": "In a conviction for homicide, the trial court appreciated two (2) mitigating circumstances and one (1) aggravating circumstance. Homicide under Article 249 of the Revised Penal Code is punishable by reclusion temporal, an imprisonment term of twelve (12) years and one (1) day to twenty (20) years. Applying the Indeterminate Sentence Law, determine the appropriate penalty to be imposed. Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Under the Indeterminate Sentence Law, the minimum of the sentence shall be anywhere within the range of 6 years and 1 day to 12 years imprisonment while the maximum of the sentence shall be anywhere within the range of Reclusion Temporal minimum i.e., not lower than 12 yrs. and 1 day to not more than 14 yrs. and 8 months."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 166,
        "Question": "Will your answer be the same if it is a conviction for illegal possession of drugs under R.A. 9165 (Dangerous Drugs Act of 2002), the prescribed penalty of which is also imprisonment for a term of twelve (12) years and one (1) day to twenty (20) years? Why or why not?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. My answer will not be the same because violations of Rep. Act 9165 are mala prohibita in which mitigating and aggravating circumstances are not appreciated. Although in People v. Simon... it was held that Art. 64 can be applied if the special law adopted the nomenclature of penalties provided under the RPC, such pronouncement cannot be applied in the instant case because the penalties for illegal possession of drugs under RA 9165 do not follow the technical nomenclature of penalties in the RPC and thus, cannot be divided into periods. Hence, the existence of mitigating and aggravating circumstances cannot be appreciated."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 167,
        "Question": "An agonizing and protracted trial having come to a close, the judge found A guilty beyond reasonable doubt of homicide and imposed on him a straight penalty of SIX (6) YEARS and ONE (1) day of prision mayor. The public prosecutor objected... The defense counsel chimed in... Who of the three is on the right track? Explain  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "None of the contentions is correct because the Indeterminate Sentence Law (Act 4103, as amended) has not been followed. The imposition of penalty for the crime of homicide, which is penalized by imprisonment exceeding one (1) year and is divisible, is covered by the Indeterminate Sentence Law. The said law requires that the sentence in this case should reflect a minimum term for purposes of parole, and a maximum term fixing the limit of the imprisonment. Imposing a straight penalty is incorrect."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 168,
        "Question": "Explain the application of the Indeterminate. Sentence Law (ISL).  ",
        "Answer": "The court shall sentence the accused to an indeterminate sentence the maximum term of which shall be that which, in view of the attending circumstances, could be properly imposed under the rules of the Revised Penal Code, and the minimum of which shall be within the range of the penalty next lower to that prescribed by the Code for the offense; and if the offense is punished by any other law (special law); the court shall sentence the accused to an indeterminate sentence, the maximum term of which shall not exceed the maximum fixed by said law, and the minimum shall not be less than the minimum term prescribed in the same (R.A. 4103, Sec. 1)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 169,
        "Question": "Because of the barbarity and the hideousness of the acts committed by the suspects/ respondents in cutting off their victims’ appendages... the Commission on Human Rights (CHR) investigating team recommended to the panel of public prosecutors that all respondents be charged with violation of the Heinous Crimes Law. As the chief prosecutor tasked with approving the filing of the information, how will you pass upon the recommendation? Explain?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The CHR is correct in describing the crimes committed as “heinous crimes”... despite the passage of Rep. Act No. 9346 prohibiting the imposition of the death penalty. However, the “Heinous Crimes Law” does not define crimes; it is only an amendatory law increasing the penalty for the crimes specified therein as heinous, to a maximum of death. Thus, the heinous crimes committed shall be prosecuted under the penal law they are respectively defined and penalized... The crime shall be designated as defined and punished under the penal law violated and the penalty shall be reclusion perpetua without the benefit of parole or life imprisonment without the benefit of parole, as the case maybe in lieu of the death penalty."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 170,
        "Question": "Roman was charged with, and was convicted of, five (5) counts of rape, but the judge did not impose the penalty of reclusion perpetua for each count. Instead, the judge sentenced Roman to 40 years of imprisonment on the basis of the three-fold rule. Was the judge correct? ",
        "Answer": "No, the three-fold rule is applicable only in connection with the service of the sentence not in the imposition of the proper penalties. The court must impose all penalties for all the crimes for which the accused have been found guilty... The computation under the three-fold rule is for the prison authorities to make."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 171,
        "Question": "Santos was sentenced to suffer imprisonment in three separate judgments... After his 20th year in the National Penitentiary, Santos filed a petition for habeas corpus claiming that he had fully served his sentence of 20 years and should therefore be immediately released from imprisonment. Was Santos correct? (A) Yes, because he served his sentences simultaneously so that his 20 years of incarceration was sufficient. (B) No, because multiple sentences are served successively not simultaneously. (Article 70, RPC) (C) No, only penalties other than imprisonment can be served simultaneously. (D) Yes, because after he has served the minimum of his penalties, he can now be released.",
        "Answer": "No, because multiple sentences are served successively not simultaneously. (Article 70, RPC)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 172,
        "Question": "Under which of the following circumstances is probation not applicable?  a) Probation is not applicable when the accused is sentenced to serve a maximum of six (6) years. b) Probation is not applicable when the accused has been convicted by final judgment of an offense punished by imprisonment of less than one (1) month and/or fine of less than P200.00. c) Probation is not applicable when accused is convicted of indirect assault. d) Probation is not applicable when accused is convicted of indirect bribery.",
        "Answer": "Probation is not applicable when the accused has been convicted by final judgment of an offense punished by imprisonment of less than one (1) month and/or fine of less than P200.00. [NOTE: In 2012, option c) 'Probation is not applicable when accused is convicted of indirect assault' was considered the correct answer as crimes against public order were excluded, though subsequent law amendments removed this specific disqualification.]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 173,
        "Question": "The period of probation of the offender sentenced to a term of one (1) year shall not exceed:  a) two (2) years; b) six (6) years; c) one (1) year; d) three (3) years.",
        "Answer": "two (2) years;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 174,
        "Question": "Andres was convicted of frustrated homicide... sentenced to 6 years and 1 day as minimum, to 8 years... Andres appealed his conviction to the Court of Appeals, which convicted him of attempted homicide, and sentenced him to 6 months of arresto mayor as minimum, to 4 years of prision correccional as maximum. Instead of appealing his conviction, Andres filed an application for probation... Is Andres qualified to avail of the benefits of the probation law?  (A) No, because when he filed a notice of appeal with the Court of Appeals, he waived his right under the probation law. (B) Yes, because after his appeal, he qualified for probation as the sentence imposed on him was less than 6 years. (C) Yes, because the probation law is meant to favor the accused. (D) No, because his previous sentence of more than 6 years disqualified him so that he can no longer avail of probation as an alternative remedy. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "Yes, because after his appeal, he qualified for probation as the sentence imposed on him was less than 6 years."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 175,
        "Question": "Juancho was convicted of Alarms and Scandals and sentenced to suffer a penalty of 1 month and 1 day of arresto mayor and a fine of P200. Is Juancho qualified for probation?  (A) Yes, because the penalty for alarms and scandals is less than six (6) years. (B) Yes, because Juancho did not appeal his conviction. (C) No, because the crime of alarms and scandals carries with it a fine of P200. (D) No, because the crime of alarms and scandals affects public order. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "No, because the crime of alarms and scandals affects public order."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 176,
        "Question": "Suppose Joe (17 years old, charged with homicide) was convicted of attempted murder with a special aggravating circumstance and was denied suspension of sentence, would he be eligible for probation under Presidential Decree (PD) 968, considering that the death penalty is imposable for the consummated felony? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. He would be eligible for probation because the penalty imposable on Joe will not exceed 6 years imprisonment. Even if it would be considered that the crime committed was punishable by death, the penalty as far as Joe is concerned can only be reclusion perpetua because Rep. Act 9344 forbids the imposition of the capital punishment upon offenders thereunder. The murder being attempted only, the prescribed penalty is two degree lower than reclusion perpetua; hence, prision mayor. Because Joe was 17 years old... the penalty of prision mayor should be lowered further by one degree because his minority is a privileged mitigating circumstance; hence, prision correccional or imprisonment within the range of six months and 1 day to 6 years is the imposable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 177,
        "Question": "Matt was found guilty of drug trafficking while his younger brother Jeff was found guilty of possession of equipment, instrument, apparatus and other paraphernalia for dangerous drugs under Section 12 of Republic Act No. 9165. Matt filed a petition for probation. Jeff appealed his conviction during the pendency of which he also filed a petition for probation. The brothers' counsel argued that they being first time offenders, their petitions for probation should be granted. How would you resolve the brothers' petitions for probation? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The brothers' petition for probation should both be denied. Matt's petition for probation shall be denied because he was convicted for drug-trafficking. Section 24 of RA 9165... expressly provides, 'Any person convicted for drug trafficking or pushing under this Act, regardless of the penalty imposed by the court, cannot avail of the privilege granted by the Probation Law...' On the other hand, Jeff's application for probation cannot also be entertained or granted because he has already appealed his conviction by the trial court (Section 4, P.D. 968, as amended)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 178,
        "Question": "A child in conflict with the law shall enjoy all the rights of a child until  (A) he is found to have acted with discernment. (B) his minority is setoff by some aggravating circumstance. (C) he is proved to be 18 years or older. (D) he forfeits such rights by gross misconduct and immorality.",
        "Answer": "he is proved to be 18 years or older."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 179,
        "Question": "Joe was 17 years old when he committed homicide in 2005... Since Republic Act 9344 (Juvenile Justice and Welfare Act of 2006) was already in effect, Joe moved to avail of the process of intervention or diversion. What is intervention or diversion? Is Joe entitled to intervention or diversion? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Intervention refers to a series of comprehensive measures to address the individualized problems of a child in conflict with the law... Diversion refers to an alternative, child-appropriate process of determining the responsibility and treatment of a child in conflict with the law... Yes. Joe is entitled to diversion. Being only 17 years old at the time he committed the crime of homicide, he is treated as a child in conflict with the law under RA 9344"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 180,
        "Question": "Suppose Joe's motion for intervention or diversion was denied, and he was convicted two (2) years later when Joe was already 21 years old, should the judge apply the suspension of sentence? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. The judge should not suspend sentence anymore because Joe was already 21 years old. Suspension of sentence is availing under Rep. Act 9344 only until a child reaches the maximum age of twenty-one (21) years."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 181,
        "Question": "Tiburcio was convicted for Estafa by the RTC. The decision was affirmed by the Court of Appeals and an Entry of Judgment was subsequently issued. Before the service of his sentence, Tiburcio died. His counsel filed a Motion to Dismiss the case. Should the RTC grant the Motion to Dismiss the case? Explain. [Part a] ",
        "Answer": "The RTC may not grant the motion to dismiss because the Court of Appeals, having issued an Entry of Judgment, the decision has become final and executory. However, the pecuniary penalty, such as the civil liability arising from the crime consisting of actual damages of P25,000 survives the death of Tiburcio."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 182,
        "Question": "Assuming that Tiburcio's death occurred before the Court of Appeals rendered its decision, will you give a different answer? [Part b] ",
        "Answer": "Yes. The RTC decision must be set aside and the case against Tiburcio must consequently be dismissed. The demise of Tiburcio which occurred before the Court of Appeals rendered its decision causes his criminal liability, as well as his civil liability ex delicto, to be totally extinguished inasmuch as there is no longer a defendant to stand as the accused, the civil action is instituted therein for recovery of civil liability ex delicto is ipso facto extinguished, grounded as it is on criminal case."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 183,
        "Question": "AAA was convicted of theft by a Manila Court and sentenced to a straight penalty of one (1) year of prision correccional. After serving two (2) months of the sentence, he was granted conditional pardon by the Chief Executive. One of the conditions of the pardon was for him not to be found guilty of any crime punishable by the laws of the country. He subsequently committed robbery in Pasay City. Can the Manila Court require AAA to serve the unexpired portion of the original sentence? ",
        "Answer": "No. AAA must first be found guilty of the subsequent offense before he can be prosecuted for violation of conditional pardon."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 184,
        "Question": "Taylor was convicted of a violation of the Election Code... Taylor failed to appear when summoned for execution of judgment... Taylor was able to use the backdoor and left for the United States. Fifteen years later, Taylor returned... and filed a Motion to Quash the warrant of arrest... on the ground that the penalty imposed against him had already prescribed. If you were the judge, would you grant Taylor's Motion to Quash? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "If I were the judge, I will deny the motion to quash. Article 93 of the Revised Penal Code provides when the prescription of penalties shall commence to run... it shall commence to run from the date the felon evades the service of his sentence... Taylor never served a single minute of his sentence, and thus, prescription never started to run in his favor. Clearly, one who has not been committed to prison cannot be said to have escaped therefrom."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 185,
        "Question": "Assuming that instead of the United States, Taylor was able to go to another country with which the Philippines had no extradition treaty, will your answer be the same? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Even if Taylor was able to go to another country which the Philippines had no extradition treaty, I will deny the motion to quash. Going to a foreign country with which this Government has no extradition treaty to interrupt the running of prescription is not applicable nor even material because the period of prescription is not applicable nor runs in favor of the offender until he evades service of sentence. Since he never served, he could not have evaded."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 186,
        "Question": "Baldo killed his wife on January 2, 1960. Baldo concealed the body of his wife in an unused septic tank, which was discovered by the police 10 years later. Baldo was arrested and charged with the crime of Murder on January 6, 1980. Baldo contended that the crime had already prescribed, as 20 years had lapsed from the commission of the crime. Is Baldo's contention correct? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, Baldo's contention is not correct because the crime committed has not yet prescribed. The prescriptive period of the crime committed commenced to run only after it was reported to the police on January 2, 1970, not on the date it was clandestinely committed on January 2, 1960. Under the discovery rule, which governs when a crime is not publicly committed, the prescriptive period of a crime commences to run only from the day on which the crime is discovered by the offended party, the authorities or their agents: in this case, from January 2, 1970 when it was made known to the police authorities until January 6, 1980, when Baldo was arrested and charged."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 187,
        "Question": "Under the Revised Penal Code, when does the period of prescription of a crime commence to run?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Generally, the period of prescription of a crime commences to run from the date it was committed; but if the crime was committed clandestinely, the period of prescription of the crimes under the Revised Penal Code commence to run from the day on which the crime was discovered by the offended party, the authorities or their agents (Art 91, RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 188,
        "Question": "When is the prescriptive period of a crime interrupted?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The running of the prescriptive period of the crime is interrupted when any kind of investigative proceeding is instituted against the guilty person which may ultimately lead to his prosecution (Panaguiton, Jr. v. Dept. of Justice, G.R. No. 167571, Nov. 25, 2008)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 189,
        "Question": "A killed his wife and buried her body in their backyard. Ten years later, a care-taker found the bones and reported the matter to the police. A was subsequently arrested. Is A's defense of prescription of the crime tenable? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, the defense of prescription of the crime is not tenable. The crime committed is parricide which prescribes in twenty (20) years (Art 90, RPC). It was only when the care-taker, Z, found the victim's bones and reported the matter to the police that the crime is deemed legally discovered by the authorities or their agents and thus the prescriptive period of the crime commenced to run."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 190,
        "Question": "Senator Adamos was convicted of plunder... the President of the Philippines granted him absolute pardon... The signed pardon states: 'I hereby grant absolute pardon unto Adamos, who was convicted of plunder... and upon whom the penalty of reclusion perpetua was imposed.' He now wants to know if he could run for senator in the next election. What advice will you give Adamos? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "I will give him the advice that he cannot run in the Senatorial race since the terms of the pardon has not expressly restored his right to hold public office or remitted the accessory penalty of perpetual absolute disqualification. Under Article 36 of the Revised Penal Code, a pardon shall not work the restoration of the right to hold public office unless such right be expressly restored by terms of the pardon. Under Article 41, the penalty of reclusion perpetua shall carry with it perpetual absolute disqualification which the offender shall suffer even though pardoned as to the principal penalty, unless the same shall have been expressly remitted in the pardon."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 191,
        "Question": "Assuming that what Adamos committed was heading a rebellion for which he was imposed the same penalty of reclusion perpetua, and what he received was amnesty from the government, will your answer be the same (regarding running for Senator)? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "If Senator Adamos was convicted of rebellion and he received amnesty, I will give him the advice that he can run in the Senatorial race. Under Article 89 of the Revised Penal Code, criminal liability is totally extinguished by amnesty, which completely extinguishes the penalty and all its effects. Thus, the amnesty extinguishes not only the principal penalty of reclusion perpetua but also its effects such as the accessory penalty of perpetual absolute disqualification."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 192,
        "Question": "Antero Makabayan was convicted of the crime of Rebellion. While serving sentence, he escaped from jail. Captured, he was charged with, and convicted of, Evasion of Service of Sentence. Thereafter, the President of the Philippines issued an amnesty proclamation for the offense of Rebellion. Antero applied for and was granted the benefit of the amnesty proclamation. Antero then filed a petition for habeas corpus, praying for his immediate release from confinement. He claims that the amnesty extends to the offense of evasion of Service of Sentence. As judge, will you grant the petition? Discuss fully. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes, I will grant the petition because the sentence that was evaded proceeded from the crime of Rebellion which has been obliterated by the grant of amnesty to the offender. Since the amnesty erased the criminal complexion of the act committed by the offender as a crime of rebellion and rendered such act as though innocent, the sentence lost its legal basis. The purported evasion thereof therefore cannot subsist. Amnesty obliterates, not only the basis of conviction, but also all the legal effects thereof."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 193,
        "Question": "Insuperable cause is an exempting circumstance which may be applied to  (A) robbery. (B) misprision of treason. (C) homicide. (D) rebellion.",
        "Answer": "misprision of treason."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 194,
        "Question": "Which of the following circumstances may be appreciated as aggravating in the crime of treason?  a) cruelty and ignominy; b) evident premeditation; c) superior strength; d) treachery.",
        "Answer": "cruelty and ignominy;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 195,
        "Question": "What is the crime committed by a public officer who discloses to the representative of a foreign nation the contents of the articles, data or information of a confidential nature relative to the defense of the Philippine archipelago which he has in his possession by reason of the public office he holds?  a) espionage; b) disloyalty; c) treason; d) violation of neutrality.",
        "Answer": "espionage;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 196,
        "Question": "Can the crime of treason be committed only by a Filipino citizen?  a) Yes. The offender in the crime of treason is a Filipino citizen only because the first element is that the offender owes allegiance to the Government of the Philippines. b) No. The offender in the crime of treason is either a Filipino citizen or a foreigner married to a Filipino citizen, whether residing in the Philippines or elsewhere, who adheres to the enemies of the Philippines, giving them aid or comfort. c) No. The offender in the crime of treason is either a Filipino citizen or an alien residing in the Philippines because while permanent allegiance is owed by the alien to his own country, he owes a temporary allegiance to the Philippines where he resides. d) Yes. It is not possible for an alien, whether residing in the Philippines or elsewhere, to commit the crime of treason because he owes allegiance to his own country.",
        "Answer": "No. The offender in the crime of treason is either a Filipino citizen or an alien residing in the Philippines because while permanent allegiance is owed by the alien to his own country, he owes a temporary allegiance to the Philippines where he resides."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 197,
        "Question": "Three persons (Max, Baldo and Bogart) boarded an inter-island vessel anchored in the harbor of Kaoshiung, Taiwan. Max and Baldo were armed with knives while Bogart had a handheld radio. They threatened the passengers with bodily harm and divested them of their money and jewelry. They seized the vessel and forced the captain to sail to a small island in Palawan where they disembarked and divided the loot. Was the charge of qualified piracy against the three persons correct? Explain. (4%) (2008 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The charge is correct. Qualified Piracy was committed when the offenders seized the vessel by firing on or boarding the same. In the problem, they even went further by divesting the passengers of their money and jewelry. The vessel was anchored in the harbor of Kaoshiung, Taiwan and it is submitted that the crime was committed within the territorial jurisdiction of another country. The Supreme Court has ruled that the high seas contemplated under Art. 122 of the Revised Penal Code includes the three-mile limit of any state... Moreover, piracy is an offense that can be tried anywhere because it is a crime against the Law of Nations."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 198,
        "Question": "Because peace negotiations on the Spratlys situation had failed, the People's Republic of China declared war against the Philippines. Myra, a Filipina who lives with her Italian expatriate boyfriend, discovered e-mail correspondence between him and a certain General Tung Kat Su of China... Myra discovered that... her boyfriend had sent an e-mail... in which he agreed to provide vital information on the military defense of the Philippines to the Chinese government in exchange for P1 million and his safe return to Italy. Two weeks later, Myra decided to report the matter to the proper authorities. Did Myra commit a crime? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes, Myra committed the crime of Misprision of Treason under Art. 116 of the Revised Penal Code, for failing to report or make known as soon as possible to the governor or provincial fiscal or to the mayor or fiscal of the City where she resides, the conspiracy between her Italian boyfriend and the Chinese General to commit treason against the Philippine Government in time of war. She decided to report the matter to the proper authorities only after two (2) weeks."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 199,
        "Question": "Three sea pirates, armed with unlicensed firearms, boarded a Philippine registered vessel while it was sailing in the high seas. They seized the whole cargo of the vessel, consisting of several crates containing valuable items, loaded them in their own motorboat, and immediately sailed away. What crime or crimes, if any, were committed? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "The crime of Qualified Piracy under Article 123 of the Revised Penal Code has been committed, the elements of piracy being present, namely, (1) that the vessel is on the high seas; (2) that the offenders are not members of its complement or passenger of the vessel; and (3) that the offenders (a) attack or seize that vessel or (b) seize the whole or part of the cargo of said vessel, its equipment or personal belongings of its complement or passengers. The latter act is committed when the offenders took away several crates containing valuable items and loaded them in their own motorboat."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 200,
        "Question": "A postal van containing mail matters, including checks and treasury warrants, was hijacked along a national highway by ten (10) men, two (2) of whom were armed. They used force, violence and intimidation against three (3) postal employees who were occupants of the van, resulting in the unlawful taking and transportation of the entire van and its contents. If you were the public prosecutor, would you charge the ten (10) men who hijacked the postal van with violation of Presidential Decree No. 532, otherwise known as the Anti-Piracy and Anti -Highway Robbery Law of 1974? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "Yes. The ten (10) men who hijacked the postal van should be charged with highway robbery, which is punished under P.D. 532. All the elements of highway robbery are present: (1) there is unlawful taking of personal property belonging to another (the mail van and its contents); (2) the taking is by means of violence against or intimidation of person or force upon things (used force, violence, and intimidation against the postal employees who were occupants of the van); (3) the commission is committed on any Philippine highway (along a national highway); and (4) the perpetrators are highway robbers or brigands (at least 4 armed persons commit the crime)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 201,
        "Question": "If you were the defense counsel, what are the elements of the crime of highway robbery that the prosecution should prove to sustain a conviction? ",
        "Answer": "The elements of highway robbery are: (1) The seizure of any person for ransom, extortion or other unlawful purposes, or the taking away of the property of another by means of violence against or intimidation of person or force upon things or other unlawful means; and (2) The commission is committed by any person on any Philippine highway."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 202,
        "Question": "Compelling the pilot of an aircraft of Philippine Registry to change its destination is __________.  (A) grave coercion (B) a violation of the Anti-Hijacking Law or R.A. No. 6235 (C) grave threats (D) a violation of the Human Security Act of 2007 or the Anti-Terrorism Law (E) All of the above.",
        "Answer": "a violation of the Anti-Hijacking Law or R.A. No. 6235"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 203,
        "Question": "Policeman Stone approached a priest during mass and displayed his firearm and threatened the priest because of the priest's statements during his homily, which caused the disruption of the mass and the leaving of the congregation. May Policeman Stone be properly charged with either or both of the following crimes: (a) Interruption of religious worship as defined and punished under Art. 132 of the Revised Penal Code; and/or (b) Offending the religious feelings as defined and punished under Art. 133 of the Revised Penal Code. Explain fully your answers. (8%) (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "(a) Policeman Slone may be charged with Interruption of religious worship. Under the Revised Penal Code, a public officer or employee who shall prevent or disturb the ceremonies or manifestations of any religion shall be liable for interruption of religious worship... (b) Policeman Stone may not be charged with the crime or offending religious feelings. The Supreme Court has ruled that the acts must be directed against religious practice or dogma or ritual for the purpose or ridicule... Policeman Stone threatened the priest because of the priest's statements during his homily and not to mock or ridicule the ceremony; consequently, Policeman Stone may not be charged with the crime of offending religious feelings."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 204,
        "Question": "What is the criminal liability, if any, of a mayor who, without being authorized by law, compels prostitutes residing in his city to go to, and live in, another place against their will?  a) The mayor is criminally liable for violation of domicile. b) The mayor is criminally liable for expulsion. c) The mayor is criminally liable for Grave coercion. d) The mayor incurs no criminal liability because he merely wants to protect the youth against the indecency of the prostitutes.",
        "Answer": "The mayor is criminally liable for Grave coercion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 205,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. A policeman who, without a judicial order, enters a private house over the owner's opposition is guilty of trespass to dwelling.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. The crime committed by the policeman in this case is violation of domicile because the official duties of a policeman carry with it an authority to make searches and seizure upon judicial order. He is therefore acting under color of his official authority (Art. 128, RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 206,
        "Question": "X, a police officer, placed a hood on the head of W, a suspected drug pusher, and watched as Y and Z, police trainees, beat up and tortured W to get his confession. X is liable as  (A) as accomplice in violation of the Anti-Torture Act. (B) a principal in violation of the Anti-Torture Act. (C) a principal in violation of the Anti-Hazing Law. (D) an accomplice in violation of the Anti-Hazing Law.",
        "Answer": "a principal in violation of the Anti-Torture Act."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 207,
        "Question": "What is the proper charge against public officers or employees who, being in conspiracy with the rebels, failed to resist a rebellion by all means in their power, or shall continue to discharge the duties of their offices under the control of the rebels, or shall accept appointment to office under them?  a) disloyalty of public officers or employees; b) rebellion; c) conspiracy to commit rebellion; d) dereliction of duty.",
        "Answer": "disloyalty of public officers or employees;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 208,
        "Question": "What is the proper charge against a person who, without taking arms or being in open hostility against the Government, shall incite others to deprive Congress of its legislative powers, by means of speeches or writings?  a) inciting to sedition; b) inciting to rebellion or insurrection; c) crime against legislative body; d) unlawful use of means of publication or unlawful utterances.",
        "Answer": "inciting to rebellion or insurrection"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 209,
        "Question": "What is the crime committed when a group of persons entered the municipal building rising publicly and taking up arms in pursuance of the movement to prevent exercise of governmental authority with respect to the residents of the municipality concerned for the purpose of effecting changes in the manner of governance and removing such locality under their control from allegiance to the laws of the Government?  a) rebellion or insurrection; b) sedition; c) coup d'etat; d) illegal assembly.",
        "Answer": "rebellion or insurrection;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 210,
        "Question": "What is the proper charge against a group of four persons who, without public uprising, employ force to prevent the holding of any popular election?  a) sedition; b) disturbance of public order; c) grave coercion; d) direct assault.",
        "Answer": "grave coercion;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 211,
        "Question": "A, B, and C organized a meeting in which the audience was incited to the commission of the crime of sedition. Some of the persons present at the meeting were carrying unlicensed firearms. What crime, if any, was committed by A, B, and C, as well as those who were carrying unlicensed firearms and those who were merely present at the meeting?  a) Inciting to sedition for A, B and C and illegal possession of firearms for those carrying unlicensed firearms. b) Inciting to sedition for A, B and C and those carrying unlicensed firearms. c) Illegal assembly for A, B, C and all those present at the meeting. d) Conspiracy to commit sedition for A, B, C and those present at the meeting.",
        "Answer": "Inciting to sedition for A, B and C and illegal possession of firearms for those carrying unlicensed firearms."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements constitute Inciting to Sedition?  (A) Utterance of statements irritating or obnoxious to the ears of the police officers. (B) Speeches extolling communism and urging the people to hold a national strike and paralyze commerce and trade. (C) Leaders of jeepney and bus associations shouting Bukas tuloy ang welga hanggang sa magkagulo na! (D) Speeches calling for resignation of high government officials.",
        "Answer": "Speeches extolling communism and urging the people to hold a national strike and paralyze commerce and trade."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 213,
        "Question": "A public officer who immediately returns the bribe money handed over to him commits  (A) no crime. (B) attempted bribery. (C) consummated bribery. (D) frustrated bribery.",
        "Answer": "no crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 214,
        "Question": "Dr. Chow, a government doctor, failed to submit his Daily Time Record (DTR)... The medical Director caused the withholding of his salary... Can Dr. Chow prosecute the medical director for causing him undue injury in violation of the Anti-Graft and Corrupt Practices Act? ",
        "Answer": "No, since Dr. Chow brought it upon himself, having failed to submit the required DTRs."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 215,
        "Question": "In malversation of public funds, the offender’s return of the amount malversed has the following effect  (A) It is exculpatory. (B) It is inculpatory, an admission of the commission of the crime. (C) The imposable penalty will depend on what was not returned. (D) It is mitigating.",
        "Answer": "It is mitigating."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 216,
        "Question": "Direct bribery is a crime involving moral turpitude. From which of the following elements of direct bribery can moral turpitude be inferred?  (A) The offender receives a gift by himself or through another. (B) The offender is a public officer. (C) The offender takes a gift with a view to committing a crime in exchange. (D) The act which the offender agrees to perform or which he executes is connected with his official duties.",
        "Answer": "The offender takes a gift with a view to committing a crime in exchange."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 217,
        "Question": "Mr. Gray opened a savings account... deposited a check for P200,000.00 drawn from Bank B and endorsed by Mr. White... Mr. Gray withdrew the P200,000.00... Mr. White later complained... his signature thereon was forged. Mr. Gray subsequently deposited another check signed by Mr. White for P200,000.00, which amount he later withdrew. Mr. Gray was convicted of estafa and attempted estafa, both through the use of commercial documents. Mr. Gray claims as defense that, except for Mr. White’s claim of forgery, there was no evidence showing that he was the author of the forgery and Mr. White did not suffer any injuries as to the second check (attempted estafa). Rule on the defense of Mr. Gray. ",
        "Answer": "The first defense of Mr. Gray that there was no evidence showing that he was the author of the forgery has no merit. The law presumes that the possessor and user of a falsified document is the falsifier or forger thereof. Likewise, his second defense that Mr. White did not suffer any injuries as to the second check (attempted estafa) has no merit. Damage or intent to cause damage is not considered in attempted estafa. It is considered only in consummated estafa."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 218,
        "Question": "Mr. Gray claims that he was entrapped illegally because there was no showing that the second check was a forgery and, therefore, his withdrawal based on the second check was a legal act. Is Mr. Gray correct? ",
        "Answer": "No, Mr. Gray is not correct. Entrapment is a means used to enforce criminal laws and is distinguishable from instigation... Since the accused performed the criminal act, the illegal entrapment defense would not apply."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 219,
        "Question": "The guard was entrusted with the conveyance or custody of a detention prisoner who escaped through his negligence. What is the criminal liability of the escaping prisoner?  a) The escaping prisoner does not incur criminal liability. b) The escaping prisoner is liable for evasion through negligence. c) The escaping prisoner is liable for conniving with or consenting to, evasion. d) The escaping prisoner is liable for evasion of service of sentence.",
        "Answer": "The escaping prisoner does not incur criminal liability."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 220,
        "Question": "Dancio, a member of a drug syndicate, was a detention prisoner... Brusco, another member of the syndicate, regularly visited Dancio. Edri, the guard in charge who had been receiving gifts from Brusco... became relaxed in the inspection of his belongings... Brusco... smuggled in a pistol which Dancio used to disarm the guards and destroy the padlock... enabling Dancio to escape. What crime(s) did Dancio, Brusco and Edri commit? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Dancio committed the crime of direct assault under Article 148 for disarming the guards with the use of pistol while they are engaged in the performance of their duties... Edri committed infidelity in the custody of prisoner or evasion through negligence under Article 224... By accepting gifts from Brusco... he is also guilty of indirect bribery under Article 211. Brusco committed delivery of prisoner from jail under Article 156, qualified by his bribery of Edri."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 221,
        "Question": "Miss Reyes, a lady professor, caught Mariano, one of her students, cheating... Mariano approached Miss Reyes and without any warning, slapped her on the face... Mariano then turned his ire on Dencio and punched him repeatedly, causing him injuries. What crime or crimes, if any, did Mariano commit? (2013, 2002, 1993)",
        "Answer": "Mariano is liable for two counts of direct assault. First, when he slapped Miss Reyes, who is a person in authority... Second, when he repeatedly punched Dencio, who became an agent of the person in authority when he came to the aid of a person in authority, Miss Reyes."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 222,
        "Question": "General Tejero and his men staged an uprising against the government and barricaded themselves in a hotel. The general issued a statement that they will lay down their arms if the President, Vice President and Cabinet members will resign. What crime did General Tejero and his men commit?  (A) Rebellion complexed with serious illegal detention and estafa. (B) Rebellion. (C) Coup d'etat. (D) Terrorism. (E) None of the above",
        "Answer": "Coup d'etat."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 223,
        "Question": "Rigoberto gate-crashed the 71st birthday party of Judge Lorenzo. Armed with a piece of wood... Rigoberto hit Judge Lorenzo on the back... Judge Lorenzo had cited Rigoberto in contempt and ordered his imprisonment for three (3) days two years earlier. Is Rigoberto guilty of Direct Assault? Why or why not?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, Rigoberto is not guilty of Direct Assault because Judge Lorenzo has ceased to be a judge when he was attacked. He has retired (71 yrs. old) from his position as a person in authority when he was attacked. Hence, the attack on him cannot be regarded as against a person in authority anymore."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 224,
        "Question": "Would your answer be the same if the reason for the attack was that when Judge Lorenzo was still a practicing lawyer ten years ago, he prosecuted Rigoberto and succeeded in sending him to jail for one year? Explain your answer.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. Rigoberto is guilty of Direct Assault because the employment of violence was by reason of an actual performance of a duty by the offended party acting as a practicing lawyer. Lawyers are considered persons in authority by virtue of Batas Pambansa Big. 873... But the crime having been committed 10 years ago, may have already prescribed because it is punishable by a correctional penalty."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 225,
        "Question": "X, Y and Z agreed among themselves to attack and kill A, a police officer, but they left their home-made guns in their vehicle before approaching him. What crime have they committed?  (A) Conspiracy to commit indirect assault. (B) Attempted direct assault. (C) Conspiracy to commit direct assault. (D) Illegal possession of firearms.",
        "Answer": "Conspiracy to commit direct assault."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 226,
        "Question": "What is the criminal liability, if any, of a physician who issues a false medical certificate in connection with the practice of his profession?  a) The physician is criminally liable for falsification of medical certificate. b) The physician is criminally liable if the false medical certificate is used in court. c) The physician incurs no criminal liability if the false medical certificate is not submitted to the court. d) The physician incurs no criminal liability if the false medical certificate does not cause prejudice or damage.",
        "Answer": "The physician is criminally liable for falsification of medical certificate."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 227,
        "Question": "The baptism of A was solemnized by B, an ecclesiastical minister, in the absence of C, one of the godparents... Upon request of the mother of A, B caused the inclusion of the name of C in the baptismal certificate of A as one of the godparents and allowed a proxy for C during the baptismal ceremony. What is the criminal liability, if any, of the ecclesiastical minister?  a) The ecclesiastical minister is criminally liable for falsification of baptismal certificate by causing it to appear that C participated in the baptismal ceremony when he did not in fact so participate. b) The ecclesiastical minister is not criminally liable because the insertion of the name of C in the baptismal certificate will not affect the civil status of A. c) The ecclesiastical minister is not criminally liable because he is not a public officer, employee or notary. d) The ecclesiastical minister is not criminally liable because he did not take advantage of his official position nor cause damage to a third party.",
        "Answer": "The ecclesiastical minister is criminally liable for falsification of baptismal certificate by causing it to appear that C participated in the baptismal ceremony when he did not in fact so participate."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 228,
        "Question": "Erwin and Bea approached Mayor Abral and requested him to solemnize their marriage... Mayor Abral was not there. Donato, his chief of staff, solemnized the marriage and later turned over the documents to Mayor Abral for his signature. In the marriage contract, it was stated that the marriage was solemnized by Mayor Abral. What crime(s) did Mayor Abral and Donato commit? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Mayor Abral is liable for falsification of public document by a public officer under Article 171. Making an untruthful statement by stating in a marriage contract, a public document, that the marriage was solemnized by him, is an act of falsification. Donato committed the crime of usurpation of function under Article 177 of the Revised Penal Code because he performed the act of solemnizing marriage, which pertained to the mayor, a person in authority, without being lawfully entitled to do so."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 229,
        "Question": "Andrea applied for a loan from a bank and submitted a Deed of Absolute Sale, which was registered in her name, as collateral. It turned out that the signature of her mother-in-law in the Deed of Absolute Sale was forged by Andrea's husband, and her mother-in-law suffered damage. Andrea's appeal is based on her claim of absence of criminal intent and of good faith. Should she be found guilty of falsification? Discuss briefly.",
        "Answer": "Andrea should be held guilty of falsification of public documents. Her claim of absence of criminal intent and of good faith cannot be considered because she is presumed to know that her husband is dead. The element of damage required in falsification does not refer to pecuniary damage but damage to public interest."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 230,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. For a person who transacts an instrument representing the proceeds of a covered unlawful activity to be liable under the Anti-Money Laundering Act (R.A. 9160, as amended), it must be shown that he has knowledge of the identities of the culprits involved in the commission of the predicate crimes.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. There is nothing in the law which requires that the accused must know the identities of the culprits involved in the commission of the predicate crimes. To establish liability under RA 9160, it is sufficient that proceeds of an unlawful activity are transacted, making them appear to have originated from legitimate sources."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 231,
        "Question": "There being probable cause to believe that certain deposits and investments in a bank are related to an unlawful activity of smuggling by Alessandro... an application for an order to allow inquiry into his deposit was filed with the Regional Trial Court. After hearing the application, the court granted the application and issued a freeze order. Pass upon the correctness of the court’s order. Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The freeze order issued by the Regional Trial Court is not correct, because jurisdiction to issue said freeze order is now vested with the Court of Appeals under Rep Act 9194, amending the Anti-Money Laundering Act (Rep. Act No. 9160). The Regional Trial Court is without jurisdiction to issue a freeze order of the money involved."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 232,
        "Question": "Define Money laundering. What are the three (3) stages in money laundering?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Money Laundering is the process by which a person conceals the existence of unlawfully obtained money and makes it appear to have originated from lawful sources. The intention behind such a transaction is to hide the beneficial owner of said funds and allows criminal organizations or criminals to enjoy proceeds of such criminal activities.” The three (3) stages in money laundering are: 1. Placement/ infusion or the physical disposal of criminal proceeds 2. Layering or the separation of the criminal proceeds from their source... 3. Integration or the provision of apparent legitimacy to the criminal proceeds."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 233,
        "Question": "Two informations were filed against Solito in the RTC – one for forcible abduction with rape... the other for illegal sale of drugs... Was Solito charged with the proper offenses based on the circumstances? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The charge of rape through forcible abduction is correct. The rule is settled that if the main objective of the accused is to rape the victim, the crime is rape even if he abducted for her forcefully. Forcible abduction is absorbed. The doctrine of absorption rather than Article 48 of RPC is applicable since forcible abduction is an indispensable is an indispensable means to commit rape... If forcible abduction, however, is a necessary means to commit rape, this is a complex crime proper under Article 48 of RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 234,
        "Question": "While the Prosecution was presenting its evidence in Branch 29 (illegal sale of drugs), Branch 8 (forcible abduction with rape) convicted Solito. Immediately after the judgment of conviction was promulgated, Solito filed in both Branches a motion for the release of the Toyota Innova. He argued and proved that he had only borrowed the vehicle from his brother, the registered owner. Branch 8 granted the motion but Branch 29 denied it. Were the two courts correct in their rulings? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Yes. The two courts were correct in their rulings. Under Article 45 of the Revised Penal Code... every penalty imposed for the commission of a felony shall include the forfeiture of the instruments or tools with which the crime was committed, unless they be the property of a third person not liable for the offense... Hence, the determination of whether it will be forfeited could be made only when judgment is rendered. In this case, the RTC Branch 8 already rendered a judgment of conviction against Solito... Solito was able to prove that the car belonged to his brother who was not charged with forcible abduction with rape; hence, it was correct for the RTC branch 8 to order the release... On the other hand, Section 20 of R.A. No. 9165 states in part... no property... which may be confiscated and forfeited, shall be disposed... while the trial is still ongoing... The RTC Branch 29, thus was correct in denying Solito’s motion to release the Toyota Innova considering that the trial for illegal sale of drugs is still ongoing."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 235,
        "Question": "Amelia, a famous actress, bought the penthouse unit of a posh condominium... Every night, Amelia would swim naked in the private, but open air, pool of her penthouse unit. It must have been obvious to Amelia that she could be seen from nearby buildings... some residents... did indeed entertain themselves and their friends by watching her swim in the nude from their windows. What crime did Amelia commit?  (A) Alarms and scandals because her act of swimmmg naked disturbs the public tranquility. (B) Grave scandal because she committed highly scandalous acts that are offensive to decency or good customs. (C) Immoral doctrines, obscene publications and exhibitions, and indecent shows under Article 201 of the Revised Penal Code... (D) Amelia did not commit any crime because the swimming pool is located in her private home.",
        "Answer": "Grave scandal because she committed highly scandalous acts that are offensive to decency or good customs."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 236,
        "Question": "When the adoption of a child is effected under the Inter-Country Adoption Act for the purpose of prostitution, what is the proper charge against the offender who is a public officer in relation to the exploitative purpose?  a) acts that promote trafficking in persons; b) trafficking in persons; c) qualified trafficking in persons; d) use of trafficked person.",
        "Answer": "qualified trafficking in persons;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 237,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by a public officer who, having control of public funds or property by reason of the duties of his office and for which he is accountable, permits any other person through abandonment to take such public funds or property?  a) The public officer commits malversation. b) The public officer commits technical malversation. c) The public officer commits the crime of failure of accountable or responsible officer to render accounts. d) The public officer commits the crime of failure to make delivery of public funds or property.",
        "Answer": "The public officer commits malversation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 238,
        "Question": "What is the criminal liability, if any, of a police officer who, while Congress was in session, arrested a member thereof for committing a crime punishable by a penalty higher than prision mayor?  a) The police officer is criminally liable for violation of parliamentary immunity because a member of Congress is privileged from arrest while Congress is in session. b) The police officer is criminally liable for disturbance of proceedings because the arrest was made while Congress was in session. c) The police officer incurs no criminal liability because the member of Congress has committed a crime punishable by a penalty higher than prision mayor . d) The police officer is criminally liable for violation of parliamentary immunity because parliamentary immunity guarantees a member of Congress complete freedom of expression without fear of being arrested while in regular or special session.",
        "Answer": "The police officer incurs no criminal liability because the member of Congress has committed a crime punishable by a penalty higher than prision mayor ."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 239,
        "Question": "AA was appointed for a two-year term to serve the unexpired portion of a resigned public official. Despite being disqualified after the lapse of the two-year term, AA continued to exercise the duties and powers of the public office to which appointed. What is the criminal liability of AA?  a) AA is criminally liable for malfeasance in office. b) AA is criminally liable for prolonging performance of duties and powers. c) AA is criminally liable for disobeying request for disqualification. d) AA incurs no criminal liability because there is no indication that he caused prejudice to anyone.",
        "Answer": "AA is criminally liable for prolonging performance of duties and powers."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 240,
        "Question": "What crime is committed when a person assumes the performance of duties and powers of a public office or employment without first being sworn in?  a) anticipation of duties of a public office; b) usurpation of authority; c) prohibited transaction; d) unlawful appointment.",
        "Answer": "anticipation of duties of a public office;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 241,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by a public officer who, before the acceptance of his resignation, shall abandon his office to the detriment of the public service in order to evade the discharge of the duties of preventing, prosecuting or punishing the crime of treason?  a) abandonment of office or position; b) qualified abandonment of office; c) misprision of treason; d) negligence in the prosecution of offense.",
        "Answer": "qualified abandonment of office;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 242,
        "Question": "A jailer inflicted injury on the prisoner because of his personal grudge against the latter. The injury caused illness of the prisoner for more than thirty (30) days. What is the proper charge against the jailer?  a) The jailer should be charged with maltreatment of prisoner and serious physical injuries. b) The jailer should be charged with serious physical injuries only. c) The jailer should be charged with complex crime of maltreatment of prisoner with serious physical injuries. d) The jailer should be charged with maltreatment of prisoner only.",
        "Answer": "The jailer should be charged with serious physical injuries only."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 243,
        "Question": "What is the proper charge against a lawyer who reveals the secrets of his client learned by him in his professional capacity?  a) The lawyer should be charged with revelation of secrets of private individual. b) The lawyer should be charged with betrayal of trust. c) The lawyer should be charged with unauthorized revelation of classified materials. d) The proper charge against the lawyer should be revealing secrets with abuse of office.",
        "Answer": "The lawyer should be charged with revelation of secrets of private individual."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 244,
        "Question": "A typhoon destroyed the houses of many of the inhabitants of X Municipality... Mayor Maawain approved the withdrawal of ten boxes of food from X Municipality's feeding program, which were given to the families of the beneficiaries of the shelter assistance program. The appropriations for the funds pertaining to the shelter assistance program and those for the feeding program were separate items... What crime did Mayor Maawain commit? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Mayor Maawain committed the crime of Illegal use of public funds or property punishable under Article 220 of the RPC. This offense is also known as Technical Malversation. The crime has 3 elements: a.) that the offender is an accountable public officer; b) that he applies public funds or property under his administration to some public use; and c) that the public use for which such funds or property were applied is different from the purpose for which they were originally appropriated by law or ordinance."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 245,
        "Question": "May Mayor Maawain invoke the defense of good faith and that he had no evil intent when he approved the transfer of the boxes of food from the feeding program to the shelter assistance program? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "No. Mayor Maawain cannot invoke good faith when he approved the transfer of the boxes of food... “Criminal intent is not an element of technical malversation. The law punishes the act of diverting public property earmarked by law or ordinance for a particular purpose to another public purpose. The offense is mala prohibita, meaning that the prohibited act is not inherently immoral but becomes a criminal offense because positive law forbids its commission based on considerations of public policy, order and convenience... Hence, malice or criminal intent is completely irrelevant.”"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 246,
        "Question": "Filthy, a very rich businessman, convinced Loko, a clerk of court, to issue an order of release for Takas, Filthy’s cousin, who was in jail for a drug charge. After receiving P500,000.00, Loko forged the signature of the judge on the order of release and accompanied Filthy to the detention center. At the jail, Loko gave the guard P10,000.00 to open the gate and let Takas out. What crime or crimes did Filthy commit? ",
        "Answer": "Filthy is liable of: (1) Corruption of Public Officials, Article 212, RPC, because he gave P500,000.00 to the clerk of court... (2) Delivery of prisoners from Jail, Article 156, RPC, because he assisted in the removal of Takas... (3) Falsification of Public Document, Article 172(1), RPC, as a principal by inducement because he gave the clerk of court P500,000.00 to induce him to forge the signature of the judge."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 247,
        "Question": "What crime or crimes did Loko (clerk of court) commit? ",
        "Answer": "Loko is liable of: (1) Direct Bribery, Article 210, RPC, because he accepted P500,000.00 in consideration of the execution of an act which constitutes a crime, i.e., forging the signature of the judge... (2) Falsification of Public Document, Article 171, RPC, because he took advantage of his position as a clerk of court in forging the signature of the judge... (3) Delivery of Prisoners from Jail, Article 156, RPC, because he assisted in the removal of Takas from jail."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 248,
        "Question": "What crime or crimes did the guard commit? ",
        "Answer": "The guard is liable of: (1) Direct Bribery, Article 210, RPC, because he agreed to open the gate and let Takas out in consideration of P10,000.00. (2) Infidelity in the Custody of Prisoners, Article 223, RPC, because he, as the custodian of Takas, connived or consented to his escape by opening the gate."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 249,
        "Question": "What is the criminal liability, if any, of AAA who substitutes for a prisoner serving sentence for homicide by taking his place in jail or penal establishment?  a) AAA is criminally liable for delivering prisoner from jail and for using fictitious name. b) AAA is criminally liable as an accessory of the crime of homicide by assisting in the escape or concealment of the principal of the crime. c) AAA is criminally liable for infidelity in the custody of prisoners. d) AAA is criminally liable for misrepresentation or concealing his true name.",
        "Answer": "AAA is criminally liable for delivering prisoner from jail and for using fictitious name."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 250,
        "Question": "What is the crime of qualified bribery?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Qualified bribery is a crime committed by a public officer who is entrusted with law enforcement and who, in consideration of any offer, promise, gift of offer, refrains from arresting or prosecuting an offender who has committed a crime punishable by reclusion perpetua and/ or death (art. 211-A, RPC)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 251,
        "Question": "May a judge be charged and prosecuted for qualified bribery? How about a public prosecutor? A police officer? Explain  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, a judge may not be charged of this felony because his official duty as a public officer is not law enforcement but the determination of cases already filed in court. On the other hand, a public prosecutor may be prosecuted for this crime in respect of the bribery committed, aside from dereliction of duty committed in violation of Art. 208 of the Revised Penal Code, should be refrain from prosecuting an offender who has committed a crime punishable by reclusion perpetua and / or death in consideration of any offer, promise, gift or present. Meanwhile, a police officer who refrains from arresting such offender for the same consideration above stated, may be prosecuted for this felony since he is a public officer entrusted with law enforcement."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 252,
        "Question": "Mr. Gulang, President and CEO of Bangon Waray, Inc. (BaWI), an NGO, received funds from public sources. COA reported that P10 Million worth of public funds were not properly accounted for. Mr. Gulang was criminally charged... with malversation of public funds and failure of accountable officer to render accounts... He was also charged with violation of Sec. 3(e) of R.A. No. 3019. In his defense, Mr. Gulang mainly contended that he could not be held liable under the various charges because he was not a public officer. Who is a public officer?  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Under Article 203 of the Revised Penal Code, any person who, by direct provision of the law, popular election or appointment by competent authority, shall take part in the performance of public functions in the Government of the Philippine Islands, or shall perform in said Government or in any of its branches public duties as an employee, agent or subordinate official, of any rank or class, shall be deemed to be a public officer."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 253,
        "Question": "Discuss whether the crimes charged against Mr. Gulang (malversation, failure to render accounts, and violation of Sec. 3(e) of R.A. 3019) are proper. Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The crimes of Malversation and Failure of accountable officer to render accounts are not proper. Only public officers may be held liable for Malversation (Art. 217, RPC) and Failure of accountable officer to render accounts (Art. 218, RPC). The criminal charge for violation of Section 3 (e) of RA No. 3019 is proper. Under RA No. 3019, a private person, if acting in conspiracy with a public officer, may be held liable for violation of Section 3 (e)... Provided that the private individual exercised some degree of control over the public officer."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 254,
        "Question": "Overjoyed by the award to his firm of a multi-billion government contract... Mr. Gangnam allotted the amount of P100 Million to serve as gifts for certain persons instrumental in his firm’s winning the award... Governor Datu received 50%... Bokal Diva received 25%... and Mayor Dolor 25%... Mayor Dolor and Bokal Diva later facilitated an overpriced project for Mr. Gangnam. What provisions of R.A. No. 3019 (Anti-Graft & Corrupt Practices Act), if any, were violated by any of the above-named individuals, specifying the persons liable therefor? Explain your answer. (4%) (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Governor Datu, Mayor Dolor and Bokal Diva are liable for violations of Section 3 (b) or RA No. 3019 in receiving money in connection with government contract or transaction... Mr. Gangnam for giving money to the said public officers and Dee, who received kickbacks for her husband, Governor Dato, are also liable for violation of Section 3 (b) of RA No. 3019 on the basis of conspiracy... Mayor Dolor and Bokal Diva are liable for violations of Section 3 (b) of RA No. 3019 for receiving money in connection with government contract... or violation of Section 3 (e) for giving Mr. Gangnam, a private party, unwarranted benefits... or violation of Section 3 (g) for entering... into any contract or transaction... manifestly and grossly disadvantageous to the same."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 255,
        "Question": "What crimes under the Revised Penal Code, if any, were committed, specifying the persons liable therefor (in the scenario involving Governor Datu, Bokal Diva, Mayor Dolor and Mr. Gangnam)? Explain your answer. (4%) (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Governor Datu, Mayor Dolo and Bokal Diva are liable for indirect bribery under Art. 211, RPC for receiving money from Mr. Gangnam offered to change by reason of their position as public officers while the letter is liable for corruption of public officer. Direct bribery is not committed since there is no showing that they received the money by virtue of an agreement to commit a crime or unjust act... Meanwhile, Mr. Gangnam is liable for corruption of public officer under Article 212 of the RPC because of his act of giving gifts to the public officers."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 256,
        "Question": "Governor A was given P10 million... for the purpose of buying seedlings... Governor A bought farm equipment through direct purchase from XY Enterprise, owned by his kumpare B... The equipment purchased turned out to be overpriced. What crime or crimes, if any, were committed by Governor A? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Governor A committed the crimes of: (1) Technical Malversation; and (2) Violation of Sections 3 (e) and (g) of Republic Act No. 3019. Governor A committed the crime of illegal use of public funds or property punishable under Art. 220 of the Revised Penal Code. This offense is also known as technical malversation... Governor A also violated Section 3 (e) of R.A. 3019 for giving unwarranted benefit... to his kumpare B... The act committed by the Governor is also in violation of Section 3 (g) of RA No. 3019 for entering a contract on behalf of the government which is manifestly and grossly disadvantageous to the same."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 257,
        "Question": "Malo, a clerk of court... promised the accused in a drug case... that he would convince the judge to acquit him for a consideration of P5 million... Malo was charged with violation of Section 3(b), Republic Act (R.A.) No. 3019... He was later charged also with indirect bribery under the Revised Penal Code. Malo claims he can no longer be charged under the Revised Penal Code for the same act under R.A. 3019. Is he correct? ",
        "Answer": "No. One may be charged with violation of R.A. 3019 in addition to a felony under the RPC for the same delictual act, either concurrently or subsequent to being charged with a felony under the RPC. This is very clear from Sec. 3 of R.A. 3019. Also, R.A. 3019 is a special law, the elements of the crime is not the same as those punished under the RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 258,
        "Question": "Malo was charged with estafa under Article 315 because he misrepresented that he had influence, when he actually had none. Is the charge correct? ",
        "Answer": "Yes, estafa is committed by any person who shall ask for money from another for the alleged purpose of bribing a government employee when in truth the offender intended to convert the money to his own personal use and benefit (Art. 315(2)(c), RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 259,
        "Question": "Roger and Jessie... falsified the disbursement vouchers and supporting documents in order to make it appear that qualified recipients who, in fact, are non-existent individuals, received the money. Roger and Jessie are charged with violation of Section 3 (e) of R.A. 3019 for causing undue injury to the government. Discuss the propriety of the charge filed against Roger and Jessie. Explain. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "They should be charged of violation of Section 3(e) of Rep. Act 3019 for the breach of public trust and undue injury caused to the Government. The violation is a crime malum prohibitum."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 260,
        "Question": "Charina, Clerk of Court of an RTC Branch, promised the plaintiff in a case... that she would convince the Presiding Judge to decide the case in plaintiff's favor. In consideration therefor, the plaintiff gave Charina P20,000.00. Charina was charged with violation of Section 3 (b) of Republic Act No. 3019... While the case was being tried, the Ombudsman filed another information against Charina for Indirect Bribery under the Revised Penal Code. Charina demurred to the second information, claiming that she can no longer be charged under the Revised Penal Code having been charged for the same act under R.A. 3019. Is Charina correct? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, Charina is not correct. Although the charge for violation of Rep. Act No. 3019 and the charge for Indirect Bribery (Art. 211, RPC) arose from the same act, the elements of the violation charged under Rep. Act No. 3019 are not the same as the felony charged for Indirect Bribery under the Rev. Penal Code... Hence, the crimes charged are separate and distinct from each other, with different penalties."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 261,
        "Question": "Proserfina, an assistant public high school principal, acted to facilitate the release of salary differentials and election duty per diem of classroom teachers with the agreement that they would reimburse her for her expenses. Did Proserfina commit a crime? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes, Proserfina committed violation of Sec. 3(b) of Rep. Act No. 3019 which considers as corrupt practice, the act of: “(b) Directly or indirectly requesting or receiving any gift, present, share, percentage, or benefit, for himself or for any other person, in connection with any contract or transaction between the Government and any other party, wherein the public officer in his official capacity has to intervene under the law.” Being the assistant public high school principal, it is her duty to intervene in the release of salary differentials and per diem of classroom teachers under her. Her act of doing so, made a request for a share or benefit therefor constitutes graft or corrupt practice under Sec 3(b) of Rep. Act No. 3019."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 262,
        "Question": "Overjoyed by the award to his firm of a multi-billion government contract... Mr. Gangnam allotted the amount of P100 Million to serve as gifts... Governor Datu received 50%... Bokal Diva received 25%... and Mayor Dolor 25%... Mayor Dolor and Bokal Diva later facilitated an overpriced project for Mr. Gangnam. May each of the above-named individuals be held liable for plunder? Explain your answer. (4%) (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The act of receiving P50 Million by Governor Datu kickback... is a predicate crime of plunder. He is not liable, however, for plunder... To be held liable for plunder, the public officer must amass, accumulate or acquire ill-gotten wealth through a combination or series of overt or criminal acts... A single predicate crime amounting to 50 million pesos is not plunder. The series acts of receiving by Mayor Dolor Kickback or gift in the amount of P25 million and P10 million... are predicate crimes of plunder. However, the aggregate amount of ill-gotten wealth acquired is less than P50 million. Hence, plunder is not committed... Bokal Diva is liable for plunder because he acquired ill-gotten wealth in the aggregate amount of P50 million through a series of predicate crimes... Mr. Gangnam, for giving kickbacks to Bokal Diva, and Terry for depositing the money in his account for Bokal Diva are also liable for plunder."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 263,
        "Question": "City Engr. A... diverted the construction of a road leading to his farm. He accepted P10 million each from three (3) contending bidders... service vehicles valued at P2 million could not be accounted for... funds under City Engr. A’s custody amounting to P10 million which were found to be missing... awarded a contract... costing P10 million to a close relative, although the lowest bid was P8 million... City Engr. A has a net worth of more than P50 million, which was way beyond his legitimate income. If you are the Ombudsman, what charge or charges will you file against City Engr. A? ",
        "Answer": "If I am the Ombudsman, I would file a case of Plunder under R.A. 7080 against City Engr. A. It is very clear from the facts given that all the elements of plunder are present... The offender amassed, accumulated, or acquired ill-gotten wealth through a combination of overt or criminal acts of misuse, misaapropriation, conversion or malversation of public funds, receiving kickbacks... and illegally or fraudulently conveying or disposing of assets belonging to the national government or any of its subdivisions; and The aggregate amount or total value of the ill gotten wealth amassed, accumulated, or acquired is at least P50M."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 264,
        "Question": "Suppose the discovered net worth of City Engr. A is less than P50 million, will your answer still be the same? ",
        "Answer": "Yes, the answer will be the same since in plunder the basis is the combination of criminal acts or series of acts, which constitutes the accumulation of more than P50M. The predicate crimes are already absorbed in the crime of plunder. City Engr. A’s net worth being less than P50M is not determinative of his liability, as long as the wealth amassed/ accumulated is more than P50M."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 265,
        "Question": "If the slightest penetration of the female genitalia consummates rape by carnal knowledge, how does the accused commit attempted rape by carnal knowledge?  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The accused commits attempted rape by carnal knowledge when he commences to force his penis into the female sexual organ, but does not succeed in penetrating even the slightest part of the female sexual organ by reason of supervening cause or resistance on the part of the victim; or by reason of independent cause other than his own desistance."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 266,
        "Question": "Why is there no crime of frustrated serious physical injuries?  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Serious physical injuries is a result crime. There is no crime of frustrated serious physical injuries because the existence of intent to commit serious physical injuries is negated by the gravity of the resulting physical injuries. If the physical injuries sustained are serious, the crime is consummated serious physical injuries. If the injury sustained is slight, the crime is slight physical injuries. If the injury sustained is physical injury not covered by serious and slight physical injuries, the crime is less serious physical injuries."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 267,
        "Question": "A criminal complaint for attempted rape with homicide was brought against Aliswan... the Investigating Prosecutor recommended the filing of two separate informations – one for attempted rape and the other for homicide. Do you agree with the recommendation? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "I do not agree with the recommendation for the filing or attempted rape. Intent to have sexual Intercourse is an essential element of attempted rape. In other words, intent to lie with the victim must be closer. However, this intent is not established for failure to show that Aliswan had done acts to have sex with Amethyst... Moreover, he spontaneously desisted from committing further lascivious acts after undressing Amethyst which is a defense in attempted rape. Undressing the victim with lewd design merely constitutes acts of lasciviousness."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 268,
        "Question": "After receiving medical attendance for 10 days, Alisto consulted you about filing the proper criminal complaint against Amante (who struck Alisto/error in personae). What crimes, if any, will you charge Amante with? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The proper charge against Amante is Child Abuse. His act of physically harming the child, Alisto, which resulted to an injury requiring medical attendance for 10 days, is considered physical abuse under Sec. 10 (a), in relation to Sec. 3(b)(2), of R.A. No. 7610... Since Amante inflicted physical injuries that required medical attendance for 10 days, he inflicted less serious physical injuries."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 269,
        "Question": "Jojo caught his wife Felipa in the act of sexual intercourse with Alma, another woman. Jojo shot Alma to death and seriously wounded Felipa. Is Art. 247 (death or physical injuries inflicted under exceptional circumstances) of the Revised Penal Code (RPC) applicable in this case given that the paramour was of the same gender as the erring spouse?  ",
        "Answer": "No. Art. 247 of the Revised Penal Code is not applicable. Under the Revised Penal Code, for Art. 247 to apply, the offender must catch his or her spouse in the act of committing sexual intercourse with another person. Sexual intercourse generally presupposes the penetration of the man’s sexual organ into that of a woman’s. In this case, the paramour was of the same gender as the erring spouse. As such, there is legally, no sexual intercourse to speak of, hence, Art. 247 is not applicable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 270,
        "Question": "Is Felipa liable for adultery for having sexual relations with Alma?  ",
        "Answer": "No. Under Article 333 of the Revised Penal Code, adultery is committed by any married woman who shall have sexual intercourse with a “man” not her husband. Thus, Felipa in having homosexual intercourse with Alma, a “woman,” is not committing adultery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 271,
        "Question": "A, B and C were charged with libel before the RTC of Manila... C, the author/writer, wrote about X, a public official, calling him 'BUWAYA,' 'Atty. Buwaya,' 'magnanakaw,' and 'kurakot.' The three defendants argued that the article is within the ambit of qualified privileged communication; that there is no malice in law and in fact; and, that defamatory comments on the acts of public officials... do not constitute libel. Was the crime of libel committed? If so, are A, B, and C all liable for the crime? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Yes. The crime of libel is committed. Fair comment on acts of public officers related to the discharge of their duties is a qualified privileged communication, hence, the accused can still be held liable for libel if actual malice is shown. In fair comment, actual malice can be established by showing that comment was made with knowledge that it was false or with reckless disregard of whether it was false or not. The report made by C describing a lawyer in the Bureau of Customs as corrupt cannot be considered as “fair” and “true” since he did not do research before making his allegations, and it has been shown that these allegations were baseless... A, B and C are all liable as principals since the RPC holds the author, editor, and the publisher liable as principals."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 272,
        "Question": "Braulio, 25 years of age, cornered Lulu, 10 years of age, and started touching Lulu’s chest and sex organ. Lulu shouted and a security guard came and apprehended Braulio. What is the crime committed? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "The acts of Braulio of touching the chest and sex organ of Lulu, who is under 12 years of age, are merely acts of lasciviousness and not attempted rape because intent to have sexual intercourse is not clearly shown... To be held liable of attempted rape, it must be shown that the erectile penis is in the position to penetrate... Undressing the victim with lewd design merely constitutes acts of lasciviousness."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 273,
        "Question": "Lina murdered a 3-year old child. She gagged the mouth of the child with stockings, placed him in a box, sealed it with masking tape, and placed the box in the attic. She then demanded ransom from the parents of the child as a means to divert the attention of the parents and the police from the fact of the child's death. What crime or crimes, if any, did Lina and Fely commit? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Lina is liable for murder. Gagging the mouth of the child with stockings, placing him in a box, sealing it with masking tape, and placed the box in the attic were only methods employed by the defendant in committing: murder qualified by the circumstance of treachery. Taking advantage of the defenseless condition of the victim by reason of his tender age in killing him is treachery... She is not liable for kidnapping with murder, the essence of which is the actual confinement or restraint of the victim or the deprivation of his liberty. In this case, the victim was not deprived of liberty since he immediately died. The demand for ransom did not convert the offense into kidnapping with murder."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 274,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by a person who kills a three-day old baby?  a) infanticide; b) homicide; c) murder; d) parricide.",
        "Answer": "infanticide;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 275,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by a person who kills his legitimate brother on the occasion of a public calamity?  a) parricide; b) homicide; c) murder; d) death caused in a tumultuous affray.",
        "Answer": "parricide;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 276,
        "Question": "The key element in a crime of parricide other than the fact of killing is the relationship of the offender to the victim. Which one of the following circumstances constitutes parricide?  a) Offender killing the illegitimate daughter of his legitimate son. b) Offender killing his illegitimate grandson. c) Offender killing his common-law wife. d) Offender killing his illegitimate mother.",
        "Answer": "Offender killing his illegitimate mother."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 277,
        "Question": "What crime is committed when a mother kills the three-day old child of her husband with their daughter?  a) parricide; b) infanticide; c) murder; d) homicide.",
        "Answer": "murder;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 278,
        "Question": "With intent to kill, GGG burned the house where F and D were staying. F and D died as a consequence. What is the proper charge against GGG?  a) GGG should be charged with two (2) counts of murder. b) GGG should be charged with arson. c) GGG should be charged with complex crime of arson with double murder. d) GGG should be charged with complex crime of double murder.",
        "Answer": "GGG should be charged with complex crime of arson with double murder."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 279,
        "Question": "At a wake, there were people watching a game of dice. With treachery and use of unlicensed firearms, AA fired successively several gunshots at their direction. During the shooting, four (4) persons were killed and fourteen (14) others were injured and brought to the hospital for the treatment of gunshot wounds. What should be the proper charge against AA?  a) AA should be charged with multiple murder and attempted murder. b) AA should be charged with four (4) counts of murder and fourteen (14) counts of attempted murder. c) AA should be charged with four (4) counts of murder, fourteen (14) counts of serious physical injuries and illegal possession of firearms. d) AA should be charged with complex crime of murder and attempted murder with illegal possession of firearms.",
        "Answer": "AA should be charged with four (4) counts of murder and fourteen (14) counts of attempted murder."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 280,
        "Question": "What crime is committed when a person ill-treats another by deed without causing any injury?  a) slight physical injuries; b) maltreatment; c) physical injuries; d) grave oral defamation.",
        "Answer": "maltreatment;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 281,
        "Question": "X killed B, mistakenly believing that she was his wife, upon surprising her having sex with another man in a motel room. What is the criminal liability of X?  (A) None since he killed her under exceptional circumstances. (B) None since he acted under a mistake of fact. (C) Parricide. (D) Homicide.",
        "Answer": "Homicide."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 282,
        "Question": "Dagami concealed Bugna’s body and the fact that he killed him by setting Bugna’s house on fire. What crime or crimes did Dagami commit?  (A) Murder, the arson being absorbed already (B) Separate crimes of murder and arson (C) Arson, the homicide being absorbed already (D) Arson with murder as a compound crime",
        "Answer": "Separate crimes of murder and arson"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 283,
        "Question": "On hearing a hospital ward patient on the next bed, shrieking in pain and begging to die, Mona shut off the oxygen that was sustaining the patient, resulting in his death. What crime if any did Mona commit?  (A) Homicide. (B) Murder if she deliberated on her action. (C) Giving Assistance to Suicide. (D) Euthanasia.",
        "Answer": "Homicide."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 284,
        "Question": "A criminal action for rape is extinguished when the offender is forgiven by  (A) the offender’s wife who herself is the rape victim. (B) his wife for having raped another woman. (C) the rape victim’s husband. (D) the rape victim herself.",
        "Answer": "the rape victim herself."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 285,
        "Question": "Explain and illustrate the stages of execution of the crime of homicide, taking into account the nature of the offense, the essential element of each of the stages of execution and the manner of committing such intentional felony as distinguished from felony committed through reckless imprudence. ",
        "Answer": "Elements of the crime – Homicide as an intentional felony has three stages, attempted, frustrated and consummated. In whatever stages homicide is committed, intent to kill must be established for being an indispensible element thereof. However, if the victim died as a consequence of wounds caused by an act committed with malice, intent to kill is conclusively presumed and the crime committed is consummated homicide... But if the victim did not die as a consequence of wounds caused by an act committed with malice, intent to kill must be established beyond reasonable doubt. If intent to kill is proven, the crime committed is frustrated or attempted homicide. If intent to kill is not proven, the crime committed is physical injuries."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 286,
        "Question": "Macho pointed his gun at a passing vehicle, intending to shoot the driver, but the driver swerved the vehicle, causing it to crash on a wall, killing the driver instantly. What was the crime committed? ",
        "Answer": "Macho committed the crime of Homicide. Since death resulted from Macho’s act of accidentally pulling the trigger of the gun, homicide is committed. Here, intent to kill is a general criminal intent which is presumed by law because the victim died."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 287,
        "Question": "Out of spite and simply intending to put Gina to shame for breaking off with him, Ritchie emptied a gallon of motor oil on the school's stairway where Gina usually passed. Gina, unaware of what Ritchie did, used the slippery stairway and slipped, hitting her head on the stairs. Gina died from brain hemorrhage. What crime did Ritchie commit?  (A) Murder. (B) Reckless imprudence resulting in homicide. (C) Homicide. (D) Impossible crime of homicide. (E) None.",
        "Answer": "Homicide."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 288,
        "Question": "A, in a public place, fired his gun at B with the intention of killing B, but the gun did not fire because the bullet is a dud. The crime is:  (A) attempted homicide (B) grave threat (C) impossible crime (D) alarm and scandal",
        "Answer": "impossible crime"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 289,
        "Question": "After a heated argument... Higino punched on the head his wife Aika, who was six and a half months pregnant. Because of the impact, Aika lost her balance, fell on the floor... Aika died and the child was expelled prematurely. After thirty-six hours, the child died. What crime(s) did Higino commit? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "With respect to the killing of the wife, parricide under Article 246 of the Revised Penal Code is committed... With respect to the killing of the child, Higino is liable for infanticide under Article 255 of the Revised Penal Code because his child was born alive and was already viable or capable of independent existence and the child’s age is less than three (3) days... Inasmuch as the single act of Higino produced two grave felonies, it falls under Art. 48, RPC, ie. a complex crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 290,
        "Question": "Assuming that when the incident occurred (Higino hitting Aika), Aika was only six months pregnant, and when she died, the fetus inside her womb also died, will your answer be different? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "If the child died inside the womb of Aika, who was only six months, the crime committed is complex crime of parricide with unintentional abortion. Killing the unborn child as a result of the violence employed against the mother without intent to abort is unintentional abortion... Because the same violence that killed the mother also caused unintentional abortion, the crime committed is a complex crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 291,
        "Question": "Honesto killed Melba, the cousin of his wife, believing that she was his wife, due to error in personae. What crime(s) did Honesto commit? Explain.",
        "Answer": "Honesto is liable for murder qualified by the circumstance of treachery for killing Melba due to error in personae or mistake of identity and slight physical injuries for the wound sustained by the passerby due to aberratio ictus or mistake of blow. Although his intention to commit parricide, he is liable for murder and slight physical injuries since they are the direct, natural and logical consequence of act committed with intent to kill his wife."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 292,
        "Question": "Will your answer be the same (regarding Honesto killing Melba), assuming that the other passerby was hit in the left eye which caused his/her blindness? Explain.",
        "Answer": "If the passerby was hit in the left eye causing blindness, the crime committed by Honesto is serious physical injuries. Unlike slight physical injuries, serious physical injuries can be made a component of a complex crime under Article 48 of the Revised Penal Code. Since a single act of shooting the victim constitutes murder and serious physical injuries, they can be merged together to form a complex crime. Thus, my answer would be different since the crime would be Murder with Serious physical injuries."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 293,
        "Question": "Choose the correct circumstance when a woman may be held liable for rape:  (A) With the use of force or intimidation. (B) When the rape is committed by two or more persons. (C) When the offender uses an instrument and inserts it into the mouth of the victim. (D) When she befriends and puts a sleeping pill in the victim's drink to enable her husband to have intercourse with the victim.",
        "Answer": "When she befriends and puts a sleeping pill in the victim's drink to enable her husband to have intercourse with the victim."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 294,
        "Question": "If Rod killed Irene, his illegitimate daughter, after taking her diamond earrings and forcing her to have sex with him, what crime/s should Rod be charged with?  (A) Robbery and rape with parricide. (B) Robbery, rape and parricide. (C) Rape with homicide and theft. (D) Rape with homicide. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "Rape with homicide."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 295,
        "Question": "Charlie was charged for the qualified rape of AAA... AAA was 14 years old... and Charlie was AAA's stepfather... BBB (AAA's mother) and Charlie only became live-in partners after CCC's (AAA's father) death. The RTC found Charlie guilty of qualified rape. On appeal, the Court of Appeals convicted Charlie of simple rape. Charlie appealed before the Supreme Court. How will you rule and why? ",
        "Answer": "I will rule that Charlie is guilty of qualified rape. Rape is qualified when the offender is the step-father of the victim (Art. 266-B). It is settled that in rape, the relationship of step-father and step-daughter is included in the concept of a ‘legal relationship of relationship by affinity’ (People v. Abaro, G.R. No. 105598, March 14, 1995)... The legal tie of affinity between the parties is not affected by the subsequent dissolution of the marriage or by the death of the spouse."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 296,
        "Question": "Procopio killed his wife Bionci while they were living together in an adulterous relationship. What crime did Procopio commit? [Part a] ",
        "Answer": "The crime committed is Parricide. Relationship by common-law marriage is not included in the coverage of the crime of Parricide."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 297,
        "Question": "Assuming that Procopio and Bionci were common-law spouses, will your answer be the same? Explain. [Part b] ",
        "Answer": "No, the answer is not the same. The crime committed is Homicide if Procopio and Bionci were common law spouses. Parricide contemplates killing by spouse who are legally married."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 298,
        "Question": "What is the criminal liability, if any, of a pregnant woman who tried to commit suicide by poison, but she did not die and the fetus in her womb was expelled instead?  a) The woman who tried to commit suicide is not criminally liable because the suicide intended was not consummated. b) The woman who tried to commit suicide is criminally liable for unintentional abortion which is punishable when caused by violence. c) The woman who tried to commit suicide is criminally liable for abortion that resulted due to the poison that she had taken to commit suicide. d) The woman who tried to commit suicide incurs no criminal liability for the result not intended.",
        "Answer": "The woman who tried to commit suicide incurs no criminal liability for the result not intended."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 299,
        "Question": "Mr. P owns a boarding house where he knowingly allowed children to be videotaped while simulating explicit sexual activities. What is Mr. P's criminal liability, if any?  (A) Corruption of minors under the Penal Code (B) Violation of the Child Pornography Act (C) Violation of the Child Abuse Law (D) None",
        "Answer": "Violation of the Child Pornography Act"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 300,
        "Question": "Tony struck Juanito (10-year old) on the head with his hand and caused the boy to fall and to hit his head on a chair... Juanito sustained a lacerated wound on the head that required medical attendance for 10 days. Tony was charged with child abuse in violation of Sec. 10(a), in relation to Sec. 3(b)(2), of R.A. No. 7610 (Child Abuse Law)... In his defense, Tony contended that he had no intention to maltreat Juanito, much less to degrade his intrinsic worth and dignity as a human being. Was Tony criminally liable for child abuse under R.A. No. 7610? Explain your answer.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Tony laid hands on Juanito without intent to debase the “intrinsic worth and dignity” of Juanito as a human being... It appears that the laying of hands on Juanito have been done at the spur of the moment and in anger... With the loss of his self-control, he lacked that specific intent to debase, degrade or demean the intrinsic worth and dignity of a child as a human being that was so essential in the crime of child abuse; hence, the crime committed is only slight physical injuries."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 301,
        "Question": "Arnold, 25 years old, was in Luneta when he saw Leilani, 17 years old, sitting alone. Arnold sat beside her and started talking. Is Arnold liable for the charge of child abuse? Explain. . ",
        "Answer": "No, Arnold is not liable. Under Section 10 of RA No. 7610, any person who shall keep or have in his company a minor, twelve (12) years or under or who in ten (10) years or more his junior in any public or private place, hotel, motel, beer joint, discotheque, cabaret, pension house, sauna or massage parlor, beach and/or other tourist resort or similar places is liable for child abuse. Arnold is not liable for the charge. To be held liable under Section 10 (6) of RA No. 7610, it is indispensable that the child in the company of the offender must be 12 years or under or who in 10 years or more his junior in a public place. In this case, Leilani is 17 years of age, and only 8 years younger than Arnold."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 302,
        "Question": "Razzy abducted Angelino, a trans-gender person, who underwent gender reassignment to become a woman. Angelino was subsequently killed in the course of the detention. What crime or crimes, if any, were committed? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Razzy is liable for kidnapping with homicide. Abducting Angelino is not forcible abduction since the victim in this crime must be a woman. Gender reassignment will not make him a woman within the meaning of Article 342 of the Revised Penal Code... There is no showing, moreover, that at the time abduction is committed with lewd design; hence, his abduction constitutes illegal detention. Since Angelino was killed in the course of the detention, the crime constitutes kidnapping and serious illegal detention with homicide under Article 267."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 303,
        "Question": "Which among the following circumstances do NOT qualify the crime of kidnapping?  (A) The victim is killed as a consequence of the detention. (B) The offender is a public officer. (C) Ransom is demanded. (D) The victim is raped.",
        "Answer": "The victim is killed as a consequence of the detention."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 304,
        "Question": "The three accused forcibly took their victim from his car but the latter succeeded in freeing himself from their grip. What crime did the three accused commit?  (A) forcible abduction. (B) frustrated kidnapping. (C) attempted kidnapping. (D) grave coercion.",
        "Answer": "attempted kidnapping."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 305,
        "Question": "A entered the house of B. Once inside the house of B, A took and seized personal property by compulsion from B with the use of violence and force upon things, believing himself to be the owner of the personal property so seized. What is the criminal liability of A?  a) A is criminally liable for robbery with violence because he employed violence in the taking of the personal property from B, robbery characterized by violence being graver than ordinary robbery committed with force upon things. b) A is criminally liable for robbery with force upon things in an inhabited house because the act was committed in a house constituting the dwelling of one or more persons. c) A is criminally liable for grave coercion because the presumption of intent to gain is rebutted. d) A is criminally liable for qualified trespass to dwelling because he employed violence.",
        "Answer": "A is criminally liable for grave coercion because the presumption of intent to gain is rebutted."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 306,
        "Question": "AA was arrested for committing a bailable offense and detained in solitary confinement. He was able to post bail after two (2) weeks of defection. During the period of detention, he was not given any food. Such deprivation caused him physically discomfort. What crime, if any, was committed in connection with the solitary confinement and food deprivation of AA? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The crime of torture and maltreatment of prisoner is committed. Food deprivation and confinement in solitary cell are considered as physical and psychological torture under Sec. 4(2) of the Anti-Torture Act of 2009 or R.A. 9745. “Torture” refers to an act by which severe pain or suffering, whether physical or mental, is intentionally inflicted on a person for such purposes as obtaining from him/her or a third person information or a confession; punishing him/her for an act which he/she or a third person has committed or is suspected of having committed..."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 307,
        "Question": "Guapo and Pogi forcibly abducted Pretty and subsequently raped her twice. Would Guapo and Pogi be liable for Pretty’s death (by suicide) one hour after the rape? Explain.",
        "Answer": "Guapo and Pogi cannot be held liable for the death of Pretty due to suicide committed by reason of the rapes. Suicide is an intervening cause that breaks the connection between the rapes and death. The death resulting from suicide cannot be considered as the direct, natural and logical consequence of the rapes committed by Guapo and Pogi."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 308,
        "Question": "Sexy boarded a taxi on her way home from a party... Pogi, the taxi driver, decided to take advantage of the situation and drove Sexy to a deserted place where he raped her for a period of two (2) weeks. What crime did Pogi commit? ",
        "Answer": "The crime committed by Pogi is kidnapping and Serious Illegal Detention with rape. Since Sexy was raped for two weeks, there was a clear deprivation of liberty, which constitutes the crime of kidnapping with serious illegal detention... Since as a consequence of the detention, the victim is raped, the crime committed is special complex crime of kidnapping with rape, the resultant crime is only one kidnapping with rape."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 309,
        "Question": "While walking alone on her way home from a party, Mildred was seized at gun point by Felipe and taken on board a tricycle to a house some distance away... Felipe, Julio, and Roldan succeeded in having sexual intercourse with Mildred against her will... Lucio was not around when the sexual assaults took place... but he returned everyday to bring food... For five days, Felipe, Julio and Roldan kept Mildred in the house and took turns in sexually assaulting her. What crime/s did Felipe, Julio, Roldan, and Lucio commit and what was their degree of participation? ",
        "Answer": "The crime committed is Qualified Kidnapping with Rape. All the offenders, Felipe, Julio, Roldan and Lucio, are liable as principals for the crime of qualified kidnapping with rape... Felipe, Julio, and Roldan are liable as principals by direct participation, and Lucio as principal by indispensable cooperation because although he was not present when the sexual assault took place, his complicity is evident as he was the one who drove the tricycle and returned every day to bring food and news to his cohorts."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 310,
        "Question": "At the Maligaya Disco Club, Leoncio and Evelyn were intimately dancing a very seductive dance number. While gyrating with their bodies, Leoncio dipped his private parts in Evelyn's buttocks. Incensed, Evelyn protested, but Leoncio continued and tightly embraced her. What crime or crimes, if any, did Leoncio commit? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Leoncio committed the crime of unjust vexation only because the act was done in the course of dancing. The act of dipping his private parts in Evelyn's buttocks during a very seductive dance, although offensive to Evelyn, may be viewed as part of a dirty dancing... The fact that the act was perpetrated in a public place and with an audience, negates lewd designs or lascivious intent, which is essential in the crime of acts of lasciviousness."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 311,
        "Question": "Would your answer be the same if, even after the music had stopped (in the case of Leoncio and Evelyn), Leoncio continued to dance dirty, rubbing his private parts on Evelyn's buttocks? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The crime would then be acts of lasciviousness. That the music for dancing had already stopped, puts an end to any pretense of dancing by Leoncio. His continued dirty acts absent the dancing as there was no music anymore is patently lewd and lascivious. More so, Evelyn already protested Leoncio's lewd acts in the course of dancing. So where the dance ended, Leoncio's continued dirty acts cannot be veiled as still part of dancing."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 312,
        "Question": "Virgilio, intending to demand P1M ransom, kidnapped 6 year-old Jeremias, but failed to communicate his demand to the parents who immediately reported the kidnapping to the police, resulting in Jeremias' rescue and Virgilio's arrest. What crime or crimes, if any, did Virgilio commit? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The crime committed against Jeremias, the 6 year-old child, is Kidnapping and Serious Illegal Detention under Art 267 (4), RPC. The evident criminal intent of the offender, Virgilio, is to lock up the child to demand ransom. Whether or not the ransom was eventually obtained will not affect the crime committed because the demand for ransom is not an element of the crime; it only qualifies the penalty to death but the imposition of this penalty is now prohibited by Rep. Act. No. 9346."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 313,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. The creditor who resorts to forced labor of a child under the pretext of reimbursing himself for the debt incurred by the child's father commits the crime of slavery.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. The proper offense is exploitation of child labor (Art. 273, RPC). Exploitation of child labor is committed by a person, who under the pretext of reimbursing himself of a debt incurred by an ascendant, guardian or person entrusted with the custody of a minor, shall against the minor's will, retain him in his services."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 314,
        "Question": "A widower of ten years, septuagenarian Canuto felt that he had license to engage in voyeurism. If not peeping into his neighbors’ rooms through his powerful single-cylinder telescope, he would trail young, shapely damsels along the hallways of shopping malls. While going up the escalator, he stayed a step behind a mini-skirted one, and in a moment of excitement, put his hand on her left hip and massaged it. The damsel screamed and hollered for help. Canuto was apprehended and brought up on inquest. What charge/s if any, may he be held responsible for? Explain . (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Canuto may be held liable only for the milder crime of “unjust vexation” which is a form of light coercion under Art 287 of the Revised Penal Code, instead of the crime of acts of lasciviousness although the offender is known for his voyeurism. Our Revised Penal Code inclines towards milder criminal responsibility... Holding the hip of a person is not per se lascivious but undoubtedly annoys, irritates and vexed the young offended party."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 315,
        "Question": "A was caught peeping through a small hole in the bathroom door while a young 16-year-old lady was taking a bath. A is liable for:  (A) Violation of R.A. 9262 or Violence Against Women and their Children (B) Violation of R.A. 7610 – Child Abuse Law (C) Light coercion (D) Acts of lasciviousness",
        "Answer": "Acts of lasciviousness"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 316,
        "Question": "From an extension line, Ricardo overheard a telephone conversation between Julito and Atty. Hipolito. The latter (Atty. Hipolito) was asking money from Julito in exchange for dropping the extortion charge filed against Julito. Ricardo was charged of violating the Anti-Wire Tapping Act or R.A. 4200. Under these facts, was there a violation as charged?  (A) Yes, because the conversation was private in nature. (B) Yes, because the conversation was overheard without the consent of the parties, Julito and Atty. Hipolito. (C) No, because what is punishable is intentional listening to a conversation through a wire. (D) No, because a telephone extension line is not the device or arrangement contemplated by the law and the use of an extension line cannot be considered as wire tapping. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "No, because a telephone extension line is not the device or arrangement contemplated by the law and the use of an extension line cannot be considered as wire tapping."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 317,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by a capataz who enrolls two fictitious names in the payroll and collects their supposed daily wages every payday?  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "The crime committed is Estafa through Falsification of Public Documents. A capataz is a foreman for the government and since the falsification of the public document is committed as a means to commit estafa, the proper charge is estafa through falsification of documents."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 318,
        "Question": "Domingo is the caretaker of two (2) cows and two (2) horses owned by Hannibal. Hannibal told Domingo to lend the cows to Tristan on the condition that the latter will give a goat to the former when the cows are returned. Instead, Tristan sold the cows and pocketed the money. Due to the neglect of Domingo, one of the horses was stolen. Knowing that he will be blamed for the loss, Domingo slaughtered the other horse, got the meat, and sold it to Pastor. He later reported to Hannibal that the two horses were stolen. What crime or crimes, if any, did Tristan commit? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Tristan is liable for Estafa through Misappropriation under Article 315 of the Revised Penal Code. He received the cows under obligation involving the duty to return the same thing deposited, and acquired legal or juridical possession in so doing, since their transaction is a commodatum. Selling the cows as if he owned it constitutes misappropriation or conversion within the contemplation of Article 315."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 319,
        "Question": "What crime or crimes, if any, were committed by Domingo (the caretaker who sold the remaining horse)? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Domingo is liable for qualified theft under Article 308 of the Revised Penal Code. Although Tristan received the horse with the consent of the owner, Hannibal, his possession is merely physical or de facto since the former is an employee of the latter. Slaughtering the horse, which he physically possessed, and selling its meat to Pastor shall be considered as taking without consent of the owner with intent to gain, which constitutes theft. Since the horse is accessible to him, the theft is qualified by the circumstance of abuse of confidence."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 320,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts does not constitute estafa or other forms of swindling?  a) When a person mortgages a real property by pretending to be the owner thereof. b) When a person disposes of the real property knowing it to be encumbered. c) When a person wrongfully takes real property from its lawful possessor to the prejudice of the latter. d) When a person mortgages real property while being a surety given in a civil action without express authority from the court.",
        "Answer": "When a person wrongfully takes real property from its lawful possessor to the prejudice of the latter."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 321,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by a person who, having found a ring, fails to deliver the same to the owner or to the local authorities?  a) The finder commits theft. b) The finder commits concealment. c) The finder commits qualified theft. d) The finder commits usurpation of property.",
        "Answer": "The finder commits theft."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 322,
        "Question": "Who among the following is liable for estafa?  a) The seller of a laptop computer who failed to inform the buyer that the laptop had a defect. b) The person who ran away with a cell phone which was handed to him upon his pretense that he had to make an emergency call. c) The person who assured he will pay interest on the amount but failed to do so as promised. d) The son who induced his father to buy from him a land which the son is no longer the owner.",
        "Answer": "The person who ran away with a cell phone which was handed to him upon his pretense that he had to make an emergency call."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 323,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by one who, having received money, goods or any other personal property in trust or on commission, or for administration, defrauds the offended party by denying receipt of such money, goods or other property?  a) He commits violation of the Trust Receipt Law. b) He commits estafa through fraudulent means. c) He commits estafa by false pretenses. d) He commits estafa with unfaithfulness or abuse of confidence.",
        "Answer": "He commits estafa with unfaithfulness or abuse of confidence."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 324,
        "Question": "RR convinced WW to take a job in Taiwan, assuring her of a good salary... WW paid to RR the processing fee... WW was made to use the alien certificate of registration of another person... The application of WW was rejected... The case of illegal recruitment was dismissed. Is RR liable for estafa?  a) RR is liable for estafa with unfaithfulness or abuse of confidence. b) RR is liable for estafa by means of false pretenses. c) RR is not liable for estafa because WW participated in the illegal travel documents. d) RR can no longer be held liable for estafa because with the dismissal of the case against him for illegal recruitment, double jeopardy has already set in.",
        "Answer": "RR is liable for estafa by means of false pretenses."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 325,
        "Question": "With intent to cause damage, AAA deliberately set fire upon the two storey residential house of his employer, mostly made of wooden materials. The blaze spread and gutted down seven neighboring houses. On the occasion of the fire, six (6) persons sustained burn injuries which were the direct cause of their death. What crime was committed by AAA?  a) AAA committed the complex crime of arson with multiple homicide. b) AAA committed arson and multiple homicide. c) AAA committed simple arson. d) AAA committed arson and multiple murder.",
        "Answer": "AAA committed arson and multiple murder."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 326,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by a utility worker in government who destroys office files as an act of revenge against his supervisor?  a) The utility worker commits infidelity in the custody of papers. b) The utility worker commits malicious mischief. c) The utility worker commits estafa by removing, concealing or destroying office files. d) The utility worker commits crime involving destruction.",
        "Answer": "The utility worker commits malicious mischief."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 327,
        "Question": "Is the crime of theft committed by a person who, with intent to gain, takes a worthless check belonging to another without the latter's consent?  a) Yes. All the elements of the crime of theft are present: that there be taking of personal property; that the property belongs to another; and that the taking be done with intent to gain and without the consent of the owner. b) No. The taking of the worthless check, which has no value, would not amount to the crime of theft because of the legal impossibility to commit the intended crime. c) Yes. Theft is committed even if the worthless check would be subsequently dishonored because the taker had intent to gain from the check at the time of the taking. d) Yes. Theft is committed because the factual impossibility to gain from the check was not known to the taker or beyond his control at the time of taking.",
        "Answer": "No. The taking of the worthless check, which has no value, would not amount to the crime of theft because of the legal impossibility to commit the intended crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 328,
        "Question": "Isabel, a housemaid, broke into a pawnshop intent on stealing items of jewelry in it. She found, however, that the jewelry were in a locked chest. Unable to open it, she took the chest out of the shop. What crime did she commit?  (A) Robbery in an uninhabited place or in a private building (B) Theft (C) Robbery in an inhabited house or public building. (D) Qualified theft",
        "Answer": "Qualified theft"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 329,
        "Question": "There is violation of Art. 316, RPC (Other forms of Swindling) where  (A) the owner of property sells a property and subsequently rescinds the sale. (B) the real property subject of the sale does not exist. (C) the property was mortgaged for a usurious contract of loan. (D) the owner disposes of his encumbered real property as if it is free from encumbrances",
        "Answer": "the owner disposes of his encumbered real property as if it is free from encumbrances"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 330,
        "Question": "Any person who, having found lost property, shall fail to deliver the same to the local authorities or to its owner is liable for  (A) occupation or usurpation of personal property. (B) civil damages only. (C) theft. (D) other deceits.",
        "Answer": "theft."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 331,
        "Question": "X draws a check upon request of Y, the payee, who told X that he would merely show the check to his creditor to gain more time to pay his account. The check bounced upon presentation by the creditor. Under the circumstances, who can be prosecuted for estafa based on the dishonored check?  (A) Y as the one who negotiated the check contrary to the agreement (B) X as the drawer of the check (C) Both X and Y based on conspiracy (D) None",
        "Answer": "Y as the one who negotiated the check contrary to the agreement"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 332,
        "Question": "Removing, concealing or destroying documents to defraud another constitutes the crime of estafa if committed by  (A) any public officer. (B) a public officer officially entrusted with the document. (C) private individuals who executed the same. (D) private individuals.",
        "Answer": "a public officer officially entrusted with the document."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 333,
        "Question": "Which of the following circumstances of dishonor of a check can be a basis for prosecution under the bouncing checks law?  (A) The check was returned unpaid with stamp stop payment, although the drawer’s deposit was sufficient. (B) The check, drawn and issued in the Philippines, was dishonored by the drawee bank in a foreign country. (C) The check was presented to the bank for payment 6 months after the date of issue. (D) The drawer of the dishonored check paid its value within 5 days from notice of dishonor.",
        "Answer": "The check was presented to the bank for payment 6 months after the date of issue."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 334,
        "Question": "X and his step-father have a long-standing enmity. One day, irked by an argument with his step-father, X smashed the windshield of his step-father’s brand new Audi sports car. X is liable for  (A) physical injuries. (B) malicious mischief. (C) qualified malicious mischief. (D) civil damages only.",
        "Answer": "civil damages only."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 335,
        "Question": "A and B entered the house of X. A went to X's bedroom and started getting all the valuables... while B entered another room. B saw a male person and immediately B brought out his gun but he accidentally pulled its trigger. The bullet went through the window, hitting a neighbor that killed him... A and B got hold of a young boy and shouted to the policemen... that they would harm the boy if the policemen did not disperse... What crime/s did A, B, and C commit, and what modifying circumstances attended the commission of the crime/s? ",
        "Answer": "A, B and C are principals in the crime of Robbery with Homicide and Serious Illegal Detention, a complex crime. C is liable as a principal by direct participation for the crime of Robbery with Homicide, being in conspiracy... A and B are likewise liable for Direct Assault with Grave Threats... The aggravating circumstances attendant are nighttime, dwelling, and the use of an unlicensed firearm (absorbed as generic aggravating circumstance)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 336,
        "Question": "Madam X, a bank teller... received from depositor Madam Y a check payable to cash... Because the check was not a crossed check, Madam X credited the amount to the account of her good friend, Madam W, by accomplishing a deposit slip... Madam W readily acceded (to withdrawing the money and turning it over to X)... What crime/s, if any, did Madam X and Madam W commit? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Madam X shall be liable as principal in the crime of qualified theft committed with grave abuse of confidence... Being a bank teller, she had only the physical possession not juridical possession of the money received by her. Consequently, her subsequent misappropriation of the same shall constitute the crime of theft, qualified with grave abuse of confidence. Madam W is not criminally liable. She had no knowledge of the crime and withdrew the money from her account and turned over the same to Madam X because of the misrepresentation of the latter..."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 337,
        "Question": "Is the crime of theft susceptible of commission in the frustrated stage? Explain your answer in relation to what produces the crime of theft in its consummated stage and by way of illustration of the subjective and objective phases of the felony. ",
        "Answer": "No. Unlawful taking is deemed complete from the moment the offender gains possession of the thing, even if he has no opportunity to dispose of the same. Unlawful taking, which is the deprivation of one’s personal property, is the element which produces the felony in its consummated stage. At the same time, without unlawful taking as an act of execution, the offense could only be attempted theft, if at all. Thus, the theft cannot have a frustrated stage. Theft can only be attempted or consummated."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 338,
        "Question": "Mr. Ed purchased several plumbing materials in the total amount of P5 million from Mr. Benjie, paying with five (5) postdated checks. All checks were dishonored for insufficiency of funds. Mr. Benjie filed a complaint against Mr. Ed, although no demand letter was earlier sent to Mr. Ed. During the preliminary investigation, Mr. Benjie accepted several amounts from Mr. Ed as partial payments. Mr. Ed counters that no demand letter was earlier sent to him, that the obligation is merely civil in character and that novation took place... Discuss the criminal liability, if any, of Mr. Ed. ",
        "Answer": "Mr. Ed is criminally liable for 5 counts of violation of B.P. 22... The law punishes the mere act of issuing a bouncing check... The absence of a prior demand letter is immaterial to B.P. 22 charges... The defense of novation is not tenable. Criminal liability for violation of B.P. 22 is extinguished only by payment of the full amount of the checks before the filing of the criminal information... Mr. Ed is also criminally liable for 5 counts of Estafa under Art. 315(2)(d) of the Revised Penal Code. All the elements of Estafa are present... Demand for the payment of the check is not an essential element of the crime of estafa. The acceptance of partial payments does not extinguish criminal liability."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 339,
        "Question": "William, whose wife predeceased his mother-in-law, forged the signature of his mother-in-law in a Special Power of Attorney (SPA) and, by using the SPA, sold her properties and converted the proceeds for his own use. William was charged with estafa through falsification of public document. Was the criminal charge proper? ",
        "Answer": "The criminal charge of estafa through falsification is correct. William forged the signature of his mother-in-law in the Special Power of Attorney, which is a public document, as a necessary means to sell her properties to third parties without delivering the proceeds thereof. Although the relationship of affinity... survived the death of either party to the marriage, the coverage of the absolutory cause under Art. 332 (1) of the RPC cannot be applied to him. It is strictly limited to the simple crimes of theft, estafa and malicious mischief. It does not apply where any of the crimes mentioned is complex with another crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 340,
        "Question": "The wife of AAA predeceased his mother-in-law. AAA was accused of defrauding his mother-in-law under a criminal information for estafa, but the actual recital of facts of the offense charged therein, if proven, would constitute not only the crime of estafa, but also falsification of public document as a necessary means for committing estafa. AAA invokes the absolutory cause of relationship by affinity. Which statement is most accurate?  a) The relationship by affinity created between AAA and the blood relatives of his wife is dissolved by the death of his wife and the absolutory cause of relationship by affinity is therefore no longer available to AAA. b) The death of spouse does not severe the relationship by affinity which is an absolutory cause available to AAA for estafa through falsification of public document. c) If AAA commits in a public document the act of falsification as a necessary means to commit estafa, the relationship by affinity still subsists as an absolutory cause for estafa which should be considered separately from the liability for falsification of public document because there is no specific penalty prescribed for the complex crime of estafa through falsification of public document. d) Considering that under the given situation, the two (2) crimes of estafa and falsification of public document are not separate crimes but component crimes of the single complex crime of estafa and falsification of public document, the absolutory cause of relationship by affinity is not available to AAA.",
        "Answer": "Considering that under the given situation, the two (2) crimes of estafa and falsification of public document are not separate crimes but component crimes of the single complex crime of estafa and falsification of public document, the absolutory cause of relationship by affinity is not available to AAA."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 341,
        "Question": "Anthony drew a promissory note and asked his terminally-ill and dying business partner Ben to sign it. The promissory note bound Ben to pay Anthony One Million Pesos (P1,000,000) plus 12% interest, on or before June 30, 2011. If Ben died before the promissory note's due date and Anthony still collected P1,000,000 with interest from Ben's estate, what crime/s did Anthony commit?  (A) Falsification of a public document. (B) Falsification of a private document and estafa. (C) Estafa. (D) Estafa thru falsification of a private document. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "Estafa thru falsification of a private document."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 342,
        "Question": "On June 1, 2011, Efren bought a used top-of-the-line Mercedes Benz for P7.5 Million from Switik Trading. On the same day, he paid P2,500,000 in cash and issued Switik Trading a check for P5,000,000 dated July 31, 2011. He then brought the car to a friend's house and hid it... The check Efren issued was dishonored... Efren was asked to honor and pay the check or to return the car, but he refused. What crime/s did Efren commit?  (A) Carnapping. (B) Estafa and carnapping. (C) A violation of BP Blg. 22. (D) Estafa and a violation of BP Blg. 22. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "Estafa and a violation of BP Blg. 22."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 343,
        "Question": "Frank borrowed P1,000,000 from his brother Eric... Frank issued a post-dated check... Two days before maturity, Frank called Eric telling him he had insufficient funds and requested that the deposit of the check be deferred. Nevertheless, Eric deposited the check and it was dishonored. When Frank failed to pay despite demand, Eric filed a complaint against him for violation of Batas Pambansa Big. 22 (The Bouncing Checks Law). Was the charge brought against Frank correct? ",
        "Answer": "Yes, the charge brought against Frank is correct. Violation of B.P. 22 is malum prohibitum which is committed by mere issuance of a check. Good faith is not a defense... For this reason, the request of Frank to defer the deposit of the check as it has insufficient funds will not militate against his prosecution for B.P. 22. Despite notice, Frank can still be charged. Moreover, if what is charged is Estafa, Frank, being a brother of the offended party, cannot be held criminally liable under Art. 332, RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 344,
        "Question": "What crime is committed by one who defrauds another by taking undue advantage of the signature of the offended party in a blank check and by writing the payee and amount of the check to the prejudice of the offended party?  a) estafa with unfaithfulness or abuse of confidence; b) estafa by false pretense; c) estafa through fraudulent means; d) estafa by other deceits.",
        "Answer": "estafa with unfaithfulness or abuse of confidence;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 345,
        "Question": "Dora gave Elen several pieces of jewelry for sale on commission basis... Elen would remit the proceeds of the sale and return the unsold items to Dora within sixty days. The period expired without Elen remitting the proceeds... Elen still failed to make good on her promise but instead issued post-dated checks... the checks were returned unpaid for insufficient funds. Elen was charged with estafa and violation of Batas Pambansa Big. 22. Will the charges against Elen prosper? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Yes, the charges will prosper. Elen is liable for Estafa through Misappropriation (Art. 315 par. 1(b), RPC) because her failure to remit the proceeds or return the jewelry within 60 days gives rise to the presumption of misappropriation. She is also liable for violation of BP 22 for issuing bouncing checks on account or for value and with knowledge that her funds were insufficient... The crime of estafa was already consummated when the 60-day period expired without Elen accounting for the items."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 346,
        "Question": "Dela convinced Nita to work in Taiwan, promising Nita that she would take care of the processing of the necessary documents. Dela collected P120,000.00 from Nita... Nita later discovered that Dela was not licensed to recruit. Nita confronted Dela and demanded the return of her money. Dela promised to return the same in a week's time. A week later, Dela was nowhere to be found. What crime(s) did Dela commit? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Dela defrauded Nita by leading her to believe that she has the capacity to send her to Taiwan for work, even though she does not have a license or authority for the purpose... As a consequence of Dela’s false pretenses, Nita suffered damages... Thus, the crime of estafa through falsification of public documents is committed. Since Dela has no license to recruit, the crime of illegal recruitment is also committed."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 347,
        "Question": "Will your answer still be the same, assuming that the promise to deploy for employment abroad was made by Dela to Celia, Digna and Emma, in addition to Nita, and from whom Dela also collected the same amount of processing fee? ",
        "Answer": "Yes, Dela shall be liable for both Estafa under Par.2 (a) of Art. 315 of the RPC and Illegal Recruitment, but in large-scale. Illegal recruitment is deemed committed in large scale if committed against three or more persons individually or as a group. Since there are at least 3 victims in this case, Cela, Digna, Emma, and Nita, Dela shall be liable for large scale illegal recruitment under the earlier cited provisions."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 348,
        "Question": "AA misrepresented to the complainant that he had the power, influence, authority and business to obtain overseas employment upon payment of placement fee. AA duly collected the placement fee from complainant. As per certification of the Philippine Overseas Employment Administration, AA did not possess any authority or license for overseas employment. Is it proper to file two (2) separate Informations for illegal recruitment under the Labor Code and for estafa by means of deceit?  a) No. The filing of two (2) separate Informations for illegal recruitment under the Labor Code and for estafa by means of deceit for the same act is violative of the principle against double jeopardy. b) No. One Information for a complex crime of illegal recruitment with estafa by means of deceit should be filed, instead of two (2) separate Informations. c) No. A person convicted of illegal recruitment under the Labor Code may not, for the same act, be separately convicted of estafa by means of deceit. d) Yes. A person convicted of illegal recruitment under the Labor Code may, for the same act, be separately convicted of estafa by means of deceit.",
        "Answer": "Yes. A person convicted of illegal recruitment under the Labor Code may, for the same act, be separately convicted of estafa by means of deceit."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 349,
        "Question": "Bruno found a wallet containing P10,000 cash and IDs belonging to Ms. Y. Bruno used the money to pay his rent. What crime, if any, did Bruno commit? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Bruno committed the crime of theft. The owner is known to Bruno because there are IDs found in the wallet. Failure to deliver to the local authorities or to its owner the lost property which he found constitutes theft under Article 308 of the Revised Penal Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 350,
        "Question": "Assuming that instead of using the money, Bruno turned over the wallet and its contents to the nearby police station, and it was the chief of police of that station who appropriated the money for his own benefit, what crime was committed by the chief of police? ",
        "Answer": "The chief of police is liable for the crime of malversation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 351,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. A person who, on the occasion of a robbery, kills a bystander by accident is liable for two separate crimes: robbery and reckless imprudence resulting in homicide.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. Only one crime of robbery with homicide is constituted because the Revised Penal Code punishes the crimes as only one indivisible offense when a killing, whether intentional or accidental, was committed by reason or on occasion of a robbery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 352,
        "Question": "On her way home, Eva Marie saw an injured chow chow puppy behind a bush. Since the puppy did not have a collar, she brought it home so she could have it as a pet... Did Eva Marie incur criminal liability in bringing the puppy home as a pet? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes, Eva Marie incurred criminal liability for the crime of simple theft. The puppy is personal property which, is susceptible of taking and has pecuniary value. Obviously, she took it with intent to own it; hence, with intent to gain."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 353,
        "Question": "Did she incur civil liability (for taking the puppy)? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Eva Marie may incur civil liability if the owner of the puppy would incur a loss due to non-restitution or return thereof to the owner... Once Eva Marie is found guilty of theft, she will incur civil liability, which consists of restitution or reparation for damage caused and indemnification for consequential damages, Art. 100 RPC). The general rule is: a person who is criminally liable is also civilly liable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 354,
        "Question": "Paul lives with his long-time girlfriend Joan in a condominium... he has been secretly saving money in an envelope under their bed... Joan... found the envelope, took the money and left Paul. As prosecutor, what crime, if any would you charge Joan? Explain  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Joan may be charged with qualified theft because she took away personal property belonging to Paul without the latter’s consent, so obviously with intent to gain and with grave abuse of confidence. But Joan may invoke as a defense Art.332 of the Revised Penal Code, under which no criminal liability but only civil liability shall result from the crime of theft, swindling or malicious mischief committed by spouses, among others. The reference to theft under Article embraces both simple theft and qualified theft, and the reference to spouses includes common-law or live-in relationship."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 355,
        "Question": "Christopher, John, Richard, and Luke are fraternity brothers... One night, after attending a party, they boarded a taxicab, held the driver at gunpoint and took the latter's earnings. What crime, if any, did the four commit? Enumerate the elements of the crime.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The crime committed is robbery by a band since there were four (4) offenders acting in concert in committing the robbery and all the four were armed. The elements of this crime are: 1. unlawful taking of personal property belonging to another (the earnings of the taxi-driver); 2. intent to gain in the taking; 3. violence against or intimidation of person or force upon things was employed in the taking; and 4. there were more than three armed malefactors taking part in the commission of the robbery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 356,
        "Question": "Who are brigands? Distinguish brigandage from robbery in band as to elements, purpose of the offender and agreement among the offenders. ",
        "Answer": "When more than three armed persons form a band of robbers for the purpose of committing robbery in the highway, or kidnapping persons for the purpose of extortion or to obtain ransom, for any other purpose to be attained by means of force and violence, they shall be deemed highway robbers or brigands (Art. 306, RPC)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 357,
        "Question": "Senio planned to burn Bal's house... Carlo warned Bal that Senio would burn his house... Senio went to Bal' s house and proceeded to pour gasoline around the walls of the house and it was at that point when he was caught by the police. What crime did Senio commit, if any? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Senio committed frustrated arson under Article 3 of the RPC. He performed all the acts of execution which would produce the felony (i.e. procuring gasoline and pouring it around the walls) but did not produce the crime of arson by reason of independent cause (i.e. the intervention of the police). (ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: The crime could only be malicious mischief as the problem does not mention that he is carrying a match or a lighter. It was not shown that SEnio was about to light a match or ignite a lighter to set the house on fire.)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 358,
        "Question": "Ofelia, engaged in the purchase and sale of jewelry, was charged with violation of PD 1612, otherwise known as the Anti-Fencing Law, for having been found in possession of recently stolen jewelry... Her defense is that she merely bought the same from Antonia and produced a receipt covering the sale. She presented other receipts... What is a “fence” under PD 1612?  ",
        "Answer": "A “fence” is any person who, with intent to gain for himself or for another, shall buy, receive, possess, keep, acquire, conceal, sell or dispose of, or shall in any manner deal in or dispose of any object, item or item of value which he knows or should be known to him, to have been derived from the proceeds of the crime of robbery or theft."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 359,
        "Question": "Is Ofelia liable under the Anti-Fencing Law? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "Yes. Under Section 5 of PD No. 1612, mere possession of any good, article, item, object, or anything of value which has been the subject of robbery or thievery shall be prima facie evidence of fencing. Failure to prove that Ofelia knows; or should have known that the jewelry is stolen, therefore, is not a defense since this element is presumed to be present under Section 5 because Ofelia is in possession of this stolen property. Moreover, there is no showing that Ofelia secured a permit or clearance from the PNP station commander of the place of sale required in Section 6 of PD No. 1612."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 360,
        "Question": "Manolo... noticed a nice painting that exactly looked like the painting which he reported was stolen from him some years back. Manolo confronted Tonio about the painting, but Tonio denied any knowledge... Tonio may be charged with what crime/s, if any? ",
        "Answer": "Tonio may be charged with the crime of fencing. Under Sec. 5 of P.D. 1612, mere possession of a stolen article or object or anything of value which has been the subject of robbery or thievery is prima facie evidence of fencing. Since Tonio is in possession of a stolen property, it is presumed that he committed the crime of fencing."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 361,
        "Question": "Manolo decided to take matters into his own hands and, one night, broke into Tonio’s house by destroying the wall and taking the painting. What, if any, would be the liability of Manolo? ",
        "Answer": "Manalo is liable for the crime of trespass to dwelling qualified by use of force since he entered the house of Tonio against the latter’s will. There is no robbery because the owner of the property taken cannot commit robbery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 362,
        "Question": "Roberto bought a Toyota Fortuner from Iñigo for P500,000... When the policeman checked the plate, chassis and motor numbers... he found the chassis and motor numbers to be different from what the Registration Certificate stated... The chassis and motor numbers on the Fortuner were found... to correspond to a vehicle previously reported as carnapped. Roberto claimed that he was in good faith... If you were the prosecutor, would you or would you not charge Roberto with a crime? ",
        "Answer": "I will charge Roberto with violation of Anti-Fencing Law. In this case, someone carnapped the vehicle, sold it to Roberto who did not take part in the crime. Roberto should have known also that the car was stolen because it was not properly documented as the deed of sale and registration certificate did not reflect the correct numbers of the vehicle’s engine and chassis. Apparently, he made no effort to check the papers covering his purchase. Lastly, Roberto’s defense of good faith is flawed because P.D. 1612 is a special law and, therefore, its violation is regarded as malum prohibitum, requiring no proof of criminal intent."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 363,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. In a prosecution for fencing under R D. 1612, it is a complete defense for the accused to prove that he had no knowledge that the goods or articles found in his possession had been the subject of robbery.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. Fencing is committed if the accused should have known that the goods or articles had been the subject of theft or robbery (P.D. 1612, Sec. 2[a]). Mere possession of the stolen goods gives rise to the prima facie presumption of fencing."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 364,
        "Question": "Arlene is engaged in the buy and sell of used garments... Among the items found by the police in a raid of her store in Baguio City were brand – new Louie Feraud blazers. Arlene was charged with fencing. Will the charge prosper? Why or why not?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, a charge of fencing will not prosper. “Fencing” is committed when a person, with intent to gain for himself or for another, deals in any manner with an article of value which he knows or should be known to him to have been derived from proceeds of theft or robbery. Thus, for a charge of fencing to prosper, it must first be proven that the goods or items found in the possession of the accused were the proceeds of theft or robbery, the corpus delicti of fencing. The mere possession of the blazers is not sufficient to establish that they were the result of a theft or robbery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 365,
        "Question": "Val, a Nigerian, set up a perfume business... The investors would buy the raw materials... Val made a written commitment... that he would buy back the gel at a higher price... When the amounts to be paid by Val... reached millions of pesos, he sold all the equipment... absconded... What crime or crimes were committed, if any? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "The crime committed is estafa through false pretenses (Art. 315 par. 2(a)). Val defrauded the investors by falsely pretending to possess business or imaginary transactions. The fact that he sold all the equipment of his perfume business, and absconded with the money when the amounts to be paid by him to the investors reached millions of pesos shows that the transaction or his business is imaginary, and he defrauded the victims."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 366,
        "Question": "A asked financial support from her showbiz friend B who accommodated her by issuing in her favor a post-dated check in the sum of P90,000.00. Both of them knew that the check would not be honored because B’s account had just been closed. The two then approached trader C whom they asked to change the check with cash, even agreeing that the exchange be discounted at P85,000.00... Upon C’s presentment of the check for payment... it was dishonored because the account has already been closed. What action/s may C commence against A and B to hold them to account for the loss of her P85,000.00? Explain. (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "A criminal action for violation of BP22 may be filed against B who drew the postdated check against a closed bank account, for value paid by C, and with knowledge at the time he issued the check that the account thereof is already closed. A cannot be held liable under BP 22 because he was a mere endorser of B’s check to C who exchanged the check with cash. BP22 does not apply to endorser of checks. Hence only a civil action may be filed by C against A to recover the P85,000.00."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 367,
        "Question": "Three persons who owned and controlled a corporation (P, Q and R) were charged with Syndicated Estafa for defrauding complainants by falsely manifesting that the corporation was engaged in foreign exchange trading... and that these resulted to the damage and prejudice of the complainants and other persons... Will the case for syndicated estafa prosper? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, a case for syndicated estafa will not prosper because a syndicate for such crime under Pres. Decree 1689 must be comprised of five (5) or more persons committing the estafa or other forms of swindling defined in Arts. 315 and 316 of the Revised Penal Code; whereas the case given involved only three (3) accused who are alleged to have conspired in the commission of the swindling. But because the amount defrauded exceeds P100,000.00, the case is still under the same P.D. 1689 with a lower penalty than syndicated estafa."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 368,
        "Question": "Percy, Pablo, Pater and Sencio commandeered an MMDA bus... Pater killed a Barangay Tanod... They also took the money and valuables of the passengers... and set the bus on fire. State your legal opinion on the recommendation of the police authorities on the criminal liabilities incurred by Percy, Pablo, Pater and Sencio. (10%) (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Because Percy, Pablo, Pater and Sencio commandeered the bus for purpose of robbing the passengers, the crime committed is robbery... Since death results by reason or on occasion of robbery, the crime committed is a special complex crime of robbery with homicide... Even though only Pater killed the Tanod, Percy, Pablo, and Sencio are also liable for robbery with homicide since they failed to attempt to prevent the same... Arson shall not be considered as a separate crime but as a mere aggravating circumstance of commission of the felony by means of fire... Since the crime committed is robbery with homicide, all other felonies such as arson and direct assault committed by reason or on occasion of robbery shall be integrated into the special complex crime of robbery with homicide."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 369,
        "Question": "A took B's car for a 'joy ride' but abandoned it after several hours, intact and undamaged. What crime or crimes, if any, were committed? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "The crime committed by A is carnapping. The unlawful taking of motor vehicles is now covered by the Anti-Carnapping Law (R.A. 6539 as amended), and not by the provisions on qualified theft or robbery... In this case, A took the car without consent of B with intent to temporarily deprive him of the car... when a person... takes possession of a vehicle belonging to another, without the consent of its owner, he is guilty of theft because by taking possession of the personal property belonging to another and using it, his intent to gain is evident since he derives therefrom utility; satisfaction, enjoyment and pleasure."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 370,
        "Question": "What should be the proper charge against an offender who unlawfully took and carried away a motor vehicle belonging to another without the latter's consent, killing the driver in the process?  a) The proper charge against the offender should be murder with the use of motor vehicle. b) The proper charge against the offender should be qualified carnapping or carnapping in an aggravated form. c) The proper charge against the offender should be carnapping and homicide. d) The proper charge against the offender should be robbery with homicide.",
        "Answer": "The proper charge against the offender should be qualified carnapping or carnapping in an aggravated form."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 371,
        "Question": "Using his charms because of his movie star looks, Phil, in a movie date with Lyn, a 19-year old colegiala, kissed her on the cheek and stroked her pubic hair. Lyn shouted for help and Phil was arrested. Phil is liable for ______ .  (A) rape by sexual assault for using his fingers (B) violation of the Anti-Child Abuse Law for lascivious conduct (C) unjust vexation (D) acts of lasciviousness (E) None of the above",
        "Answer": "acts of lasciviousness"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 372,
        "Question": "Filipino citizens Hector and Wendy were married in New York... Hector found a video of Wendy and another man Ariel, in the act of sexual intercourse... Angered by what he saw, he filed a complaint for adultery against Wendy and Ariel... it was proved that Wendy was born male and underwent sex reassignment later in life. What is an impossible crime? Can there be an impossible crime of adultery? ",
        "Answer": "An impossible crime is an act which would be an offense against persons or property, were it not for the inherent impossibility of its accomplishment or on account of the employment of inadequate or ineffectual means. There is no impossible crime of adultery since this is a crime against chastity, and not against person or property."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 373,
        "Question": "Loko, promised Ganda a modeling career but instead brought her to a photo shoot where she was told to pose nude, then later forced her to engage in prostitution. Ganda was 16 years old. What crime or crimes did Loko commit? ",
        "Answer": "Loko is liable of the crime of Trafficking in Persons under RA 9208. He recruited, offered and hired Ganda by means of fraud or deception for the purpose of exploitation or prostitution. Ganda’s minority is a qualifying circumstance. Under Section 6, RA 9208, when the trafficked person is a child, the crime committed is Qualified Trafficking in Persons, penalized by life imprisonment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 374,
        "Question": "The prescriptive period for bigamy is 15 years counted from the date of the  (A) discovery of the second marriage by the offended spouse. (B) registration of the second marriage in the Local Civil Registry. (C) celebration or solemnization of the second marriage. (D) discovery of the second marriage by the authorities.",
        "Answer": "discovery of the second marriage by the authorities."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 375,
        "Question": "What are the elements of the crime of bigamy? If you were the judge in a bigamy case where the defense was able to prove that the first marriage was null and void or a nullity, would you render a judgment of conviction or acquittal? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The following are the elements of bigamy: 1. the offender has been legally married; 2. the marriage has not been legally dissolved or, in case of absence, the absent spouse vould not yet be presumed dead according to NCC; 3. he contracts a second or subsequent marriage; and 4. the subsequent marriage has all the essential requisites for validity... If I were the judge, I will render judgment of conviction. Proof that the first marriage is null and void is not a defense in bigamy. As long as the previous marriage was not lawfully dissolved or judicially declared as null and void, contracting a new marriage constitutes bigamy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 376,
        "Question": "Assuming the existence of the first marriage when accused contracted the second marriage and the subsequent judicial declaration of nullity of the second marriage on the ground of psychological incapacity, would you render a judgment of conviction or acquittal? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "I will render a judgment of conviction. A declaration of the nullity of the second marriage on the ground of psychological incapacity is absolutely of no moment insofar as the State’s penal laws are concerned... the nullity of this second marriage is not per se an argument for the avoidance of criminal liability for bigamy. To hold otherwise would render the State’s penal laws on bigamy completely nugatory."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 377,
        "Question": "A, B, C and D are members of the police department of a municipality. Conspiring with one another, they arrested E, without reasonable ground, for the purpose of delivering him to the proper authorities by imputing to E the crime of bribery. While E was being investigated... one of them placed a marked five hundred peso bill... to make it appear that E... agreed to perform an act not constituting a crime in connection with the performance of E's duties... What is the crime committed by A, B, C and D?  a) A, B, C and D committed incriminatory machination through unlawful arrest. b) A, B, C and D committed intriguing against honor with unlawful arrest. c) A, B, C and D committed slight illegal detention. d) A, B, C and D committed corruption of public official.",
        "Answer": "A, B, C and D committed incriminatory machination through unlawful arrest."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 378,
        "Question": "Plaintiff X said in his civil complaint for damages that defendant Y, employing fraud, convinced him to buy a defective vehicle. Y filed a criminal action for libel against X for maliciously imputing fraud on him. Will the action prosper if it turns out that the civil complaint for damages was baseless?  (A) No, since pleadings filed in court are absolutely privileged. (B) No, since malice is not evident. (C) Yes, given the fact that the imputation of fraud was baseless. (D) Yes, parties must state the truth in their pleadings.",
        "Answer": "No, since pleadings filed in court are absolutely privileged."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 379,
        "Question": "X, a tabloid columnist, wrote an article describing Y, a public official, as stupid, corrupt, and having amassed ill-gotten wealth. X relied on a source from Y's own office who fed him the information. Did X commit libel?  (A) Yes, since the article was libelous and inconsistent with good faith and reasonable care. (B) No, since X but made a fair commentary on a matter of public interest. (C) No, since X’s article constitutes privileged communication. (D) No, since he wrote his article under the freedom enjoyed by the press.",
        "Answer": "Yes, since the article was libelous and inconsistent with good faith and reasonable care."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 380,
        "Question": "The exchanges of highly offensive words between two quarrelling women in the presence of a crowd of people constitute  (A) one count of grave slander against the woman who uttered the more insulting expressions. (B) grave slander against the woman who started it and light slander against the other woman. (C) two separate counts of light slander, one for each woman. (D) two separate counts of grave slander, one against each of them.",
        "Answer": "two separate counts of light slander, one for each woman."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 381,
        "Question": "X, a court employee, wrote the presiding judge a letter, imputing to Y, also a court employee, the act of receiving an expensive gift from one of the parties in a pending case. Because of this, Y accused X of libel. Does Y need to prove the element of malice in the case?  (A) No, since malice is self-evident in the letter. (B) Yes, malice is not presumed since X wrote the letter to the presiding judge who has a duty to act on what it states. (C) No, since malice is presumed with respect to defamatory imputations. (D) Yes, since malice is not presumed in libel.",
        "Answer": "Yes, malice is not presumed since X wrote the letter to the presiding judge who has a duty to act on what it states."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 382,
        "Question": "Sam wrote a letter to his friends stating that Judge Odon loves obscene magazines and keeps these in his desk. Charged with libel, can Sam present proof that Judge Odon indeed loves obscene magazines and keeps these in his desk?  (A) No, since the imputation is not related to the duties of a judge. (B) No, since Sam does not impute a crime to Judge Odon. (C) No, since Sam imputes the commission of a crime to Judge Odon. (D) Yes, since truth can be a valid defense in libel.",
        "Answer": "No, since the imputation is not related to the duties of a judge."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 383,
        "Question": "In her weekly gossip column in a tabloid, Gigi wrote an unflattering article about Pablo, a famous singer, and his bitter separation from his wife... Pablo charged Gigi with libel. In her defense, Gigi countered that she did not commit libel because Pablo has attained the status of a public figure so that even his personal life has become a legitimate subject of public interest and comment. Is Gigi correct?  (A) Yes, because Pablo’s private life has become a public interest. (B) No, because Pablo's private life, even if he is a celebrity, is not a subject of privileged communication. (C) No, Gigi must have been motivated by actual malice to be liable. (D) Yes, but Gigi must show that the imputation is true and made with good motives and for justifiable ends.",
        "Answer": "No, because Pablo's private life, even if he is a celebrity, is not a subject of privileged communication."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 384,
        "Question": "In his Answer to a complaint, Atty. Jose (counsel for the defendant) stated that Atty. Agrada (counsel for the plaintiff) is bobo, inutile, good for nothing, stupid, and a menace to clients. Can Atty. Jose be held criminally liable for libel?  a. No, because an Answer to a complaint is a court pleading where communications made are privileged; the writer cannot be held liable for libel. b. Yes, because the statement casts aspersion on the character, integrity and reputation of Atty. Agrada as a lawyer and exposed him to public ridicule. c. Yes, although a court pleading is a privileged communication, malicious statements that are irrelevant and impertinent to the issue in the pleading may be libelous. d. Yes, there was a malicious intent to ridicule Atty. Agrada as a lawyer. e. No, because the statement is in a pleading, but Atty. Jose can be charged administratively for misconduct before the Supreme Court.",
        "Answer": "Yes, although a court pleading is a privileged communication, malicious statements that are irrelevant and impertinent to the issue in the pleading may be libelous."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 385,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. To secure a conviction for libel, the prosecution must prove that the defamatory statement is false.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "False. The law presumes malice in every defamatory imputation unless the same constitutes a privileged communication."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 386,
        "Question": "Angeline maintains a website where visitors can give their comments... Bettina posted a comment that the red Birkin bag shown in Angelina’s website is fake and that Angelina is known to sell counterfeit items. Angelina wants to file a case against Bettina. She seeks your advice. What advice will you give her? (4%) (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will advise Angelina to file a criminal case of libel against Bettina because the imputations made by Bettina is libelous. Whether the imputation of a defect, status, or condition is real or imaginary, if it publicly tends to discredit, dishonor or place in contempt or ridicule a particular person who is identified, the imputation is presumed by law to be malicious and thus penalized as libel under Art 355 of the Revised Penal Code. Moreover, if Bettina is engaged in similar line of trade, her statement against the goods sold by Angelina may constitute a violation of the law on Unfair Competition (Rep. Act No. 8291.)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 387,
        "Question": "AB was driving a van along a highway. Because of her recklessness, the van hit a car which had already entered the intersection. As a result, CD who was driving the car suffered physical injuries, while damage to his car amounted to P8,500.00. What is the proper charge against AB?  a) AB should be charged with complex crime of reckless imprudence resulting in damage to property with slight physical injuries. b) AB should be charged with reckless imprudence resulting in slight physical injuries and reckless imprudence resulting in damage to property. c) AB should be charged with complex crime of slight physical injuries with damage to property. d) AB should be charged with slight physical injuries and reckless imprudence resulting in damage to property.",
        "Answer": "AB should be charged with reckless imprudence resulting in slight physical injuries and reckless imprudence resulting in damage to property."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 388,
        "Question": "After drinking a bottle of Jack Daniels, Jonjon drove his BMW sports car at high speed, rammed into a group of crossing pedestrians, and hit a traffic light post. The incident caused the death of one (1) pedestrian, serious injuries to three (3) others, and the destruction of the traffic light post. If you were the prosecutor, what would you charge Jonjon?  (A) Homicide with serious physical injuries through simple negligence. (B) Damage to property, serious physical injuries and homicide through reckless negligence. (C) Simple negligence resulting in damage to property, serious physical injuries and homicide. (D) Reckless imprudence resulting in homicide, serious physical injuries and damage to property.",
        "Answer": "Reckless imprudence resulting in homicide, serious physical injuries and damage to property."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 389,
        "Question": "A crime resulting from negligence, reckless imprudence, lack of foresight or lack of skill is called  (A) dolo. (B) culpa. (C) tortious crimes. (D) quasi delict.",
        "Answer": "culpa."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 390,
        "Question": "Culpa can either be a crime by itself or a mode of committing a crime. Culpa is a crime by itself in  (A) reckless imprudence resulting in murder. (B) medical malpractice. (C) serious physical Injuries thru reckless imprudence. (D) complex crime of reckless imprudence resulting in serious physical injuries.",
        "Answer": "serious physical Injuries thru reckless imprudence."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 391,
        "Question": "The maxim 'Nullum crimen nula poena sine lege' means that  (A) the act is criminal at the time of its commission and recognized as such at the time of its commission but the penalty therefor is prescribed in a subsequently enacted law. (B) the act is criminal and punished under and pursuant to common law. (C) there is a crime for as long as the act is inherently evil. (D) crime is a product of the law.",
        "Answer": "crime is a product of the law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 392,
        "Question": "Motive is generally IMMATERIAL in determining criminal liability EXCEPT when  (A) several offenders committed the crime but the court wants to ascertain which of them acted as leader. (B) the evidence of the crime consists of both direct and circumstantial evidence. (C) ascertaining the degree of penalty that may be imposed on the offender. (D) the evidence of guilt of the accused is circumstantial.",
        "Answer": "the evidence of guilt of the accused is circumstantial."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 393,
        "Question": "X inflicted serious injuries on Y. Because of delay in providing medical treatment to Y, he died. Is X criminally liable for the death of Y?  (A) Yes because the delay did not break the causal connection between X’s felonious act and the injuries sustained by Y. (B) Yes because any intervening cause between the infliction of injury and death is immaterial. (C) No because the infliction of injury was not the immediate cause of the death. (D) No because the delay in the administration of the medical treatment was an intervening cause.",
        "Answer": "Yes because the delay did not break the causal connection between X’s felonious act and the injuries sustained by Y."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 394,
        "Question": "X inflicted violent kicks on vital parts of E’s body. E nevertheless was able to flee for fear of his life. Refusing to undergo treatment for his injuries, E died 3 days later. Is X liable for E’s death?  (A) No, since kicks on the body cannot cause death. (B) No, since it took too long for death to occur. (C) Yes, since E cannot be compelled to undergo medical treatment. (D) Yes, since it was a natural result of the injuries X inflicted on E.",
        "Answer": "Yes, since it was a natural result of the injuries X inflicted on E."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 395,
        "Question": "(a) Distinguish crimes mala in se from crimes mala prohibita.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "Mala in se and mala prohibita are distinguished as follows: (1) Mala in Se are inherently wrong or immoral, while mala prohibita are not inherently wrong; they are only wrong because they are prohibited by law; (2) In mala in se, good faith or lack of criminal intent is a defense, while in mala prohibita, good faith is not a defense; (3) Modifying circumstances can be appreciated in mala in se. These circumstances cannot be appreciated in mala prohibitia, unless the special law that punishes them adopts the technical nomenclature of the penalties of the Revised Penal Code; (4) Mala in se are punishable under the Revised Penal Code; or special laws where the acts punishable therein are wrong by nature. Mala prohibita are punishable under special laws."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 396,
        "Question": "Choose from the list below the correct principle in considering 'motive'.  (A) If the evidence is merely circumstantial, proof of motive is essential. (B) Generally, proof of motive is not necessary to pin a crime on the accused if the commission of the crime has been proven and the evidence of identification is convincing. (C) Motive is important to ascertain the truth between two antagonistic theories. (D) Motive is relevant if the identity of the accused is uncertain. (E) All of the above are correct.",
        "Answer": "All of the above are correct."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 397,
        "Question": "The acquittal of an accused shall bar the civil action arising from the crime where the judgment of acquittal holds that ______.  (A) the acquittal is based on reasonable doubt (B) the liability of the accused is not criminal but civil in nature (C) the civil liability does not arise from or is not based on the criminal act for which the accused has been acquitted (D) the accused did not commit the act imputed to him",
        "Answer": "the accused did not commit the act imputed to him"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 398,
        "Question": "Subsidiary liability may be imposed on the following, except ______.  (A) innkeepers, in relation to the crime committed in their establishment (B) employers engaged in industry, for the crime committed by their employees (C) parents of minors who act with discernment in committing crimes (D) hospital administrators or owners, for crimes committed by their hospital nurses",
        "Answer": "hospital administrators or owners, for crimes committed by their hospital nurses"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 399,
        "Question": "Luis was sentenced to prison mayor and to pay a fine of P50,000.00, with subsidiary imprisonment in case of insolvency. Is the sentence correct?  (A) Yes, because Luis has no property to pay for the fine, so he must suffer the equivalent imprisonment provided by law in lieu of fine. (B) No, because subsidiary imprisonment is applicable only when the penalty imposed is prison correctional or below. (C) Yes, because the sentence says so. (D) No, because the subsidiary imprisonment is applicable only when the penalty imposed is limited to a fine. (E) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "No, because subsidiary imprisonment is applicable only when the penalty imposed is prison correctional or below."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 400,
        "Question": "X, without intent to kill, aimed his gun at Z and fired it, hitting the latter who died as a consequence. Under the circumstances  (A) X cannot plead praetor intentionem since the intent to kill is presumed from the killing of the victim. (B) X may plead praetor intentionem since he intended only to scare, not kill Z. (C) X may plead aberratio ictus as he had no intention to hit Z. (D) X may plead commission of only Discharge of Firearm as he had no intent to kill Z when he fired his gun.",
        "Answer": "X may plead praetor intentionem since he intended only to scare, not kill Z."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 401,
        "Question": "Ando, an Indonesian national who just visited the Philippines, purchased a ticket for a passenger vessel bound for Hong Kong. While on board the vessel, he saw his mortal enemy lason, also an Indonesian national, seated at the back portion of the cabin and who was busy reading a newspaper. Ando stealthily approached lason and when he was near him, Ando stabbed and killed lason. The vessel is registered in Malaysia. The killing happened just a few moments after the vessel left the port of Manila. Operatives from the PNP Maritime Command arrested Ando. Presented for the killing of lason, Ando contended that he did not incur criminal liability because both he and the victim were Indonesians. He likewise argued that he could not be prosecuted in Manila because the vessel is a Malaysian-registered ship. Discuss the merits of Ando’s contentions. ",
        "Answer": "Both contentions of Ando lack merit. Under the generality principle, penal laws shall be obligatory upon all who live or sojourn in the Philippine territory. The foreign characteristic of an offender and offended party does not exclude him from operation of penal laws. Under the Revised Penal Code, except as provided in treaties and laws of preferential application, penal laws of the Philippines shall have force and effect within its territory. Here, since the killing took place within the Philippine territory, our penal laws applies and Ando may be held criminally responsible despite his being an Indonesian citizen. Likewise, the contention of Ando that he could not be prosecuted in Manila because the vessel is a Malaysian-registered ship is without merit. Under the English Rule, crimes committed aboard a vessel within the territorial waters of a country are triable in the courts of such country except when crimes merely affect things within the vessel or when they only refer to the internal management thereof. Here, since the crime was committed within the Philippine waters and neither exception applies, Ando may be prosecuted in Manila."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 402,
        "Question": "DO, intending to kill EE, peppered the latter's bedroom with bullets, but since the intended victim was not home at that time, no harm came to him. What crime is committed?  a) DO committed the crime of attempted murder. b) DO committed the crime of attempted homicide. c) DO committed the crime of impossible crime. (Intod vs. CA, GR 103119, October 21,1992) d) DD committed the crime of malicious mischief.",
        "Answer": "DO committed the crime of impossible crime."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 403,
        "Question": "Puti detested Pula, his roommate, because Pula was courting Ganda, whom Puti fancied. One day, Puti decided to teach Pula a lesson and went to a veterinarian (Vet) to ask for poison on the pretext that he was going to kill a sick pet, when actually Puti was intending to poison Pula. The Vet instantly gave Puti a non-toxic solution which, when mixed with Pula’s food, did not kill Pula.  (A) What crime, if any, did Puti commit? (B) Would your answer be the same if, as a result of the mixture, Pula got an upset stomach and had to be hospitalized for 10 days?",
        "Answer": "(A) Puti committed the impossible crime of murder. All the elements of an impossible crime are present. Puti’s act of mixing a solution with Pula’s food would have been murder, a crime against persons. The act was done with evil intent which is to kill Pula. However, the crime was not accomplished because of the employment of ineffectual means, i.e., the solution turned out to be non-toxic which would not kill Pula. And said act would not fall under any other provision of the RPC. (B) No, my answer would not be the same. If as a result of the mixture, Pula got an upset stomach and had to be hospitalized for 10 days, the crime committed by Puti is Less Serious Physical Injuries. It is not an impossible crime because the last element of an impossible requires that the act performed should not constitute a violation of another provision of the RPC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 404,
        "Question": "Carla, four (4) years old, was kidnapped by Enrique, the tricycle driver engaged by her parents to drive her to and from school every day. Enrique wrote a ransom note demanding that Carla’s parents pay him P500,000.00 ransom in exchange for her liberty. However, before the ransom note could be received by Carla’s parents, Enrique’s hideout was discovered by the police. Carla was rescued while Enrique was arrested. The prosecutor considered that the ransom note was never received by Carla’s parents and filed a case of 'Impossible crime to commit kidnapping' against Enrique. Is the prosecutor correct? If he is not correct, can he instead file a case of grave coercion? ",
        "Answer": "The Prosecutor is not correct. There is no 'Impossible crime to commit kidnapping'. First, an impossible crime applies only to Crimes against Persons and Crimes against Property under Titles 8 and 10 of the RPC, respectively. Kidnapping is a Crime against Personal Liberty and Security under Title 9, RPC. Second, even if the ransom note was not received by Carla’s parents, the crime of kidnapping and serious illegal detention for ransom is already consummated. Under Article 267, RPC, Kidnapping for Ransom is committed 'when the kidnapping or detention is for the purpose of extorting ransom from the victim or any other person.' To consummate the crime, it suffices that the purpose is to extort ransom; it is not necessary that the ransom note be received or that ransom be paid. No, the Prosecutor cannot file a case of grave coercion because the crime committed, as explained above, is kidnapping for ransom."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 405,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Felonies – Impossible crime of murder Charlie hated his classmate, Brad, because the latter was assiduously courting Lily, Charlie’s girlfriend. Charlie went to a veterinarian and asked for some poison on the pretext that it would be used to kill a very sick, old dog. Actually, Charlie intended to use the poison on Brad. The veterinarian mistakenly gave Charlie a non-toxic powder which, when mixed with Brad’s food, did not kill Brad. [a] Did Charlie commit any crime? If so; what and why? If not, why not?  (2009 Bar Question) [b] Would your answer be the same if Brad proved to be allergic to the powder, and after ingesting it with his food, fell ill and was hospitalized for ten (10) days? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "[a] Charlie committed an impossible crime of murder. His act of mixing the non-toxic powder with Brad’s food, done with intent to kill, would have constituted murder which is a crime against persons, had it not been for the employment of a means which, unknown to him, is ineffectual (Art.4, par. 2, RPC). [b] No, the answer would not be the same. Charlie would be, criminally liable for less serious physical injuries because his act of mixing the powder with Brad’s food was done with felonious intent and was the proximate cause of Brad’s illness for 10 days. It cannot constitute attempted murder, although done with intent to kill, because the means employed is inherently ineffectual to cause death and the crime committed must be directly linked to the means employed, not to the intent. Liability for an impossible crime can only arise from a consummated act."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 406,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Stages of execution – Frustrated murder Delmo learned that his enemy, Oscar, was confined at the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) of the Philippine Medical Center. Intending to kill Oscar, Delmo disguised himself as a nurse, entered the ICU, and saw a man lying on the hospital bed with several life-saving tubes attached to the body. Delmo disconnected the tubes and left. Later, the resident physician doing his rounds entered the ICU and, seeing the disconnected tubes, reconnected them. Oscar survived. Delmo was charged with frustrated murder. Discuss the propriety of the charge. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Delmo was correctly charged with the crime of frustrated murder qualified by treachery—not evident premeditation because the victim was different from the one premeditated against. All the elements of frustrated murder are present, namely: (1) Delmo had the intent to kill Oscar; (2) Delmo performed an overt act which would have produced the felony of murder as a consequence; (3) the felony was not produced, but not due to the spontaneous desistance of Delmo; and (4) the overt act of Delmo was sufficient in itself to consummate the felony of murder."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 407,
        "Question": "Overjoyed by the award to his firm of a multi-billion government contract, the President of the construction company threw a party for his top executives and staff. The President made a toast: 'We have to do everything to make this project succeed. I want all of you to work together.' He then gave each one of his executives P1 million in cash. The executives were: the Vice-President for Finance, the Vice-President for Operations, the Vice-President for Administration, the Vice-President for Legal, and the Vice-President for Marketing. The President also gave P100,000.00 to each of the ten (10) staff members of the company. The executives and staff members knew that the President was alluding to the giving of bribes to government officials to ensure that the project would succeed. (b) Define wheel conspiracy and chain conspiracy. Is either or both kinds existent herein? Explain your answer. (4%)",
        "Answer": "(b) In the case at bar, both type of conspiracy exists. Wheel conspiracy refers to a large scale conspiracy where one person at the center (hub) transacts illegal business with various other persons (spokes). In this case, the President is the hub and the executives are the spokes. Chain conspiracy refers to a conspiracy where there is successive communication and cooperation in a series to achieve a common illegal objective. In this case, the executives and staff members form the chain."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 408,
        "Question": "(A) Define malfeasance, misfeasance and nonfeasance.  (B) Differentiate wheel conspiracy and chain conspiracy.  ",
        "Answer": "(A) 'Malfeasance' is the doing of an act which a person ought not to do at all. 'Misfeasance' is the improper doing of an act which a person mayor might lawfully do. 'Nonfeasance' is the omission of an act which a person ought to do. — (Black’s Dictionary, 6th Edition, West Publishing 1990) (B) There are two structures of multiple conspiracies, namely: wheel or circle conspiracy and chain conspiracy. In a wheel or circle conspiracy, there is a single person or group (the hub) dealing individually with two or more other persons or groups (the spokes). In a chain conspiracy, there is a successive communication and cooperation in a series to achieve a common illegal objective."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 409,
        "Question": "During trial for theft in 2014, the prosecution managed to show that accused AA has also been convicted by final judgment for robbery in 2003, but she eluded capture. A subsequent verification showed that AA had several convictions, to wit: 1. In 1998, she was convicted of estafa; 2. In 2002, she was convicted of theft; 3. In 2004, she was convicted of frustrated homicide; The judge trying the theft case in 2014 is about to convict AA. What circumstances affecting the liability or penalty may the judge appreciate against AA? ",
        "Answer": "The judge may appreciate the aggravating circumstance of recidivism. AA is a recidivist because she was previously convicted of theft in 2002, which is a crime embraced in the same title (Title 10) as the present crime of theft. The judge may also appreciate habitual delinquency if AA was convicted of theft or estafa at least twice before within 10 years from release or last conviction. However, frustrated homicide is not among the crimes enumerated for habitual delinquency."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 410,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Multiple offenders - Recidivist TRUE or FALSE. Answer TRUE if the statement is true, or FALSE if the statement is false. Explain your answer in not more than two (2) sentences.  (2009 Bar Question) [a] Amado, convicted of rape but granted an absolute pardon by the President, and one year thereafter, convicted of homicide, is a recidivist.",
        "Answer": "True. Rape is now a crime against persons and, like the crime of homicide, is embraced in the same Title of the Revised Penal Code under which Amado had been previously convicted by final judgment. The absolute pardon granted to Amado did not obliterate the fact of his previous conviction for purposes of recidivism."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 411,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Felonies – Continuing crimes Angelo devised a Ponzi Scheme in which 500 persons were deceived into investing their money upon a promise of a capital return of 25%, computed monthly, and guaranteed by post-dated checks. Angelo issued 500 separate checks to the 500 investors, all of which were dishonored. The investors filed 500 separate complaints for estafa against Angelo. Angelo moved to consolidate the 500 cases into one case, contending that all the 500 acts of estafa constitute a single or continuing crime of estafa. [a] What is delito continuado?  (2009 Bar Question) [b] Is Angelo’s contention tenable? Explain. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "[a] Delito continuado refers to a crime constituted by several overt acts committed by the offender in one place, at about the same time, and all such overt acts violate one and the same provision of penal law, thus demonstrating that all such acts are the product of a single indivisible criminal resolution. [b] No. His contention is not tenable. The 500 acts of estafa do not constitute a single or continuing crime of estafa. Each act of issuing a check to each investor constitutes a separate crime of estafa. The fact that the checks were issued at about the same time and in one place does not make it a continuing crime because each act of estafa is a complete crime in itself, affecting different victims."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 412,
        "Question": "Pedro, Pablito, Juan and Julio, all armed with bolos, robbed the house where Antonio, his wife, and three (3) daughters were residing. During the robbery, Julio raped Antonio’s daughter, aged 15 years old, while the other three malefactors were ransacking the house. (A) What crime or crimes, if any, did Pedro, Pablito, Juan and Julio commit?Explain. (B) Suppose, after the robbery, the four took turns in raping the three daughters inside the house, and, to prevent identification, killed the whole family just before they left. What crime or crimes, if any, did the four malefactors commit?  ",
        "Answer": "(A) Julio is liable for special complex crime of robbery with rape since he raped the daughter of Antonio on occasion or by reason of robbery. Pedro, Pablito and Juan are liable for robbery by band. They cannot be held liable for robbery with rape because they had no participation in the rape committed by Julio. (B) They are liable for a special complex crime of robbery with homicide. The killing of the whole family was done by reason of the robbery. They are also liable for the rape of the three daughters as a separate crime, but it may be complexed with robbery with homicide if the rape was committed on the occasion of the robbery."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 413,
        "Question": "OFW, worked in Kuwait for several years as a chief accountant, religiously sending to his wife, B, 80% of all his earnings. B, in turn, deposited all the remittances in a joint savings account with their son, C, and daughter, D. OFW was able to save P10 million. When OFW returned to the Philippines for good, he discovered that B had an illicit relationship with X, and that B, C and D had already withdrawn and spent all the P10 million savings. OFW confronted B, C and D, who all admitted the withdrawals and the affair. Enraged, OFW killed B, C and D. He then surrendered to the police and confessed to the crime. As the RTC judge, decide what crime or crimes were committed by A, X, Y and Z, and what mitigating and aggravating circumstances will be applied in imposing the penalty. Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "OFW committed three counts of murder qualified by treachery, if the killing was done in a manner that ensured the victims had no chance to defend themselves. The mitigating circumstances of voluntary surrender and confession may be appreciated. The aggravating circumstance of dwelling may be applied if the killing was done in the home of the victims. However, passion and obfuscation may not be considered as a mitigating circumstance because it was not based on a lawful cause (the affair alone may not be sufficient). The penalty should be imposed considering the mitigating and aggravating circumstances."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 414,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Felonies – Special complex crime of rape with homicide Wenceslao and Loretta were staying in the same boarding house, occupying different rooms. One late evening, when everyone in the house was asleep, Wenceslao entered Loretta’s room with the use of a picklock. Then, with force and violence, Wenceslao ravished Loretta. After he had satisfied his lust, Wenceslao stabbed Loretta to death and, before leaving the room, took her jewelry. [a] What crime or crimes, if any, did Wenceslao commit? Explain. (4%) (2009 Bar Question) [c] Would your answer to [a] be the same if, despite the serious stab wounds she sustained, Loretta survived? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "[a] Wenceslao committed the following crimes: (1) the special complex crime of rape with homicide (2) theft and (3) unlawful possession of picklocks and similar tools under Art. 304, RPC. The rape and homicide constitute a special complex crime under Article 266-B, RPC. The theft is a separate crime because it was committed after the rape and homicide. The unlawful possession of picklocks is also a separate crime. [c] No, the answer will be different. If Loretta survived, Wenceslao would be liable for rape and attempted homicide (or frustrated homicide, depending on the gravity of the wounds), and theft. The rape and homicide would not complex into a special complex crime because there was no death."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 415,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Complex crimes - Malversation through falsification Roger and Jessie, Municipal Mayor and Treasurer, respectively, of San Rafael, Leyte, caused the disbursement of public funds allocated for their local development programs for 2008. They accomplished and signed disbursement vouchers and payrolls and made it appear that the funds were used to pay for the labor services of several persons, when in truth no such services were rendered. The Commission on Audit (COA) discovered the anomaly and recommended the filing of charges against Roger and Jessie. The Ombudsman filed against them an information for Malversation through Falsification. Discuss the propriety of the charge filed against Roger and Jessie. Explain. (4%) (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The charge of malversation through falsification is not correct because the falsifications of several documents were not necessary means to obtain the money that were malversed. The malversation was committed through the illegal use of public funds, and the falsification was only to conceal the malversation. Thus, they should be charged with separate crimes of malversation and falsification, or with complex crime if the falsification was a necessary means to commit malversation, which is not the case here."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 416,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Complex crimes - Robbery with homicide; direct assault with multiple attempted homicide While Alfredo, Braulio, Ciriaco, and 'Domingo were robbing a bank, policemen arrived. A firefight ensued between the bank robbers and the responding policemen, and one of the policemen was killed. [a] What crime or crimes, if any, had been committed? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question) [b] Suppose it was Alfredo who was killed by the responding policemen, what charges can be filed against Braulio, Ciriaco and Domingo? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question) [c] Suppose in the course of the robbery, before the policemen arrived, Braulio shot and killed Alfredo following a heated disagreement on who should carry the money bags, what would be the criminal liability of Braulio, Ciriaco and Domingo? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "[a] The crimes committed are Robbery with homicide (Art. 294(1), RPC), a single indivisible offense, and Direct Assault with Multiple Attempted Homicide, a complex crime (Art. 48, Art. 148 and Art. 249, RPC; People v. Gayrama, 60 Phil. 796 (1934)). The killing of the policeman is homicide committed on the occasion of the robbery. The firing at the policemen constitutes direct assault with attempted homicide. [b] The crime of which Braulio, Ciriaco and Domingo can be charged is Robbery with Homicide (Art.294[1], RPC) because the killing resulted by reason or on the occasion, of the robbery. The death of Alfredo, a co-conspirator, does not affect their liability for robbery with homicide. [c] Braulio shall be liable for Robbery with homicide (Art. 294[1], RPC) for killing Alfredo, since the killing was by reason of the robbery. Ciriaco and Domingo shall be liable as co-principals in the robbery with homicide under the principle of conspiracy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 417,
        "Question": "Criminal law – Special complex crimes- Robbery with homicide Christopher, John, Richard, and Luke are fraternity brothers. To protect themselves from rival fraternities, they all carry guns wherever they go. One night, after attending a party, they boarded a taxicab, held the driver at gunpoint and took the latter’s earnings. What crime, if any, did the four commit if they killed the driver? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No, the crime becomes robbery with homicide and all the fraternity brothers are liable. The killing of the driver was committed by reason of the robbery, hence, it is robbery with homicide under Article 294(1) of the Revised Penal Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 418,
        "Question": "Porthos made a sudden turn on a dark street, and his Rolls-Royce SUV bumped the rear of a parked Cadillac Sedan inside which Aramis was then taking a nap. The impact awakened Aramis who, still groggy, alighted and saw Porthos also alighting from his SUV. Thinking that Porthos was about to attack him, Aramis drew his gun and shot Porthos in the chest. Porthos fell and was rushed to the hospital. He survived after a long confinement. (a) What are the kinds of unlawful aggression, and which kind was displayed in this case? Explain your answer.  (b) Standing trial for frustrated murder, Aramis pleaded self- defense. The Prosecution’s contention was that the plea of self- defense applied only to consummated killings. Rule, with explanations, on the tenability of Aramis’ claim of self-defense, and on the Prosecution’s contention.  (c) Porthos insisted that the element of treachery was present. To rule out treachery, Aramis asserted that both he and Porthos were then facing and confronting each other when he fired the shot. Rule, with reasons, on the respective contentions.  (2017 BAR EXAM)",
        "Answer": "(a) Unlawful aggression is of two kinds: (a) actual or material unlawful aggression; and (b) imminent unlawful aggression. Actual unlawful aggression is an attack or assault that is happening or is in progress. Imminent unlawful aggression is an attack that is about to happen. In this case, there is neither actual nor imminent unlawful aggression. Porthos was merely alighting from his vehicle, which does not constitute an attack. (b) The prosecution’s contention is not tenable. Self-defense can be invoked in frustrated or attempted homicide or murder. The stage of the felony does not affect the availability of self-defense. However, Aramis’ claim of self-defense is not tenable because there was no unlawful aggression on the part of Porthos. (c) There is no treachery as the attack was preceded by heated words. Treachery requires that the means of execution give the victim no opportunity to defend himself. Here, since both were facing each other, there was opportunity for defense, so treachery is absent."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 419,
        "Question": "Pedro is married to Tessie. Juan is the first cousin of Tessie, while in the market, Pedro saw a man stabbing Juan. Seeing the attack on Juan, Pedro picked up a spade nearby and hit the attacker on his head which caused the latter’s death. Can Pedro be absolved of the killing on the ground that it is in defense of a relative? Explain.  ",
        "Answer": "No. The relatives of the accused for purpose of defense of relative under Article 11 (2) of the Revised Penal Code are his spouse, ascendants, descendants, or legitimate, natural or adopted brothers or sisters, or of his relatives by affinity in the same degrees, and those by consanguinity within the fourth civil degree. Juan, being the first cousin of Tessie, is within the fourth civil degree by affinity, but the defense of relative requires that the relative being defended must be within the degrees mentioned. However, Juan is not a relative of Pedro by consanguinity or affinity within the covered degrees. First cousins are within the fourth civil degree by consanguinity, but for defense of relative, it includes relatives by affinity only in the same degrees as consanguinity. Since Juan is the cousin of Tessie, he is not a relative of Pedro by affinity within the covered degrees. Thus, Pedro cannot invoke defense of relative."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Criminal Law",
        "No": 420,
        "Question": "Romeo and Julia have been married for twelve (12) years and had two (2) children. Throughout their marriage, Romeo would constantly beat up Julia. One day, after Romeo had beaten her up again, Julia took a kitchen knife and stabbed Romeo to death. Julia was charged with parricide. She asserted 'battered woman’s syndrome' as her defense. (A) Explain the 'cycle of violence.'  (B) is Julia’s 'battered woman’s syndrome' defense meritorious? Explain.",
        "Answer": "(A) The battered woman syndrome is characterized by the so-called 'cycle of violence,' which has three phases: (1) the tension-building phase; (2) the acute battering incident; and (3) the tranquil, loving (or, at least, nonviolent) phase. (B) Yes. Under Section 3 (c) of RA NO. 9262, 'Battered Woman Syndrome' refers to a scientifically defined pattern of psychological and behavioral symptoms found in women living in battering relationships as a result of 'cumulative abuse'. Julia may invoke this defense to justify or mitigate her liability, provided that the syndrome is proven by expert testimony and that the killing occurred during a battering incident."
    }
];